In the previous lecture, we looked at a public key
encryption system that is built from the RSA,
or more generally from trapdoors functions.
In this lecture, we are going to look at public key encryption
schemes that are build from the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
So, first recall that a public key encryption system is
made up of three algorithms. There is a key
generation algorithm that I will denote by Gen,
that basically generates a public key and a
secret key. And then there are two algorithms: E
and D that encrypt and decrypt. And the point is
the encryption algorithm encrypts using the
public key and the decryption algorithm decrypts
using the secret key. The physical world analogy for
public key encryption is a locked box, where anyone
can put a message inside the box and then lock the
box, that corresponds to the public key and then
no one can open this box, except the person who has
the secret key, that has the key can put it in the
lock, unlock the box and the recover the message in
the box. Now, in the previous lecture, we looked at
a number of applications for public key encryption.
In particular, we looked at the key exchange
application, in fact, this is how public key encryption
is used in SSL, where the server sends its public
key to the browser, the browser chooses a secret
and then encrypts the secret using the server's
public key, sends it back to the server, the
server decrypts and now both the browser and the
server have a common secret that they can then
use to encrypt data, going back and forth, between
them. So, in the interactive settings, such as in a
networking protocol, public key encryption would
primarily be used for setting up shared symmetric key
which the two parties can then use to exchange
information. However, there are many settings
where interaction is simply not possible and then
public key encryption is directly used to encrypt
messages. One example of this is secure email.
The email system in some sense is designed to be non-
interactive, in the sense that the sender sends an
email, the email travels from relay to relay, to
relay, until it finally arrives at the destination
and the destination should be able to decrypt,
without interacting with the sender at that point.
That can be done basically, by the sender
encrypting the message using the recipient's public
key. The ciphertext would travel along the SMTP chain
until it reaches the recipient. The recipient would
use a secret key and recover the original sent
message. However, there are many other cases
where interaction is not possible and I want to show
you two such cases. The first example is
file systems. And in fact, public key encryption is a
good way to manage file sharing, in an encrypted file
system. So, let me show you what I mean
by that. So, imagine we have our friend Bob
here, who wants to store an encrypted file on some
storage server. So, he will go ahead and write the
encrypted file to the storage server. What he
actually writes in the server is basically the
following: he will generate a random file encryption key, we
will call it 'K sub F' and then he will use the
symmetric encryption system to encrypt the file
using the key 'K sub F'. Then, he will encrypt the
key 'K sub F', using his own public key. So public key
of Bob. This will give Bob access to the file at a later
time, right. Using his secret key, Bob can decrypt
this header, recover 'K sub F'. Then he will
decrypt the actual encrypted file and recover the
plaintext file. So, decryption will work in two steps.
However, Bob now wants also to give access to
Alice, to this file. What he will do is, he will go
ahead and in addition he will also include in the
file header, an encyption of 'K sub F' under Alice's
public key. OK. So, notice that there was no
interaction here. All that Bob knows is Alice's public
key and yet he was able to the make the file
accesible to Alice at a later time.
So, now Bob disappears and then Alice
comes and accesses the disk at a later time.
She will read the ciphertext, decrypt  her part of
the header, recover Kf and then she can decrypt
the symmetrically encrypted file and recover the
actual file contents. Ok, so you can see that without
any interaction, Bob was able to write to the file
system and enable Alice to access the file, as well.
Again, at the time that Alice was reading the file, there is no
interaction with Bob, because maybe Bob is already
inaccesible and yet Alice can still read the file
recovered by herself.
So, another example of a non-interactive
application of public key encryption is what's called
key escrow. Now, key escrow may actually sound
like a bad thing but in fact it is a mandatory
feature in corporate environments. So, the idea
here is this. So imagine Bob writes data to a
disk and then later Bob becomes inaccesible.
Maybe Bob is fired. Maybe Bob is out sick.
And somehow the company needs to have access to
Bob's files. So having Bob be the only one
able to decrypt these files is simply unacceptable in
corporate settings. The corporation might need
access to those files. So, the question is what to do.
And the answer is to introduce this entity called
a key escrow service. The way the system then
would work is as follows:
Basically, when Bob writes his file to disk, his
system, as it's writing the file to this shared
storage medium, what it would do of course, as before,
it would encrypt the file using the file encryption key Kf.
It would encrypt Kf using Bob's public key, but it would
also encrypt Kf using an escrow service. So here,
the escrow service is completely offline. We never
talk to it unless we actually need its services.
As Bob is writing the file, all he does is he simply writes
the encryption of Kf under the escrow authority's
public key into the file header. Now, later Bob
disappears and now the company needs to recover
Bob's file. What does it do? Well, at this point it would
contact the escrow service. The escrow service
would read this part of the header, use its secret
key to decrypt the header and recover Kf and then use Kf
to decrypt the actual file.
Ok. So, in this way again you notice that  the escrow service was
completely offline. There was no interaction with the
escrow service until the point at which the escrow
services were actually needed. And again, you can
see that this is a very clean and elegant application
of public key encryption. So, as I said in the
previous lecture, we saw constructions for public
key encryption based on trapdoor functions.
In particular, we look at RSA. We looked at the
generic construction we called ISO standard.
We looked at constructions like OAEP+ and so on and so forth.
In this lecture, we are going to look at public key
constructions from the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
This is another family of public key systems and
I am going to show you how they work. These public
key systems are generally called ElGamal public key
encryption schemes. Taher ElGamal was actually Marty
Hellman's student. He came up with this ElGamal
encryption system as part of his PhD thesis.
And, in fact, ElGamal encryption, for historical
reasons, is used in an email encryption system called GPG,
the GNU Privacy Guard. As usual, when we
construct public key encryption systems, our goal is
to build systems that have chosen ciphertext security,
so that they are secure both against eavesdropping
and tampering attacks. So, before I show you the ElGamal
system let's do a very brief review of the Diffie-Hellman
protocol. So, in my description here, I am going
to abstract a little bit from the version that we saw last
week. In fact, I just going to use the concept
of a finite cyclic group. In fact, we have an arbitrary finite
cyclic group, for example, it could be the group (Zp) star,
but it could also be the points of an elliptic curve.
And as I mentioned, there are some benefits to doing
Diffie-Hellman over an elliptic curve. But, for simplicity,
I am just going to refer to G as an abstract finite
cyclic group, but in your heads you should be
thinking G is the group (Zp) and let's suppose
that the group has order n for some integer n.
Now, we are going to fix a generator g of this group
and all this means, is basically, if you look at the
successive powers of g, that basically you get
all the elements in the group G. You notice,
because the group has order n, we know that
g to the power of n is equal to 1. And, therefore
there is no reason to go beyond the n-1st power
of g. g to the n is equal to 1 so that we just wrap around.
Ok. So, we have this cyclic group G. We have this
generator whose powers gave us all the elements of
G, and now let me remind you how the Diffie-Hellman
protocol works. Basically, what Alice does is she  chooses a
random a. She computes g to the a and sends it
over to Bob. Bob chooses a random b. Let's see who
remembers. What does Bob send over to Alice?
So, Bob sends over to Alice g to the b and of
course I should remind you that both g to the a and
g to the b are just elements in this group G. Now,
they can derive the shared secret, If you remember,
the shared secret is g to the ab, and these equalities
here shows that both sides can actually compute
the shared secret given the values at their disposal.
So, Alice for example, has B and she has a, and
so raising B to the power of a, gives her the shared
secret. The attacker, of course, the poor attacker
he gets to see A and B and his goal is now,
of course, he also gets to see the generated g, and
his goal now is to compute g to the ab. But, we said that
this is believed to be a hard problem. Given g, g to the a,
and g to the b, in a group like  Zp, computing g to
the ab is difficult. So, now let's see how to convert to
the Diffie-Hellman protocol into an actual public key
system. As I said, this was a brilliant idea due to
Taher ElGamal. So, as before, we are going to fix our
cyclic group G and a generator g inside of G.
Now, here I wrote the Diffie-Hellman protocol again,
except now we are going to assume that these guys
are separated in time. These two steps do not have
to occur simultaneously; they could actually take place
at quite different times. The first step of the Diffie-Hellman
protocol is what we are going to view as key
generation. That is the public key is going to be
this capital A  and the secret key is simply going to
be the little a. So, you notice of course that
extracting the secret key from the public key,
namely extracting the little a from capital A is a
discrete log problem. So, that recovering a secret
key is actually difficult. Ok, now this gives us our public key.
So, now at a later time Bob wants to encrypt a
message to Alice, encrypted using her public key.
So how does Bob encrypt? Well, what he is going to do is
he's going to compute his contribution to the Diffie-Hellman
protocol. Namely, he is going to send over g to the
little b. Of course, he is going to choose this little b
at random and now he is going to compute by
himself the shared secret. So, he is going to
compute by himself g to the ab. From this g to the ab
he is going to derive a symmetric key for a
symmetric encryption system and then he is going to
encrypt the message m using this symmetric key
that he just derived. And that is the pair he is going to
send. So, he is going to send over his contribution
to the Diffie-Hellman protocol plus the symmetric
encryption of the message m that he wants to send
over to Alice. Ok, so you can see basically, we are
doing the exact same thing as we would do in the Diffie-Hellman
protocol except now we, Bob directly immediately is using
his Diffie-Hellman secret to encrypt the message  that he
wants to send over to Alice.
Now, what does Alice do to decrypt?
Basically, she is going also to compute the
Diffie-Hellman secret. Remember, that now she just
received Bob's contribution to the Diffie-Hellman
protocol and she has her secret key a. So, she can
compute also the Diffie-Hellman secret, namely
g to the ab, from which she is going to derive the
symmetric encryption key k. And then, she is going
to decrypt the message to recover the actual
plaintext. Ok, so that is the intuition for how we
convert the Diffie-Hellman protocol into a public key
system. By the way, this was kind of an interesting
development at the time that it came out,  partially
because, you notice this is a randomized encryption scheme.
So, every time Bob encrypts a message, it is
required that he choose a new random b and
encrypt the message using this new random b.
So, let's see the ElGamal system,  actually in more
detail. So, now actually let's  view it as an actual
public key encryption system. Namely, algorithm Gen,
algorithm E and algorithm D.
So, as usual, we are going to fix our finite cyclic
group of order n. Another ingredient that we are going
to need is a symmetric encryption system. So, I am
going to refer to it as E sub s, and D sub s. These are the
encryption and decryption algorithms of a symmetric
encryption system that happens to provide
authenticated encryption. And, the key space for
this system is capital K. And, then we are also going
to need a hash function that maps pairs of elements
in the group, namely elements in G squared into
the key space. Now, here is how the public key
encryption system works. So, I have to describe
three algorithms. Algorithm that generates the
public key and the secret key, and then the  encryption
and decryption algorithms. So, the key generation
algorithm works as follows: All we do is basically,
build up Alice's contribution to the Diffie-Hellman
protocol. What we are going to do is going to choose a
random generator g in G and then we are going to
choose a random exponent a. The secret key is
going to be a and then the public key is going to be
the generator g and Alice's contribution to the
Diffie-Hellman protocol. The reason, by the way,
we don't use a fix generator, is because it
allows us to somewhat use a weaker assumption,
improving security. And, so it is actually better to
choose a random generator every time. It is easy
enough to choose a random generator. All we do, is we
take the generator that we started with and then we
raise it to some power that is relatively prime to n.
That will give us another generator. A random
generator of the group capital G. Ok. So, you can
see here that again the public key is simply Alice's
contribution to the Diffie-Hellman protocol. And, the
secret key is the random a that she chose. Now, how
do we encrypt and decrypt? Well, when Bob wants
to encrypt the message, he is going to use the
public key. Remember, it consists of  g and h.
Here, he wants to encrypt a message m.
So, here is what he is going to do. So, he is going
to choose his contribution to the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
So, this is the secret b that he would normally
choose in Diffie-Hellman. And, now he is going to
compute g to the b, which is actually his message,
that gets send to Alice in the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
He is going to compute the Diffie-Hellman secret,
that's h to the b. If you remember, h was g to the a,
therefore, this value here is really g to the ab.
That's the Diffie-Hellman secret. That is the one thing that
the attacker doesn't actually know. Next, he is going
to compute a symmetric key by basically hashing
this pair u comma v. So, u, of course, is something
that the attacker is going to know because that is
going to be sent as part of the ciphertext. But v, the
attacker isn't going to know. Again, for the proof of
security, actually it helps to hash both u and v. So, we
hash both of them together. Although, strictly speaking
we just needed to hash v, because v is the only value
that the attacker doesn't know. The attacker
already knows u, because that's going to be part of the data
that's sent on the network. So, anyhow, so Bob derives
this symmetric key k, by hashing u and v. Then, he
goes ahead and encrypts the message using the
symmetric key k and finally he outputs his
contribution to the Diffie-Hellman protocol.
The value u and then the symmetric ciphertext that
directly encrypts the message m.
That's it. So, the ciphertext consists of these two
parts and that is the thing that gets sent over the
network. Let's see, how does Alice decrypt now.
So, she is going to use her secret key a to decrypt
and she receives here, Bob's contribution to the
Diffie-Hellman protocol plus the symmetric
encryption of the message that Bob sent.
What she will do is she'll compute herself the Diffie-Hellman
secret. If you remember, u to the a is simply g to the b
to the a. Which is g to the ab. So, here Alice
computed the Diffie-Hellman secret. And, now let me
ask you, how does she derive the symmetric key k
given the Diffie-Hellman secret, g to the ab and the
ciphertext that she was given?
Well, what she will do, is simply again, now she has
u from the ciphertext and she has v, because she just
computed it herself. So, now she can rederive the
symmetric encryption key  by hashing u and v
together to get the symmetric encryption key and
then she just decrypts the ciphertext to get the
actual plaintext. OK, so that's it. That is the whole
encryption and decryption algorithm. In a picture,
the way the ciphertext would look, is also
as kind of what we saw in the last lecture. Basically,
there would be a short header that contains u.
Which as you recall, is g to the b. And, then the rest of the
ciphertext would be the encryption of the message
that is being sent, under the symmetric key k.
And, then to decrypt, Alice would use this header
to derive the Diffie-Hellman secret from which she
will derive k and then decrypts the body, to get the
original plaintext. By the way, I should note that
the way I describe this system here, is actually not
how ElGamal described it originally, this is
in some sense a modern view about the ElGamal
encryption, but it is pretty much equivalent to how
ElGamal viewed it. So, now let's look at the
performance of ElGamal. So, here what I wrote
is the, kind of the time intensive steps of  ElGamal
encryption. Namely, during encryption, there are
these two exponentiations in the group G.
Exponentiation, remember is a cubic time algorithm
using the repeated squaring algorithm. And, as a
result, it is fairly time intensive. When I say, time
intensive, I mean, that on a modern processor it would
take a few milliseconds to compute these
exponentiations and during decryption, basically,
the decryptor computes one exponentiation,
namely, u to the a. This is the bottleneck during
decryption. Ok, so you would think that encryption
actually is, takes twice as long as decryption, because
encryption requires two exponentiations, while
decryption requires only one. It turns out, that
is not entirely accurate because, you notice that the exponentiation
during decryption is done to a variable basis.
Namely, u changes every time. Whereas during
encryption, the basis is fixed: g and h are derived
from the public key and are fixed forever.
So, in fact, in turns out that if you want to do
exponentiation to a fixed basis, you can do a lot of
precomputation. In particular, you can do all the
squaring steps in the repeated squaring algorithm
offline. So, here what you would do, you would
compute all powers of 2 of g. So, you would
compute g, g squared, g to the fourth, g to the
eighth, go to the sixteenth, g to the thirty two, and so
on and so forth. These are all the squaring steps of
the repeated squaring algorithm you would do offline.
The same thing for h. And, then when it comes time to
actually do the real exponentiation all you need to do is just do the
multiplications, to accumulate these powers of 2 into the
exponent b, that you're trying to compute.
So, if you think about it, this can actually speed up
exponentiation by a factor of 3. In fact, it would
speed up it even more if you allow me to store even
larger tables. This is called a windowed exponentiation.
But, regardless, if you allow the encryptor to
store large tables that are derived from the public
key, then in fact encryption is not going to be
slower than decryption. In fact, encryption will be
faster than decryption. But, again, this requires that
the encryptor to precompute these large tables
and store them around. So, if all the encryptor is
doing, is just constantly encrypting to a single
recipient, that can be done actually fairly fast using these
precomputed tables. If the encryptor, for every
message is encrypting to a different recipient, for
example, if every time you send an email, you send
an email to a different recipient, then, in fact, the
encryption will be twice as slow as decryption.
So, this is a good trick to keep in mind. In fact, most
cryptolibraries don't do this. So, if you see that you
are always encrypting to the same public key and
for some reason your encryption process takes a
lot of time, it's a bottleneck for you, keep in mind
that you can actually really speed things up
using precomputation.
Of couse, if encryption is a bottleneck for you, you
might as well be using RSA, where an RSA encryption
is really fast. Ok, so that is the end of our
description of ElGamal encryption. Now, the next
question of course, is why is the system secure,
in particular, can we prove that it's chosen
ciphertext secure and more importantly, under what
assumptions can we prove that the system is
chosen ciphertext secure? So, we are going to
discuss that in the next segment.