In this segment we are gonna look at
another form of encryption called
tweakable encryption. I'm gonna motivate
tweakable encryption using disk encryption
as an application and we'll see disk
encryption as yet another application for
deterministic encryption. So the disk
encryption problem is that we wanna
encrypt sectors on disk. Say each sector
is four kilobytes long and the problem is
that there is no space to expand. In other
words if the sector size is four kilobytes
the cipher text size also has to be
exactly four kilobyte because there is
nowhere to write the extra bits if the
cipher text was bigger than the plaintext.
And so our goal is basically to build a
non expanding encryption where the cipher
text size is identical exactly equal to
the plaintext size. So what does it mean
that encryption can't expand? Well,
technically we were saying, basically the
message space is equal to the cipher text
space. So the message space will be four
kilobyte messages and the cipher text
space would be also four kilobyte
messages. In this case clearly we have to
use deterministic encryption because if
encryption was randomized there will be no
place to store the randomness. And similarly
we have no room for integrity, because we can't
expand the cipher text and add any
integrity bits. So the most we can achieve
is deterministic CPA security and that's
going to be our goal. Now it turns out
there's a really simple lemma to
prove, that basically says if you give me
a deterministically CPA secure cipher
where the message space is equal to the
cipher text space, so no expansion, then in
fact the cipher is a PRP. So, really all
we're saying here is if we want no
expansion at all our only option for
encrypting is what we called construction
number two in the previous segment. Namely
we have to encrypt using a PRP. So, let's
look at how we might encrypt using a
PRP. Well, we take our disk, and we break
it into sectors. And now, if we encrypted
every sector using a PRP under the same
key, we kind of run into our standard
problem with deterministic encryption.
Namely, if sector one and sector three
happen to have the same plain text, then
the encrypted sector one would be equal to
the encrypted sector three and the
attacker would learn that the
corresponding plain texts are the same.
Now this actually is a real problem for
example, if your, if some of your sectors
are empty you know they are all set to
zero then in fact the encrypted sectors
would be identical and as a result the
attacked would know exactly which sectors
on your disk are empty and which sectors
are not. So this is actually quite
problematic and the question is, can we do
any better? And so the answer is yes, and
the first idea that comes to mind is well,
why don't we use a different key for every
sector? So you can see sector number one
gets encrypted with key one, sector number
two gets encrypted with key two and so on
and so forth. So now even if the content
of sector number one is equal to sector
number three the cipher text of sector one
and sector three will be different because
they are encrypted under different keys.
So this actually avoids the leakage that
we talked about before although I do want
to point out that there is still a little
bit of leakage with this mode. For example
if the user happened to change one bit in
sector one and then that sector gets
encrypted into a different cipher text. So
this will be garbled all completely,
because this is a pseudo random
permutation, the sector will be-- even if
one bit of the plain text changes, the
sector will be just mapped to a completely
new random output. However, if the user
then undoes the change, and reverts back
to the original sector, then the encrypted
sector will revert back to its original
state, and the attacker can tell that a
change was made and then reverted. So,
there's still a little bit of
information leakage. But that type of
information leakage, there's really
nothing we can do without really
sacrificing performance. So, we're just
going to ignore that and deem that
acceptable. So the next question is now
you realize our disks are actually getting
pretty big and there are lots of sectors.
So this would mean that we are generating
lots and lots of keys here, but of course
we don't have to store all these keys, we
can simply generate these keys using a
pseudo random function. So, the way this
would work is we would have a master key
which we would call K. And then the sector
number which I'm gonna denote by T is
gonna be encrypted using the master key.
And the result of that encryption would be
the particular sector key, which I'll
denote by K sub T. Now the reason this is
secured is again because the PRF is
indistinguishable from our random
function, which means that basically if we
apply a random function to these sector
numbers, one, two, three, four, up to L,
they basically get mapped to completely
random elements in the key space and as a
result we are encrypting every sector
using a new random independent key. So
this is a fine construction, however
again, for every sector we would have to
apply this PRF. And so the natural
question is, can we do even better? And it
turns out we can. And this introduces this
concept of a tweakable block cipher where
really what we want is basically to have
one master key. And we want this one
master key to derive many, many,
many PRPs. So we said one way to do that
is simply encrypt the key K using the PRP
number. But as we'll see, there's a more
efficient way to do that. Now this PRP
number is actually what's called a tweak,
and that introduces this concept of
tweakable, a tweakable block cipher. So in
a tweakable block cipher, the encryption
and decryption algorithm basically, as
usual, take a key as input, they take a
tweak as input. This capital T is what's
called the tweak space. And of course they
take the data as input and they output
data in the set X. The property is such that for
every tweak in a tweak space in a random
key. Basically if we fix the key and the
tweak, then we end up with an invertible
function, a one to one function on the
set X. And because the key is random with
the, the function is in fact
indistinguishable from random. In other
words, for every setting of the tweak, we
basically get a PRP, an independent PRP
from X to X. And as I said, the
application for this is now we're going to
use the sector number as the tweak, and as
a result, every sector is going to get its
own independent PRP. So let me very, very
quickly just define more precisely what is
a secure tweakable block cipher. So as we
said there's a tweak space. There's a key,
a tweak space and an [inaudible] space X.
And as usual, we define our two
experiments. Here in experiment one what's
gonna happen is we are gonna choose a
truly random set of permutations. So not
just one permutation we're gonna choose as
many permutations as there are tweaks. So
you notice this is why we raise this to the
size of the tweak space. If the size of
the tweak space is five, this says we are
choosing five random permutations on the
set X. And in the other case, basically,
we're just gonna, you know, choose a
random key, and we're gonna define our set
of permutations as the ones defined by
the, by tweaks in the tweak space. And
then the adversary basically gets to
submit a tweak and an X. And he gets to
see the value of the permutation defined
by the tweak T1, evaluated at the point
X1. And he gets to see this again and
again. And again, he gets to see the value
of the permutation defined by the tweak
T2, evaluated at the point X2, and so on
and so forth. And then his goal is to say
whether he interacted with truly random
permutations, or pseudo random
permutations. And if he can't do it, we
say that this tweakable block cipher is
secure. So the difference from a regular
block cipher, is, in a regular block
cipher, you only get to interact with one
permutation. And then your goal is to tell
whether you're interacting with a
pseudorandom permutation or a truly random
permutation. Here you get to interact with
T random permutations. And again your goal
is to tell whether the T random
permutations are truly random or
pseudorandom. So as usual if you can't
distinguish, if the adversary behaves the
same in both experiments, we say that this
PRP is a secure tweakable PRP. Okay. Very
good. So let's look at some examples. So
we already looked at, at the trivial
example. In the trivial example, what we do,
we just, we're gonna assume that the key
space is equal to the input space. So this
PRP really acts on, you know, X times X to
X. So think of AES for example, where
the key space is 128 bits, the data space
is 128 bits and of course the output is
128 bits and then the way that we defined a
tweakable block cipher again there is a
key, a tweak and data as input is
basically we encrypt the tweak using our
master key and then we encrypt the data
using the resulting random key. Now
you realize that if we wanted to encrypt n
blocks with this tweakable block cipher,
this would require 2n evaluations of
the block cipher: n evaluations to encrypt
the given tweaks, and then n more evaluations
to encrypt the actual given data.
So, I want to show you a nice example,
that shows that we can actually do better.
This is called the XTS construction.
It's actually originally based on
a mode called XEX due to Phil Rogaway.
And it works as follows. So suppose you
give me a, a regular block cipher that
operates on n-bit blocks. So not a
tweakable block cipher, just a regular
block cipher. We're gonna define a
tweakable block cipher. So again, this
tweakable block cipher is gonna take two
keys as input. The tweak space, for
convenience, which you're gonna see in
just a minute, we're gonna assume this
tweak space is made up of, of two values,
T and I. T is going to be some, you know, some
tweak value which we'll see in a minute, and I is
going to be some index. And then X is
going to be an n-bit string which we're
going to apply the tweakable block cipher
to. So, the way XTS works is as follows.
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to encrypt the left half of the
tweak, namely T, using the key K2 and we're
going to call the result N. So now what
we're gonna do is we're gonna XOR the
message m with some padding function
applied to this value N that we just
derived, at the index I. And this padding
function is extremely fast. We can pretty
much ignore it in the running time. The
next thing we do is we're gonna encrypt
using the key k2. And then we're going
to XOR again, using the same pad. So
we're going to XOR again using the pad
of N applied to I. And the result is going
to be the cipher text, which we'll denote
by C. Okay, so again as I said, the
function P is some very, very simple
function. It's just some multiplication in
a finite field which I'm not going to
explain here. Very, very fast so the
running time is dominated by the running
time of the block cipher E and that's it. That's
XTS. And the nice thing about this construction
is now if we wanted to encrypt n plus one
blocks, all we do is we compute the value
N once. And then for the indices one, two,
three, four basically we just need to
evaluate the PRP E once per block. So we
would need to encrypt n blocks using the
tweaks T,1, T,2, T,3, T,4 and so on. We
would just need n plus one evaluations of
the block cipher E. So it's twice
as fast as the trivial construction.
So I want you to stare for just a minute
at this XTS construction. So my question
to you is, is it really necessary to
encrypt the tweak before using it?
That is, that is the following construction
a secure tweakable PRP. So you can see
in this construction, this tweak is used
directly as input to the padding function
for the XOR and my question to you is
if we did that, would that be a
secure tweakable PRP? And let me
remind you again that, this is the key,
this is the tweak and this is the data.
I hope everybody said that this is the correct answer.
Basically, if we set the data to
be P(t, 1), then when we XOR it with the
corresponding tweak, which is also P(t,1)
we're gonna get here, zero. And so
what's gonna get encrypted is actually
zero, so whatever that comes out to be.
Let's say that some value, C0. And
then the actual output is just gonna be C0
XOR P(t,1). Now when we do the same
thing with P(t, 2), we're gonna get c0
XOR P(t, 2). And when we XOR these two
things together, we just get P(t, 1) XOR P(t, 2).
So the fact that this is true means
that an attacker can simply query the
challenger at this tweak and this data,
this tweak and that data. And then just
compute the XOR of the two responses, and
compare to the XOR of the appropriate
padding values. And if the equality holds,
we're interacting with a pseudorandom
function; otherwise we're interacting with
a, with a truly random function. So this
would allow the attacker to defeat this
construction with advantage one. So just
to summarize the way XTS is used for disk
encryption. What we do is we look at
sector number T, and we break it into
blocks, sixteen byte blocks. And then
block number one gets encrypted with a
tweak, T1. Block number two gets encrypted
with a tweak, T2, and so on and so forth.
And so every block gets its own PRP. And
the whole sector, as a result, is
encrypted, using, you know, a collection
of PRPs. Now you notice, this is a block
level PRP. It's not a sector level PRP.
So, in fact, it's not true that each
sector gets encrypted with its own PRP.
It's just each block gets encrypted with
its own PRP. The distinction between a
sector and a block is some, somewhat
artificial, and this XTS mode actually
provides you know, deterministic CPA
encryption at the block level, at the
16-byte level. That's the goal. And this
mode actually is fairly popular in disk
encryption products. I just wrote a couple
of examples here that actually support
XTS. So I wanted you to know that this is
in fact how disk encryption is commonly
done in practice. So, to summarize,
tweakable encryption is a useful concept
to know when you need many independent
PRPs all derived from a single key. One
important thing to remember is, in fact,
the trivial construction is not the most
efficient. There are constructions like
XTS are actually more efficient, where you
can kind of reuse encryptions from one
tweak to get many encryptions for many
different tweaks. And so those are the
better ways to use them. Both the trivial
construction and the XTS construction are
what are called narrow block constructions.
Namely they provide a tweakable block
ciphers for a sixteen byte block. But as we
said, we looked the, at the EME
construction in the last segment, which
provided a PRP for larger, much larger
blocks and in fact EME is a tweakable
mode of operation. So, if you need PRPs for larger
blocks or tweakable PRPs for larger
blocks then you would just use EME. But you
notice there, in EME, you had to apply the
block cipher twice per input block, and
as a result it's twice as slow as
XTS, and is not very often used. So that's
what I wanted to say about tweakable
encryption. And in the next segment we'll
talk about format preserving encryption.