Now that we understand what is
deterministic encryption, let's see some
constructions that provide security
against deterministic chosen plaintext
attacks. So, first let me remind you that
the deterministic encryption is needed,
for example, when encrypting a data base
index and later we wanna look up records
using the encrypted index. Because the
encryption is deterministic we're
guaranteed that when we do the lookup the
encrypted index is gonna be identical to the
encrypted index that was sent to the
database when the record was written to
the database. And so, this deterministic
encryption allows us a very simple or fast
way to do lookups based on encrypted
indices. The problem was that we said the
deterministic encryption can't possibility
be secure against a general chosen
plaintext attack because if the attacker
sees two cipher texts that are equal
it learns that the underlying encrypted
messages are the same. So, then we defined
this concept of deterministic chosen plain
text security which means that we have
security as long as the encryptor never
encrypts the same message more than once
using a given key. In particular, this
key, message pair is only used once, for
every encryption, either the key changes,
or the message changes. And then as I
said, formally we define this CPA,
deterministic CPA security game, and our
goal in this segment is to actually give
constructions that are deterministic CPA
secure. So the first construction we're
gonna look at is what's called SIV,
synthetic IV's. And the way this
construction works is as follows. Imagine
we have a general CPA secure encryption
system. So here's the key and here's the
message and we are gonna denote by R the
randomness that's used by the encryption
algorithm. Remember that a CPA secure
system that doesn't use nonsense has to be
randomized and so we're explicitly gonna
write down this variable R to denote the
random string that's used by the
encryption algorithm as it's doing the
encryption. For example if we're using
randomized counter mode, r would be the
random IV that's used by randomized counter
mode. And of course C is the resulting
ciphertext. Now, in addition, we're also
going to need a pseudo random function, f,
that what it does, is it takes our
arbitrary messages in the message space
and outputs a strings, R, that can be used
as randomness for the CPA secure
encryption scheme. So, the little, r, over
here is actually a member of the big R set. Okay.
And we're going to assume this is a, f is
a pseudo random function that maps messages
to random strings. Now the way SIV works
is as follows. It's going to use two keys
K1 and K2 to encrypt the message M. And
what it does, is the first thing is going
to apply the pseudo random function f to
the message M to derive randomness for the
CPA secure encryption scheme E. And then
it's going to encrypt the message M using
the randomness that it just derived. This
is going to give us a cipher text C and
then it's going to output this cipher text
C Okay. So that's how this SIV mode works.
Basically it first derives the randomness
from the message being encrypted, and then
it uses this derived randomness to
actually encrypt the message to obtain the
cipher text. Now I'd like to point out for
example, if the encryption scheme E
happened to be randomized counter mode.
Then the randomness R would just be the
random IV which would actually be output
along with the cipher text. So this means
that the cipher text is a little bit
longer than the plain text. But the point
here isn't to generate a short cipher
text. Rather the point here is to make
sure that the encryption scheme is
deterministic, so if we encrypt the same
message multiple times, every time we
should obtain the same cipher text. And
indeed every time, we'll obtain the same
randomness, R, and as a result, every time
we'll obtain the same cipher text C. So
it's fairly easy to show that this
encryption scheme really is semantically
secure under the deterministic chosen
plaintext attack. The reason that's so
is because we apply the pseudo random
function F to distinct messages. Well if
we apply F to distinct messages then the
random string that F generates is going to
look like just truly random strings. A
different random string for every message.
And as a result the CPA secure encryption
scheme E is always applied using truly
random strings. And that's exactly the
situation where it is CPA secure. So
because these R's are just random
indistinguishable from brand new strings,
the resulting system is in fact gonna be
CPA secure. So this is just the intuition
for why this works and it's actually
fairly straightforward to actually
formalize this into a complete proof. Now,
I should emphasize that this is actually
well suited for messages that are more
than one AES block. In fact, for short
messages, we're gonna see a slightly
different encryption scheme that's
actually better suited for these short
messages. Okay, now the really cool thing
about SIV is that, actually, we get cipher
text integrity for free. In fact we don't
have to use a special Mac if we want to
add integrity. In a sense SIV already has
a built in integrity mechanism. And let me
explain what I mean by that. First of all,
our goal was to build what's called
deterministic authenticated encryption.
Dae. Deterministic Authenticated
Encryption. Which basically means that
deterministic CPA security and cipher text
integrity. Remember cipher text integrity
means that the attacker gets to ask for
the encryptions of messages of his choice
and then he shouldn't be able to produce
another cipher text that decrypts to a
valid message. Okay, so I want to claim
that in fact SIV automatically gives a
cipher text integrity without the need for
an embedded MAC or anything else. So let's
see why. In particular, let's look at a
special case of SIV when the underlying
encryption scheme is randomized counter
mode. Okay, so we'll call this SIV-CTR
again to denote SIV where we're using
randomized counter mode. Alright. So let
me remind you again how SIV works in this
case. Well, so we take our message, here,
we take our message, and then we apply a
PRF to it. And that derives an IV. And
then that IV is going to be used to
encrypt the message using randomized
counter mode. Okay. So in particular,
we're gonna use this PRF FTCRr for F
counter, for randomized counter mode and
essentially evaluate this FCTR at Iv, IV
plus one up to IV plus L. And, then, we
had sorta that with the message. And that
gives us the final ciphertext. Okay. So,
this is SIV with a randomized counter
mode. Now, let's see how decryption is
gonna work. And during decryption we're
gonna add one more check, and that's
going to provide ciphertext integrity. So let's see
how decryption is going to work. So here
we have our input cipher text that
contains the IV and the cipher text. Well,
the first thing we're going to do is we're
going to decrypt the cipher text using the
given IV, and that will give us candidate
plain text. Now we're gonna reapply the
PRF F from the definition of SIV to this
message. Now if a message is valid, we
should be getting the same IV that the
[adversary??] supplied as part of the cipher
text. If we get a different IV, then we
know that this message is not a valid
message and we simply reject the cipher
text. So this is really cute. It's a very
simple kinda built in check to make sure
that the cipher text is valid, right. We
simply check that after decryption if
we re-derive the IV we would actually get
the correct IV. And if not we reject the
message. And I claim that this simple check
during decryption is enough to [actually??] provide
ciphertext integrity. And therefore,
deterministic authenticated encryption. So
I'll state this in a simple theorem.
Basically to say, that if F is a secure
PRF, and in counter mode that's derived
from FCTR is CPA secure, then the result
is in fact a deterministic authenticated
encryption system. Now the proof for this
is not too difficult. In two sentences,
let me just show you the rough intuition
for why this is true. So, all we have to
argue is just cipher text integrity. So we
already argued before that the system has
deterministic CPA security, all we have to
argue is just cipher text integrity. So to
argue that the system has cipher text
integrity, let's think again how the
cipher text integrity game works.
Adversary asks for the encryption of a
bunch of messages of his choice. And he
gets the resulting cipher text. Then, his
goal is to produce a new valid cipher
text. Well, if that valid cipher text upon
decryption, decrypts to some completely
new message. Then when we plug this new
message into the PRF F, we're just going to
get some random IV and it's very unlikely
to hit the IV that the adversary supplied
in the cipher text that he output. So
therefore that says that when the advisory
outputs his forged cipher text, the
message in that forged cipher text
basically should be equal to one of the
messages in his chosen message queries.
Otherwise, again the IV that you get is
simply not gonna be equal to the IV in the
forged safe index with very high
probability. But if the message is equal
to one of the messages that the adversary
queried us on, well then, the cipher text
that we're gonna get is also gonna be
equal to one of the cipher texts that we
supplied to the adversary. But then his
forgery is simply one of the cipher texts
that we gave to him. And therefore, this
is not a valid forgery. He has to give us
a new cipher text to win the cipher text
integrity game. But he gave us one of our
old cipher texts. So, this is the rough
intuition. I hope, I kinda went through it
quickly. I hope it kinda makes sense. If
it doesn't then it's not the end of the
world. I'm gonna reference the paper that
describes SIV at the end of the module.
And if you wanna see this in more detail
you can read and take a look inside of
that paper. But, regardless, this is a
very cute idea that I wanted to show you
where kinda the fact that we derive the
randomness for deterministic counter mode
using a PRF. Also, gives us an integrity
check when we actually do the decryption.
Okay. So this SIV is a good mode for doing
deterministic encryption when you need to,
particularly if the messages are long. If
the messages are very short, say they're
less than sixteen bytes, in fact there's a
better way to do it, and that's the method
that I wanna show you now. So the second
construction is actually trivial. All
we're gonna do is we're gonna use a PRP
directly. So here's what we do. So suppose
(E, D) is a secure PRP. So E will encrypt, and
D will decrypt. And I claim that if we use
E directly, that already gives us
deterministic CPA security. So let me show you very quickly why. So suppose F is
a truly random invertible function from X
to X. Okay. So remember a PRP is
indistinguishable from a truly random
invertible function, so let's pretend that
we actually do have a truly random
invertible function. Now in experiment
zero what the attacker is gonna see while
he submits a bunch of messages, you know
the messages on the left. And what he's
gonna see is basically the evaluation of f
on the messages on the left that he
supplied. Well, in the deterministic CPA
game, all these messages are distinct, and
so all he's gonna get back are just q
distinct random values in X. That's all he
sees. Yes, there's Q distinct random
values in X. Now let's think about
experiment one. In experiment one, he gets
to see the encryptions of messages on the
right, okay, the M11 to MQ1. Well, again,
all these messages are all distinct so all
he gets to see are just Q random distinct
values in X. Well these two distributions,
in experiment zero and experiment one,
therefore are identical. Basically, in
both cases what he gets to see are just Q
distinct random values in X. And as a
result, he can't distinguish experiment
zero from experiment one. And since he
can't do this for a truly random function,
he also can't do this for the PRP. Ok,
so that explains why directly encrypting
with a PRP already gives us a CPA secure
system very, very, very simple to use.
That says that if all we wanna do is
encrypt short messages, say, less than
sixteen bytes, then all we need to do is
to directly encrypt them using AES and the
result will, in fact, be deterministic CPA
secure. So, if your indices are less than
sixteen bytes directly using AES is a fine
thing to do. Notice however, that's not
gonna provide any integrity. And we're
gonna see how to add integrity in just a
minute. But the question for you is, what
do we do if we have longer than sixteen
byte messages? Well, one option is to use
SIV. But what if we actually wanted to use
this construction too. It's actually an
interesting question. Can we construct
PRP's that have message spaces that are
bigger than just sixteen bytes? If you
remember in the past we constructed PRFs
on that had large message spaces from
PRFs that had small message spaces. Here,
we're going to construct PRPs with large
message spaces from PRFs that have small
message spaces. So, here's how we do it.
So suppose E D is a secure PRP that
operates on N bit blocks. There's a
standard mode called EME that actually
will construct a PRP that operates on
capital N bit blocks, where capital N is
much, much bigger than little n. So this
would allow us to do deterministic
encryption on much larger messages than
just sixteen bytes. In fact it could be as
long as we want. So let's see how EME
works. It's a bit daunting at first but
it's not a difficult construction. So,
let's see how it works. So, EME uses two
keys, K and L, and in fact in the real EME
L is derived from K. But for our purposes,
let's just pretend that K and L are two
distinct keys. The first thing we do, is
we take our message X and we break it up
into blocks. And then we XOR each block
with a certain padding function, okay? So
we use the secret key L to derive a pad
using this, you know function P that I'm
not gonna explain here. We derive a
different pad for each one of the blocks
and we XOR that pad. Into the block. The
next thing we do is we apply the PRP E
using the Key K, to each of these blocks,
and we're gonna call these outputs PP0,
PP1, and PP2. The next thing we do is we
XOR all these ppp's together and we call
the result MP. Actually this XOR
doesn't need to be there. We call the
result of the XOR MP. The next thing we
do we XOR all these ppp's together and we
call the result MP. We encrypt this MP
using E and the key K. We call the outputs of
this encryption MC. Okay. So then we use
the XOR MP and MC and this gives us
another PM, which we use to derive one
more pad, and then we XOR this output
of this pad with all the PPP's to get
these CCC's, [laugh], and then we XOR
all these C C C's together that gives us
a value of C C C zero, which we then
encrypt one more time with all these E's,
we do one more padding with all these P's
and that actually finally gives us the
output of EME. Okay, so like I said,
this may look a little daunting, but in
fact there's a theorem that shows that if
the underlying block cipher E is a secure
PRP, then in fact. This construction, EME,
is a secure PRP on this larger block, you
know, zero, one to the capital N. The nice
thing about this construction is you
notice that it's very parallel and
actually that's why it's a little
complicated. Counted every block. It's
encrypted in parallel, so if you have a
multi-core processor, you can use all your
cores to encrypt all the blocks at the
same time and then there would be one kind
of sequential step to compute this, check
sum of, all the outputs and then one more
parallel around to encrypt one more time
and then finally you get the outputs.
These function Ps, by the way, that
generate the pads, are very, very simple
functions. They take constant time so
we're just going to ignore them in terms
of performance. So the bottom line is
performance here. You notice it requires
two applications of E per input block. And
it turns out this can actually be slower
than SIV, if SIV is implemented properly
with a very fast PRF to derive the
randomness. Then in fact SIV can be twice
as fast, as this particular mode of
operation. For this reason I say that the
PRP construction is very good for short
messages, whereas SIV is good if you h, if
you want to encrypt longer messages in a
deterministic fashion. But now what if we
wanted to add integrity to this PRP-based
mechanism? So, can we achieve
deterministic authenticated encryption
using the PRP mechanism where we directly
encrypt the message using a PRP? And it
turns out the answer is yes and it's
actually again, a very simple
encryption scheme that you should know
about. Basically what we're going to do is
we're going to take our message and we're
going to append a bunch of zeros to this
message and then we're going to apply the
PRP and that's it. And that's going to
give us the cipher text. Now, very, very
simple. Just append zeros and encrypt
using a PRP. When we decrypt, we're going
to look at these least significant bits of
the resulting plain text and if they're
not equal to zero, we're just going to
reject the cipher text. And if they are
equal to zero, we're going to output the
message as valid. Okay, so that's it,
that's the whole system, very, very
simple. Simply append zeroes during
encryption, and then check that the zeroes
are there when you decrypt. And I claim
that this very simple mechanism actually
provides deterministic authenticated
encryption, assuming, of course, that
you've appended enough zeroes. And in
particular, if you append N zeroes, you
need one over two to the N to be
negligible. And if so, then, in fact, this
direct PRP based encryption, in fact,
provides deterministic authenticated
encryption. So let me see why. Well, we
already argued that the system is CPA
secure, so all we have to argue is that it
provides cipher text integrity. And again,
that's easy to see. Let's look at the
cipher text game. So the adversary
is gonna choose let's say a truly random
permutation. So a truly random, invertible
function, on the input space. In this case
the input space is the message space and
the N zero bits. Now what does the
adversary get to do? Well he gets to
submit q messages, and then he receives
the encryption of those Q messages. Mainly
he receives the PRP at his chosen points
concatenated with N zeros. Okay, that's
what it basically it means to query the
CPA challenger. So in case of a random
permutation, he simply gets to see, the
value of this permutation at Q points of
his choice, but only concatenated with N
zeroes. And now, what's his goal in the
cipher text integrity game? Well, his goal
is to produce some new cipher text that's
different from the cipher text that he was
given, that's gonna decrypt properly.
Well, what does it mean that it decrypts
properly? It means that if, when we apply,
Pi inverse To the cipher text C, it had
better be the case that the N least
significant bytes of C are all zeros. And
the question is how likely is that to
happen? Well, so let's think about this.
So basically we have a truly random
permutation and the adversary got to see
the value of this permutation as Q points.
How likely is he to produce a new point
that, when inverted, happens to have N zeroes
as the least significant bits? What we're
doing here is basically we're evaluating
the permutation Pi inverse at the point c.
And since Pi inverse is a random
permutation, how likely is it to have its
n least significant bits be equal to zero?
So it isn't hard to see that the answer
is, is, at most, the probability's at
most, one over two to the N. Because,
again, basically, the permutation is gonna
output a random element inside of, X times
0 1 to the N. And that element is gonna end
with N zeroes, but basically
with the probability one over two to the
N. And as a result, the adversary wins the
game with negligible probability, Because,
this value is negligible. So that's the
end of this segment. I wanted you to see
these two very cute deterministic
authenticated encryption schemes. The
first one we called SIV, where I said you
would use randomized counter mode and you
just arrived at randomness for randomized
counter mode from a PRF applied to the
message. And the very cute idea here is
that during decryption you can simply
recompute the IV from the, from the decrypted
message and verify that that IV is what's
given to you in the cipher text. And that
simple check is actually enough to
guarantee authenticated encryption or
rather deterministic authenticated
encryption. So this mode is, is the way
you would encrypt an index in a database
if the index was large. If the index
happens to be short, maybe say, its eight
bytes if it's an 8-byte user ID, then you
can directly use a PRP and the way you
would do is, is you would append zeros to
those eight bytes. And then those zeros
will be used as an integrity check when
you decrypt and again if you append, are
able to append enough zeros, then in fact
this also provides deterministic
authenticated encryption. As an aside, I
showed you that there's a way to build the
wide block PRP from a narrow PRP and that
particular mode of operation is called
EME. So we're gonna refer EME
actually in the next segment.