In this segment, we're gonna look at the
concept of deterministic encryption that
often comes up in practice. When I say
deterministic encryption system, I mean an
encryption system that will always map
given message to exactly the same cipher
text. So if we encrypt the same message
three times, every time we'll get exactly
the same cipher text. So there are no
nonces involved here. Literally this is
just a consistence encryption scheme that
will always output the same cipher text
given a particular message. So let's see
where this comes up in practice and in
particular, I want to show you the case of
look-ups into an encrypted database. So
the settings are imagine we have a server
here that is going to store information
inside of an encrypted database. So what
it will store is records, and every record
has an index and some data that's stored
inside of the record. Now, the first thing
the server's gonna do is, it's gonna
encrypt this record. So here's a record
became encrypted and you notice that the
index became encrypted with K1 and the
data is encrypted with K2 and then the
encrypted record is sent over to the
database. And the same thing happens to
many records so that the database overall
holds many, many encrypted records. Well,
again, you can imagine that the index is
encrypted using the key K1 and then the
data and the records is encrypted using
the key K2. Now, if encryption is
deterministic, the nice thing about that
is that, at a later time, when the server
wants to retrieve a record from the
database, all he needs to do is send to
the database an encryption of the index
that the server is interested in. So here,
it would send an encryption of the index,
Alice. That again, becomes encrypted, and
the resulting cipher text is identical to
the cipher text that was generated when
the record was first written to the
database. And the database can then, you
know, find the record that has this
encrypted index in it, and then send the
result back to the server. The nice thing
about this is that now the database is
completely in the dark as to what data is
stored in the database and it doesn't even
know what records are being retrieved by
the server since all it sees are basically
requests for encrypted entices. And so
this deterministic encryption mechanism.
Let's just do a quick look up in the
database given an encrypted index and
we're guaranteed that because of the
deterministic encryption property that the
index is going to be encrypted in exactly
the same way as if was when the record was
created. And so this should be disturbing
to many of you because we previously said
that deterministic encryption simply
cannot be chosen plain text secure. The
problem is that an attacker can look at
different cipher text and if he sees the
same cipher text twice he knows that the
underlying encrypted messages must also be
the same. So in other words, by looking at
cipher text, he can learn something about
the corresponding plain text because every
time he sees the same cipher text twice,
he knows that the underlying messages are
equal. In practice, this leads to
significant attacks, and particularly when
the message space is small. For example,
if we're transmitting single bytes across
the network, such as, keystrokes that are
being transmitted one keystroke at a time.
Then, in fact, an attacker can simply
build a dictionary of all possible cipher
texts. If it's only single bytes, then
there will only be 256 possible cipher
texts. And then, simply by learning what
the decryptions of those cipher texts are,
he can actually figure out all future
cipher texts, simply by looking them up,
in this dictionary. And so there are many
cases where the message being so small,
where this, deterministic encryption,
simply is insecure. Now concretely, in the
case of an encrypted database, what the
attacker would see is if there are two
records that happen to have the same
cipher text in the index position then now
he knows that those two records correspond
to the same index. So again, even though
he doesn't know what the index is, he
learns something about the corresponding
plain text. I wanted to briefly remind you
that, formally, we say that deterministic
encryption cannot be CPA secure by
describing an adversary that wins the CPA
game. The chosen plain text attack game,
and let me quickly remind you how that
works. The game starts by the adversary
sending two messages, M zero and M zero.
And remember that, in this game, the
adversary is always going to be given the
encryption of the left message or the
encryption of the right message. In this
case, since he used the same message in
both cases, both on the left and on the
right, he's simply gonna get the
encryption of the message M zero. In the
next step, he's gonna send the messages M
zero, M1. And now he's either gonna get
the encryption of M zero, or the
encryption of M1. And his goal is to tell
which one he got. But because the
encryption is deterministic, this is very
easy for him to do. All he has to do is
just test whether C is equal to C zero.
And if C is equal to C zero, then he knows
that he got the encryption of M zero. If C
is not equal to C zero, he knows that he
got the encryption of M1. So he can output
zero. If C is equal to C0 and output one,
if C is not equal to C0 and his advantage
in this in this particular game would be
one. So it, it would be a high, as high an
advantage as possible which means that he
attacker completely defeats chosen
plain text security. Okay so, this is just
a formal way of saying that the attacker
basically learns more information about
the plain text than he should. So, the
question is, what do we do? And it turns
out the solution is basically to restrict
the type of messages that can be encrypted
under a single key. And so, the idea is to
say that suppose the encryptor never ever,
ever encrypts the same message under a
single key. In other words the message key
pair is always different and never
repeats. So that for every single
encryption, either the message changes, or
the key changes, but, or both change. But
it can't be that we encrypt the same
message twice under the same key. So why
would this ever happen? Well it turns out
there are very natural cases where this
happens. For example, if the messages
happen to be random. Say you, the
encryptors encrypting keys and those keys,
you know, say are 128 the keys so,
they'll never actually with very high
probability, they'll never repeat. In this
case when we're encrypting keys, in fact,
is very likely that all the messages that
are encrypted under one master key are
always distinct because, again, these keys
are very unlikely to ever repeat. The
other reason why messages would never
repeat is simply because of some structure
in the message space. For example, if all
we're encrypting are unique user IDs. So
imagine, in the database example, the
index corresponds to a unique user ID. And
if there's exactly one record in the
database for each user, that says that
every encrypted record basically contains
an encrypted index, where the index is
distinct for all records in the database.
Okay so these are two reasons why messages
might never repeat. And this is a fairly
reasonable thing that actually does happen
quite often in practice. So now if the
messages never repeat, now maybe we can
actually define security and actually give
constructions to satisfy our definitions.
So this motivates the concept of deterministic chosen plain text attacks and
let me explain what they mean. So as usual
we have a cipher defined as an encryption
on a decryption algorithm. So we have a
key space, a message space and a cipher
text space and we're gonna define security
just as normal using two experiments.
Experiment zero and experiment one. And
the game actually looks very similar, it's
almost an identical game to the standard
chosen playing test attack game where
basically the attacker issues queries, so
you can see these queries consist of pairs
of messages, M0 and M1. They, as usual
they have to be the same length and for
each query the attacker either gets the
encryption of M0 or the encryption of M1
and the attacker can do this again and
again. He can do this Q times, and at the
end of the game he's supposed to say
whether he got the encryptions of the left
messages or the encryptions of the right
messages. So this is the standard chosen
plain text attack game, but now there's
one extra caveat. Which is to say that, if
the bit is equal to zero, if B is equal to
zero. In other words, the attacker always
sees the encryption of the left messages,
then it so happens that the left messages
must all be distinct. In other words, he
will never get to see the encryption of
the same message twice, because these left
messages are always distinct. So if the
bit B is equal to zero, again, he'll never
see. The same message encrypted under the
same key. Because, again, these zero
messages, M1 zero to MQ zero, are all
distinct. Similarly, we require that all
the one messages are also distinct. And so
that, again, if B happens to be equal to
one, the attacker will never see two
messages encrypted under the same key.
Okay? So this requirement that the, all
these messages are distinct, and
similarly, all these Q messages are
distinct. Basically captures this use case
that the encryptor will never encrypt the
same message multiple times using one
particular key. And as a result, the
attacker simply can't ask for, the
encryption of the same message multiple
times using the same key. Now, I should
point out as you go back to our, to the
original attack, here. So, here we go back
to our CPA attack on deterministic
encryption, you notice that here, in fact,
this is not a deterministic CPA game,
because, here, the attacker did ask for
the same message m0 to be encrypted twice.
So, in fact, this attack would be an
illegal attack under the deterministic CPA
game. And by ruling out this attack we
actually make it plausible that we might
be able to give constructions that are
deterministic CPA secure. And so as usual
we say if the adversary cannot distinguish
experiment zero, when he's given the
encryption of the left messages, from
experiment one, when he's given the
encryption of the right messages, then the
scheme is semantically secure. Under a
deterministic CPA attack. Okay. So as
usual, we ask for what's the probability
that the adversary outputs one in
experiment zero? What's the probability
that the outputs one in experiment one?
Then if these probabilities are close then
his advantage in attacking the scheme is
negligible. And if that's true for all
efficient adversaries then we say that the
scheme is semantically secure under
deterministic CPA attack. So the first
thing I want to do is show you the cipher
block training with a fixed IV, in fact,
not deterministic CPA secure. And this a
common mistake that's used in practice.
There are many products that should be
using a cipher that's deterministic CPA
secure, but instead, they just use CBC
with a fixed IV and assume that's a secure
mechanism. And in fact, it's not and I
want to show you why. So suppose we have a
PRP that happens to operate on N bits
blocks. And we're going to use this PRP in
CBC mode. So, you know, if there are five
blocks in the message then this PRP E will
be called five times to encrypt each one
of those blocks. Okay. So here's how the
attack's going to work. Well, the first
thing the adversary is going to do is he's
going to ask for the encryption of the
message as 0N, 1N. In other words, the
first block is all zeros and the second
block is all ones. So the left message is
equal to the right message here which
means that he just wants the encryption of
this 0N, one to the N message. So let's
see what the cipher text looks like. Well,
for completeness I'm gonna write the IV,
the fixed IV, as the first element in the
ciphertext. And if you think about how
CBC works and the second element in
the ciphertext is gonna be basically the
encryption of the IV XOR the first
block of the message. Well in our case the
first block of the message is all zeros so
really all we're encrypting is just a
fixed IV. So the second block of the
ciphertext is simply gonna be the
encryption of this fixed IV. So next, what
the adversary's gonna do is, now he's
gonna output two messages that are a
single block. So the first message is
gonna be, the message on the left is gonna
be the all zeroes block. And the message
on the right is gonna be all ones block.
So observe that this is a valid query,
because messages on the left are all
distinct. And the messages on the right
are also all distinct. So these are all
valid deterministic CPA queries. Now, what
does the attacker get in response? Well,
what he'll get in response is the
following. If he gets the encryption of
the message on the left. Then, well,
what's the encryption of the one block
message, zero to the N? It's simply the
encryption of the fixed IV, just as we saw
before. However, if he's getting the
encryption of the message on the right,
well, that's gonna be the encryption of 1 XOR
the fixed IV. That's the definition
of, CBC encryption. So know, you can see
basically how the attack is going to
proceed. You notice, if I, here I'll use a
different color here. You notice if these
two blocks happen to be the same, then we
know that he received the encryption of
the message on the left, in other words B
is equal to zero. If they're not the same
then he knows that B is equal to one Okay,
so he's gonna output zero if, you know, C
of one, which is this block, is equal to
C1 of one, which is this block, and he's
gonna output one otherwise. So this
basically shows that CBC with a fixed IV
is completely insecure. Basically the
first block can be very easily attacked.
And, in fact, if the messages are short
you can again build dictionaries and
completely break systems that kind
of view CBC with a fixed IV hoping that
it's gonna be a deterministic CPA secure.
So don't do that. We're actually gonna see
secure deterministic CPA constructions in
the next segment. So I'll say one more
time, if you need to encrypt the database
index in a consistent manner, don't use
CBC with a fixed IV to do it. Use the
schemes that I'm gonna show you in the
next segment. And so let me ask you the
same question about counter mode with a
fixed IV. Is this gonna be a deterministic
CPA secure system or not? And here, I'm
reminding you what counter mode with a
fixed IV is. Basically, we concatenate the
fixed IV. Fixed IV plus one, Fixed IV plus
L. We encrypt all these counters. We
concatenate the results, we encrypt the
message to get the cipher text. So if you
think this is gonna be deterministic CPA
secure. So I hope everybody said no,
because basically this is a onetime
padding encryption, and if we use this one
time pad to encrypt distinct messages,
basically we'll be getting a two time pad.
And to see more precisely, here I wrote
down the, deterministic CPA game. So,
you notice what the attacker will do is he
would start off by asking for the
encryption of the message m. So he would
get here the message m XOR the encryption
of the fixed iv and then he's gonna ask
for some two distinct messages m0 and m1
that's different from m. So, m, m0 and m1
are a three are all three are distinct
messages. And then what he'll get is the
encryption of mb and now he can simply
mount the standard, kinda two time pad
attack. And if this equality here of c XOR c prime is equal to m XOR m zero, he
knows that c prime is the encryption of m
zero. And otherwise he knows it's the
encryption of M1. So, again, he will
completely win this game with advantage
equals to one. Okay, so again deterministic CPA
with a fixed IV is also
completely insecure as a deterministic CPA
cipher. So, don't use any of those
schemes, instead let's use the schemes I'm
going to describe in the next segment.