Well, we're almost done with our
discussion of symmetric encryption. There
are just a couple of odds and ends that
I'd like to discuss before we move on to
the next topic. So the first thing I'd
like to mention is how we derive many keys
from one key. And it, actually, this comes
up all the time in practice, so I'd like
to make sure you know how to do this
correctly. So what's the setting that
we're looking at? Well, imagine we have a
certain source key that's generated by one
of, a number of methods. Imagine the
source key is generated by a hardware
random number generator or perhaps is
generated by a key exchange protocol
which we're going to discuss later. But
anyhow, there are a number of ways in
which a source key might be generated
between Alice and Bob, such that the
attacker doesn't know what the source key
is. But now, as we said, in many cases, we
actually need many keys to secure a
session, not just one single source key.
For example, if you remember, in TLS there
were unidirectional keys and we
needed keys in each direction. And in
fact, in each direction, we needed
multiple keys. We needed a MAC key, we
needed an encryption key. We need an IV,
and so on. Similarly nonce based
encryption, you remember, there were
multiple keys that were being used, and so
on. And so, the question is, how do we use
the one source key that we just derived,
either from a hardware process or
by key exchange, and generate a bunch of
keys from it that we could then use to
secure our session. The way that's done,
is using a mechanism called a key
derivation function, KDF. And I want to
talk a little bit about how KDF's are
constructed. So first of all, suppose we
have a secure PRF, that happens to have
key space K. And now, suppose that it so
happens that our source key SK is uniform
in the key K. In this case, the source key
is, in fact, a uniform random key for the
secure PRF F. And we can use it directly to
generate keys, all the keys that we need
to secure the session. So in this case,
the KDF is really simple. The key
derivation function would just work as
follows. It would take as input the
source key. It would take an input, a
parameter context, which I'm gonna
describe in just a minute. And then it's
gonna take a length input as input as
well. And then what it will do is it will
basically evaluate the PRF on zero. Then
it will evaluate the PRF on one. Then it
will evaluate the PRF on two, up until L.
And I will talk about what this context is
in just a second. And then, basically, you
would use as many bits of the output as
you would need to generate all the keys
for the session. So, if you need unidirectional keys you would generate, you
know, one key in each direction where each key
might include an encryption key and a MAC
key. And so, you would basically generate
as many bits as you need and then finally
cut off the output at the time when you've
generated enough keys to secure your
session. Okay so this is a fairly straight
forward mechanism it's basically using the
secure PRF as a pseudo random generator.
And the only question is what is its
context string. Well, I'll tell you that
the context string is basically a unique
string that identifies the application. So
in fact you might have multiple
applications on the same system that's
trying to establish multiple secure keys.
Maybe you have SSH running as one process,
you have a web server running as another process,
IPsec as a third process and all three need
to have secret keys generated. And this
context variable basically tries to separate
the three of them. So, let me ask you,
more precisely, what do you think
the purpose of this context variable is?
So I guess I've given
it away and this context variable is
supposed to basically separate
applications, so that even if, for
example, the three services that we just
talked about, SSH, web server, and IPsec,
if they all happen to obtain the same
source key from the hardware random number
generator then the context since it's
different for the three apps will make
sure that they still get three independent
strings that they can then use to secure
the sessions. I just want you to remember
that, even though this is actually fairly
straightforward, and we discussed this
before, the context string is actually
important, and it does need to be specific
to the application, so that each
application gets its own session keys,
even if multiple applications happen to
sample the same SK. The next
question is, what do we do if the source
key actually isn't uniform? Well, now we
got a problem. If the source key is not a
uniform key for the pseudo random function
then we can no longer assume that the
output of the pseudo random function is
indistinguishable from random. In fact, if
we just use the KDF that we just described
then the output might not look random to
the adversary and then he might be able to
anticipate some of the session keys that
we'll be using and thereby break the
session. So then we have a problem. Now
why would this source key not be uniform?
Well there are many reasons why this
happened. For example if you use a key
exchange protocol, it so happens typically
that key exchange protocols will generate a
high entropy key. But the
high entropy key is gonna be
distributed in some subspace of the key
space. So it's not going to be a uniform
string. It will be uniform in some
subset of a larger set, And we'll see
examples of that as soon as we talk about
key exchange protocols. And so KDFs have
to kind of accommodate for the fact that
key exchange protocols actually don't
generate uniform bit strings. The other
problem is, that, in fact, the hardware
random number generator you're using might
actually produce biased outputs. We don't
wanna rely on the non bias of the hardware
random number generator. And so all we
want to assume is that it generates a high
entropy string, but one that might be
biased. In which case, we have to somehow
clean this bias. And so this introduces
this, this paradigm for building KDFs.
This is called the extract-then-expand
paradigm, where the first step
of the KDF is to extract a pseudo random
key from the actual source key. So in a
picture you can think about it like this.
In some sense these are the different
possible values of the source key. This is
the horizontal line and the vertical axis
is basically the probability of each one
of these values, and you can see that this
is a kind of a bumpy function which would
say that the source key is not uniformly
distributed in the key space. What we do
in this case is we use what's called an
extractor. So an extractor is something
that takes a bumpy distribution and makes
it into a uniform distribution over the
key space. In our case we're actually just
gonna be using what are called
computational extractors, namely
extractors that don't necessarily produce
uniform distribution at the end but
they generated distribution that's
indistinguishable from uniform.
Now extractors typically take as input
something called a salt, and a salt just
like in a salad, it kind of adds flavor to
things, what it does is basically kind of
jumbles things around, so that no matter
what the input distribution is, the output
distribution is still going to be
indistinguishable from random. So a salt
basically, what is it? It's a non-secret
string, so it's publicly known. It doesn't
matter if the adversary knows what the
salt is, and it's fixed forever. The only
point is that when you chose it, you chose
one at random. And then the hope is that
the funny distribution that you're trying
to extract from kinda doesn't inherently
depends on the salt that you chose and
hence as a result using your salt, you
will actually get a distribution that
looks indistinguishable from random. So
essentially the salt, you know, you can
just bang it the keyboard a couple of
times when you generate it but it just
needs to be something that's random
initially but then it's fixed forever, and
it's fine if the adversary knows what
it is and nevertheless the extractor is
able to extract the entropy and output a
uniformly random string K. In some sense the
salt is only there to defend against
adversarially bad distributions that might
mess up our extractor. Okay, so now that
we have extracted a pseudo random key.
Now, we might as well just use it in a KDF
that we just saw using a secure
pseudo random function to expand the key
into as many bits as we need to actually
secure the session. Okay, so there are
these two steps. The first one is we
extract a pseudo-random key, and then once
we have a pseudo-random key we already
know how to extend it into as many keys as
we need using a pseudo-random function. So
the standardized way of doing this is
called HKDF. This is a KDF, a key derivation function that's built from HMAC.
And here HMAC is used both as the PRF for
expanding and an extractor for extracting
the initial pseudo-random key. So let me
explain how this works. So in the extract
step, we're gonna use our salt which you
remember is a public value just happened to
be generated at random at the beginning of
time. And we use this salt as the HMAC
key. And then the source key we're gonna
use as the HMAC data. So we're kind of
using a public value as a key. And
nevertheless, one can argue that HMAC has
extraction properties, such that, when we
apply HMAC, the resulting key is going to
look indistinguishable from random,
assuming that the source key actually has
enough entropy to it. And now that we have
the pseudo random key we're simply going
to use HMAC as a PRF to generate a
session key of you know as many bits as we
need for the session keys. Okay. So that
basically concludes our discussion of
HKDF. And I just want you to remember
that, once you obtain a source key, either
from hardware or from a key exchange
protocol, the way you convert it into
session keys is not by using that sample
directly. You would never use a source key
directly as a session key in a protocol.
What you would do is you will run the
source key through a KDF. And the KDF
would give you all the keys and output
that you need, for, the randomness, for
the random keys to be used in your
protocol. And a typical KDF to use is
HKDF, which is actually getting quite a
bit of traction out there. Okay. The last
topic I wanna talk about in this segment
is, how do you extract keys from
passwords. These are called password based
KDFs or PBKDFs. The problem here is
that passwords have relatively low
entropy. In fact, we're gonna talk about
passwords later on in the course when we
talk about user authentication. And so,
I'm not gonna say too much here. I'll just
say passwords generally have very little
entropy estimated on the order of twenty
bits of entropy, say. And as a result,
there is simply not enough entropy to
generate session keys out of a password.
And yet we still need to do it very
frequently. We still need to derive
encryption keys and MACs and so on out of
passwords, so the question is how to do
it. The first thing is, you know, for this
kind of purpose, don't use HKDF. That's
not what it's designed for. What will
happen is that the derived keys will
actually be vulnerable to something called
a dictionary attack, which we're gonna
talk about much later in the course when
we talk about user authentication. So, the
way PBKDFs defend against this low entropy
problem that results in a dictionary
attack is by two means. First of all, as
before they use a salt, a public,
random value that's fixed forever. But in
addition, they also use what's called a
slow hash function. And let me describe
kind of the standard approach to deriving
keys from passwords. This is called PKCS#5,
and in particular, the version I'll describe
is what's called PBKDF1. And I
should say that this mechanism is
implemented in most crypto libraries so
you shouldn't have to implement this
yourself. All you would do, you know, you
would call a function, you know, derived
key from password. You would give the
password in as input, and you would get a
key as output. But you should be aware of
course that this key is not going to have
high entropy so in fact it will be
guessable. What these PBKDFs try to do is
make the guessing problem as hard as
possible. Okay. So the way they work,
first of all, is, as we said, they
basically hash, the concatenation of the
password and the salt. And then the hash
itself is designed to be a very slow hash
function. And the way we build a slow hash
function is by taking one particular hash
function, say, SHA-256, and we
iterate it many, many times, C times. So
you can imagine 1000 times, perhaps even a
million times. And what do I mean by
iterating it? So, well, we take the
password and the salt. And we put them
inside of one input to the hash function.
And then we apply the hash function, oops,
let me write it like this. And then we
apply the hash function and we get an
output, and then we apply the hash
function again and we get another output.
And we do this again and again and again
maybe a thousand times or a million times
depending on how fast your processors are
and then finally we get the final output
that we actually output as, as the key
output of this key derivation function.
Now what is the point here? Iterating a
function 10,000 times or even a million
times is going to take very little time on
a modern CPU, and as a result, it doesn't
really affect the user's experience. The
user types in his password, it gets hashed
a million times and then it gets output.
And maybe that could even take, you know a
tenth of a second and the user wouldn't
even notice it. However the attacker, all
he can do is he can try all the passwords
in the dictionary, because we know people
tend to pick passwords in dictionaries,
and so he could just try them one by one,
remember the SALT is public, so he knows
what the SALT is. And so he can just try this
hash one by one. However because the hash
function is slow, each attempt is gonna
take him a tenth of second. So if he needs
to run through a dictionary, you know, with,
with a 200 billion passwords in it,
because the hash function is slow, this is
gonna take quite awhile. And by doing
that, we slow down the dictionary attack,
and we make it harder for the attacker to
get our session keys. Not impossible, just
harder. That's all this is trying to do.
Okay, so this is basically what I wanted
to say about password based KDFs. As I
said, this is not something you would
build yourself. All crypto libraries have
an implementation of a PKCS#5
mechanism. And you would just call the
appropriate function to convert a password
into a key, and then use the resulting
key. Okay, in the next segment, we're
gonna see how to use symmetric encryption
in a way that allows us to search on the
cipher texts.