In this segment, we're gonna look at
attacks on the one time pad, and some
things you need to be careful with when
you use the stream cipher. But before we
do that, let's do a quick review of where
we were. So recall that the one time
pad encrypts messages by XORing the
message and a secret key, where the secret
key is as long as the message. Similarly,
decryption is done by similarly
XORing the cipher text, and the same
secret key. When the key is uniform and
random, we prove that the one-time pad has
this information theoretic security that
Shannon called perfect secrecy. A problem
was, of course, the keys are as long as
the message, so the one-time pad is very
difficult to use. We then talked about a
way to make the one time pad practical by
using a pseudo random generator that
expands a short seed into a much larger
message and the way a stream cypher
worked, essentially using a pseudo random
generator, was in the same way as the one
time pad, basically, but rather than using a
truly random pad, we used this pseudo
random pad that's expanded to be as long
as the message from the short key that's
given as input to the generator. We said
now the security no longer relies on
perfect secrecy because stream ciphers
cannot be perfectly secure. Instead
security relies on properties of the
pseudo random generator and we said that
the pseudo random generator essentially
needs to be unpredictable, but in fact it
turns out that definition is a little bit
hard to work with and we're going to see a
better definition of security for PRGs in
about two segments. But in this segment
we're going to talk about attacks on the
one time pad. And the first attack I want to
talk about is what's called the two time pad
attack, okay? so remember that the
one time pad is called "one time" pad because
the pad can only be used to encrypt a
single message. I want to show you that if
the same pad is used to encrypt more than
one message, then security goes out the
window, and basically an eavesdropper can
completely decrypt encrypted messages.
So let's look at an example. So here we
have two messages m1 and m2 that are
encrypted using the same pad. So the
resulting ciphertext, C1 and C2, again
basically are encryptions of these
messages, m1 and m2, but both are
encrypted using the same pad. Now suppose
an eavesdropper intercepts C1 and C2, and
he obtains, he basically has both C1 and C2.
The natural thing for the eavesdropper
to do is actually compute the XOR of C1
and C2 and what does he get when he
computes this XOR? So I hope everybody
sees that, basically, once you XOR
C1 and C2, the pads cancel out, and
essentially, what comes out of this is the
XOR of the plaintext messages.
And it turns out that English basically
has enough redundancy, such that if I give
you the XOR of two plaintext
messages, you can actually recover those
two mesages completely. More importantly
for us is these messages are encoded
using ASCII. In fact, ASCII encodings has
enough redundancy, such that given the
XOR of two ASCII encoded messages,
you can recover the original messages
back. So, essentially, given these XORs,
you can recover both messages. So the
thing to remember here is if you ever use
the same pad to encrypt multiple messages
an attack who intercepts the resulting
ciphertexts can eventually recover the
existing plaintexts without too much
work. So, the stream cipher key or the
one time pad key should never ever, ever,
ever be used more than once. So, let's
look at some examples where this comes up
in practice. It's a very common mistake to
use the stream cipher key, or a one time
pad key more than once. Now, let me show
you some examples where this comes up. So
you know to avoid these mistakes, when you
build your own systems. The first example
is a historic example. At the beginning of
the 1940s, where the Russians actually
used a one time pad to encrypt various
mesages. Unfortunately, the pads that they
were using were generated by a human by
throwing dice. And so, you know, the human
would throw these dice, and write down the
results of these throws. And the collected
throws would then form the pads that were
used for encryption. Now, because it was
kind of laborious for them to generate
these pads, it seems wasteful to use the
pads to encrypt just one message. So the
ended up using these pads to encrypt
multiple messages. And US intelligence was
actually able to intercept these two time
pads. These ciphertexts that were
encrypted using the same pad, applied to
different messages. And it turns out, over
a period of several years, they we're able
to decrypt something like 3,000 plain
texts just by intercepting these ciphertexts.
The project is called Project Venona
It's actually a fascinating
of cryptanalysis, just because the two
time pad is insecure. More importantly, I
want to talk about more recent examples
that come up in networking protocols, so
let me give you an example from Windows NT,
in a product called the,
point-to-point transfer protocol. This is
a protocol for a client wishing to
communicate securely with a server. The
client and the server both share a secret
key here, and they both send messages to
one another. So, here, we'll denote the
messages from the client by m1. So, the
client sends a message, the server
responds, the client sends a message, the
server responds, the client sends a
message, the server responds, and so on
and so forth. Now, the way PPTP works is,
basically, the entire interaction, from
the client to the server, is considered as
one stream. In other words, what happens
is, the messages m1, and m2 and m3, are
kind of viewed as one long stream.
Here, these two parallel lines means
concatenation. So, essentially, we're
concatenating all the messages from the
client to the server into one long stream.
And all that stream is encrypted using the
stream cipher with key K. So that's
perfectly fine. I mean, there's nothing
wrong with that. This messages are
encrypted, are treated as one long stream,
and they're all encrypted using the same
key. The problem is, the same thing is
happening also on the server side. In
other words, all the messages from the
server are also treated as one long
stream. So here, they're all concatenated
together. And encrypted using,
unfortunately, the same pseudo-random
seed, in other words, using the same
stream cipher key. So basically what's
happening here is you see an effect that
the two time pad is taking place where the
set of messages from the client is
encrypted using the same one time pad as a
set of messages from the server. The
lesson here is that you should never use
the same key to encrypt traffic in both
directions. In fact, what you need to do
is have one key for interaction between
the client and the server and one key for
interaction between the server and the
client. The way I like to write this is
really that the shared key k really is a
pair of keys. One key is used to encrypt
messages from server to client, and one
key is used to encrypt messages from
client to server. So these are two
separate keys that are used, and both
sides, of course, know this key. So both
sides have this pair of keys, okay? and
they can both encrypt. So one is used to
encrypt messages in one direction and one
is used to encrypt messages in the other
direction. So another important example of
the two time pad comes up in Wi-Fi
communication, particularity in the 80211B
protocol. So all of you I'm sure know that
the 80211 contains an encryption layer and
the original encryption layer was called
WEP and WEP fortunately for us is actually
a very badly designed protocol so that I
can always use it as an example of how not
to do things. There are many, many
mistakes inside of WEP and here I want to
use it as an example of how the two time
pad came about. So let me explain how WEP
works. So in WEP, there's a client and,
and access point. Here's the client,
here's the access point. They both share a
secret key K. And then, when they wanna
transmit a message to one another. Say
these are frames, that they
transmit to one another. Let's say the
client wants to send. A frame containing
the plain text M to the axis point, what
he would do is first of all he appends
some sort of check sum to this plain text.
The check sum is not important at this
point, what is important is then this new
calculation gets encrypted using a stream
cypher where the stream cypher key is this
concatenation of a value IV and a long
term key K. So this IV is a 24 bit string.
Okay, this IV is a 24 bit string, and you
can imagine that it starts from zero and
perhaps it's a counter that counts
increments by one for every packet. The
reason they did this was the designers of
Wep realized that in a stream cypher, the
key is only supposed to be used to encrypt
one message. So they said well, let's go
ahead and change the key after every
frame. And the way they changed the key
essentially was by prepending this IV to
it. And you notice this I-V changes on
every packet. So it increments by one on
every packet. And the idea, then, is sent
in the clear along with the cipher text.
So the recipient knows the key K. He knows
what the I-V is. He can rederive the PRG
of IV concatenating  K. And then decrypts
the cipher text to recover the original
message M. Now the problem with this
of course is the IV is only 24 bits long.
Which means that there are only two to the
24 possible IV's. Which means that after
sixteen million frames are transmitted.
Essentially the IV has to cycle. And once
it cycles after 60 million frames.
Essentially we get a two time path. The
same IV will be used to encrypt two
different messages. The TK never changes.
It's a long term key. And as a result,
that same key, namely the IV concatenated K
would be used to encrypt two different
frames, and the attacker can then figure
out the plain text of both frames. So
that's one problem. And the worst problem
is in fact that on many 80211 cards, if
you powercycle the card, the IV will reset
back to zero. And as a result, everytime
you powercycle the card, essentially
you'll be encrypting the next payload
using zero concatenated K  So after every
powercycle, you'll be using the zero
concatenated K key to encrypt many, many,
many times the same packets. So you see
how in WEP, the same pad could be used to
encrypt many different messages as soon as
the IV is repeated. There is nothing to
prevent the IV from repeating after a
powercycle. Or am repeating after every
sixteen million frames which isn't that
many frames in a busy network. So while we
are talking about WEP. I want to mention
one more mistake that was done in WEP.
This is a pretty significant mistake and
let's see how we might design it better.
So you notice that the designers of WEP
basically wanted to use a different key
for every packet. Okay. So every frame is
encrypted using a different key
is concatonation of IV and K.
Unfortunately. They didn't randomize the
keys and the keys are actually, if you
look at the key for frame number one,
well, you know, it will be this
concatenation of one and k. We'll just
feel this 24 bits. Then the key for frame
number two is the concatenation of two and
k. The key for frame number three is the
concatenation of three and k. So the keys
are very closely related to one another.
And I should probably mention also that
these keys themselves can be 104 bits so
that the resulting PRG key. Is actually
104 plus 24 bytes which is 128 bytes.
Unfortunately these keys are very much
related to one another. These are not
random keys. You notice they all have the
same suffix of 104 bytes. And it turns out
the pseudo-random generator used in Wep is
not designed to be secure when you use
related keys that are so closely related.
In other words, the majority of these keys
are basically the same. And in fact, for
the PRG that's used in WEP. That PRG is
called, RSC four. We'll talk about that
more in the next segment. It turns out
there's an attack. It was discovered by
Fluhrer, Mantin and Shamir
back in 2001, that shows that after about
ten to the six of, after about a million
frames. You can recover the secret key.
Can recover key. So, this is kind of a
disastrous attack that says essentially
all you have to do is listen to a million
frames. These frames basically. As we said
they're all generated from a very common
seed, namely a 104 bits of these seeds are
all the same. The fact that they've used
such closely related keys is enough to
actually recover the original key. And it
turns out even after the 2001 attack,
better attacks have come out that show
that these related keys are very much
disastrous and in fact these days
something like 40,000 frames are
sufficient. And so that, within a matter
of minutes, you can actually recover the
secret key in any WEP network. So
WEP provides no security at all
for two reasons. First of all, it can
resolve in the two time pad. But more
significantly, because these keys are so
closely related, it's actually possible to
recover the key by watching just a few
cipher texts. And by the way, we'll see
that well, when we do a security analysis
of these steps of constructions. In a few
segments, we'll start talking about how to
analyze these steps of constructions.
We'll see that when we have related keys
like this, in fact, our security analysis
will fail. We won't be able to get the
proof to go through. So one could ask what
should the designers of a WEP should have
done, instead? Well, one approach is to
basically treat the frames, you know M1,
M2, M3. Each, each one is a separate frame
transmitter from the client to the server.
He could have treated them as one
long stream, and then XOR them
potentially. Using the pseudo random
generator as one long stream. So the first
segment of the pad would have been used to
encrypt M1. The second
encrypt M2. The third segment
of the pad would have been used to encrypt
M3. And so on and so forth.
So they basically could never have had to
change the key because the entire
interaction is viewed as one long stream.
But they chose to have a different key for
every frame. So if you want to do that, a
better way to do that is, rather than
slightly modifying this IV that just
slightly modifies the prefix of the key,
of the PRG key. A better way to do that is
to use a PRG again. So essentially, what
you could do is you will take your long
term key. And then feed that directly
through a PRG. So now we get a long stream
of bits that look essentially random.
And then the initial segment could be
used, the first segment could be used as
the key, or frame number one. And then the
second segment would be used as the key
for, you know, key for frame number two.
And so on and so forth. The third segment
would be used to encrypt frame #three and
so on and so forth, okay? So the nice
thing about this is now, essentially, by
doing this, each frame has a pseudo-random
key. These keys, now, have no relation to
one another. They look like random keys.
And as a result, if the PRG is secure for
random Cs, it was also be secure on this
input. Because these keys essentially look
as though they're independent of one
another. We'll see how to do this analysis
formally once we talk about these types of
constructions. Since this two-time pad
attack comes up so often in practice, it's
such a common mistake, I want to give one
more example where it comes up so you know
how to avoid it. The last example I want
to give is in the context of disk
encryption. So imagine we have a certain
file and maybe the file begins with, you
know, the words to Bob. And then the
contents of the file follows when this is
stored on disk of course the file is gonna
get so here we have our disk here, the
file is going to get broken into blocks.
And each block will be, you know, when we
actually store this on a disk, you know,
things will be encrypted. You know, so
maybe to Bob will go into the first block
and then the rest of the content will go
into the remaining blocks. But of course
this is all incrypted so I'll kind of use
these lines here to denote the fact that
this is encrypted. And an attacker looking
at the disk has no idea what the contents
of the message is. But now suppose that at
a later time, user goes ahead and
modifies, basically fires up the editor.
It modifies the file, so now instead of
saying to Bob, it says to Eve. And nothing
else changes in the file, that's the only
change that was made. When the user then
saves this modified file to disk,
basically he's gonna re encrypt it again.
And so the same thing is gonna happen. The
file is gonna get broken into blocks. You
know, now the file's gonna say to Eve. And
everything, of course, is gonna be
encrypted. So again, I'll, put these lines
here. Now an attacker looking at the disc,
taking a snapshot of the disc before the
edits. And then looking again at the disc
after the edits. What he will see is that
the only thing that changed is this little
segment here. That's now different.
Everything else looks exactly the same. So
the attacker, even though he doesn't know
what actually happened to the file within
the file or what changed, he knows exactly
the location where the edits took place.
And so the fact that the one-time path or
a stream cypher encrypts one bit at a time
means that if one change takes place, then
it's very easy to tell where that change
occurred instantly. That leaks information
that the attacker shouldn't actually
learn. Ideally you'd like to say that even
if the file changed just a little bit.
Entire contents of the file should change.
Or maybe at least the entire contents of
the blocks should change. Here you can see
the attacker even knows within the block
where the change was actually made, okay.
So in fact, because of this, it's usually
a bad idea to use stream cyphers for disk
encryption. And essentially this is
another example of a two-time pad attack
because the same pad is used to encrypt
two different messages. This, they happen
to be very similar, but nevertheless these
are two different messages, and the
attacker can learn what the change was and
in fact he might be able to even learn
what the actual changed words were, as a
result of this. Okay, so the lesson here
is generally we need to do something
different for disk encryption. We'll talk
about what to do for disk encryption in a
later segment, but essentially the
one-time pad is generally not a good idea
for encrypting blocks on disks. So just
again to summarize the two-time pad
attack, we saw that you're supposed, I
hope I've convinced you that you're never
ever, ever supposed to use a stream cypher
key more than once. Even though there are
natural settings where that might happen,
you have to take care and make sure that
you're not using the same key more than
once. So for network traffic typically
what you're supposed to do is every
session would have its own key. Within the
session the message from the client and
the server look as one complete stream. It
would be encrypted using one key. Is, the
messages from the server to the client
would be treated as one stream and
encrypted using a different key. And then
for this encryption typically would not
use a stream cypher because. As changes
are made to the file, he would be leaking
information about the contents of the
file. Okay, so that concludes our brief
discussion of the two time pad.
Next attack I want to mention. Is a fact
that the one time path and stream cyphers
in general provide no integrity at all.
All they do is they try to provide
confidentiality when the key's only used
once. They provide no integrity at all but
even worse than that it's actually very
easy to modify cypher text and have known
effects on the corresponding plain text.
So let me explain what I mean by that.
This property, by the way, is called
malleability, and we'll see what I mean by
that in just a second. So imagine we have
some message M that gets encrypted. So,
here, it gets encrypted using a stream
cipher. And the cipher text, of course, is
then gonna be, M XOR a K. Now an
attacker intercepts the cypher text. Well,
that doesn't tell him what's, what the
plain text is but what he can do is now
beyond eavesdropping he can actually
become an active attacker and modify the
cypher text. So when I say modify the
cypher text let's suppose that he
XOR the cypher text with a certain
value P. Whats called a sub-permutation key.
Well, the resulting cipher text then
becomes M XOR K, XOR P. So now I'll
ask you, when we decrypt the cipher text,
what is it going to decrypt to? Well I
hope everybody sees manipulating the XORs
Basically the decryption becomes M XOR P
So you notice that by XOR with this pad P, the attacker was able to
have a very specific effect on the
resulting plain text. Okay. So a summary
is basically you can modify the cypher
text. These modifications are undetected.
But even worse, they're undetected, they
have a very specific impact on the
resulting plain text. Namely whatever you
XOR the cipher text with is going to have
that exact effect on the plain text. So to
see where this can be dangerous, let's
look at a particular example. Suppose the
user sends an email that starts with the
words from Bob. In the attacker
intercepts the corresponding cypher text.
He doesn't know what the cypher text is
but let's just for the sake of it let's
pretend that he actually knows that this
message is actually from Bob. What he
wants to do is he wants to modify the
ciphertext so that the plain text would
now look like it came from somebody else.
Say, he wants to make it look like this
message actually came from Alice. All he
has is the ciphertext. Well, what he can
do is he can XOR with a certain
three characters. We'll see
what those three characters are in just a
second. And such that the resulting
ciphertext is actually an encryption of
the message from Eve. And so that now when
the user decrypts that. All of a sudden
he'll see, Hey, this message is from Eve.
It's not, he'll think this message is from
Eve, not from Bob. And that might cause
you know, the wrong thing to take place.
So here the attacker, even though he
himself could not have created a cypher
text that says from Eve, by modifying an
existing cypher text all of a sudden he
was able to make the cypher text that he
could not have done without intercepting
at least one cypher text. So again by
intercepting one cypher text he was able
to change it so not it looks like it's
from Eve, rather than from Bob. So just to
be specific, let's look what these three
characters need to be, so let's look at
the word Bob. And I'm going to write it in
askee. So Bob in askee corresponds to 42
hex six f hex and 62 hex. So little b is
encoded as 62, little o is encoded as six
f. The word eve is encoded as 45 hex, 76
hex, and 65 hex. Now when I XOR these
two words, I'm literally going to x over
them as bit strings. So Bob XOR eve,
it's not difficult to see that what I get
are the three characters zero, seven.
Nineteen and 07. So really what these
three characters here are going to be. Are
simply 07, nineteen, and 07. And by
XORing these three characters at the
right positions into the cipher text, the
attacker was able to chance the cipher
text to look like it came from Eve rather
than from Bob. So this is an example
where having a predictable impact on the
cipher text can actually cause quite a bit
of problems. And this is this property
called malleability. And we say that the
one time pad is malleable because it's
very easy to compute in cipher texts, and
make prescribed changes to the
corresponding plain text. So to prevent
all this, I'm gonna do that, actually, in
two or three lectures. And we're gonna
basically show how to add integrity to
encryption mechanisms in general. But
right now I want you to remember that the
one time pad by itself has no integrity
and is completely insecure against
attackers that actually modify the cipher
texts.