Now that we know about the one-time pad,
let's talk about making the one-time pad
more practical using something called the
stream cypher. But before we do that,
let's do a quick review of where we were.
So let me just remind you that a cypher is
defined over a triple of sets called a key
space, a message space, and a cypher text
bare space. And a cypher is a pair of
efficient algorithms called E and D; E
stands for encryption and D stands for
decryption. And the only property. That we
need to satisfy is that decryption is the
opposite of encryption. In other words if
I encrypt a message M using a particular
key. And I de-crypt using the same key. I
get back the original message. Last time
we looked at a couple of weak cyphers like
the substitution cypher and the vigonaire
cypher. We showed that all of them can be
easily broken so you should never ever,
ever use those cyphers. Those were just
for historical reference. And then we
looked at our first exam.ple of a good
cypher, namely the one-time pad. So let me
just remind you how the one-time pad is
defined. Basically the message space is
the set of all bit end bit strings. The
cypher text is a set of all bit end bit
strings. And similarly, the key. Is the
set of all N bit strings and the way we
encrypt is by a simple exor to encrypt the
message we just exor the message in the
key that gives us the cypher text. And
then to decrypt a cypher text, we just do
this x over again and it's easier to show
by properties of x over that in fact
decryption is the opposite of encryption.
And then we talked about this lemma, in
fact, we proved it, that says that the
one-time pad has perfect secrecy, which
means that if you're just an eavesdropper
and you just get to see a single cypher
text, you're not going to be able to
deduce any information about the encrypted
plain text. Unfortunately. We also said
that Shannon proved this lema, we called
it the bad news lema, that basically says
that any cypher that has perfect secrecy
must have really long keys. In other
words, the key length must be at least as
long as the length of the message, which
means that the cypher is not particularly
useful. Because if two parties have a way
to agree on really long keys that are as
long as the message, they, in some sense,
might as well use that mechanism to
already transmit the message itself. So in
this lecture we're going to take the idea
of the one time pad and try to make it
into a practical encryption scheme. So
this is called what's called a stream
cypher. So the idea in this dream cypher
is rather than using a totally random key,
we're actually going to use a
pseudo-random key. And to explain how that
works, I need to define what is a
pseudo-random generator, PRG. So a PRG,
really, all it is, is just a function,
I'll call it g for generator, that takes a
seed, so I'm going to use zero one to the
s to denote all strings of length s, so
this we'll call the seed space. So he
takes an s bit seed and maps it to a much
larger string which will denote by zero
one to the n. And the property is that n
must be much larger than s. So in other
words, we take a seed that might be only
128 bits and we expand it into a much,
much larger output string that could be
gigabytes long. That's what this
pseudo-random generator does. And of
course, the goal is that first of all, the
generator is efficiently computable, so
the function g. There should be some sort
of an efficient algorithm that computes
it. So, efficiently computable by a
deterministic algorithm. It's important to
understand that the function g itself has
no more randomness, in it, it's a totally
deterministic. The only thing that's
random here is the random seed, that's
given as input to the function g. And the
other property, of course, is that the
output. Should look random and the
question is what does it mean to look
random, and that's something we'll define
later on in the lecture. Okay so suppose
we have such a generator, how do we use
that, to build a stream cipher? We the
idea is that we're gonna use the seed, as
our key, so our short seed is gonna be our
secret key. And then we're gonna use the
generator to basically expand the seed
into a much, much larger random looking
sequence, or pseudo random sequence, as
it's known, so this would be G of K. And then
we are going to X over it just like in the
one time pad we're going to X over it the
student random sequence with the message
and that's going to give us the cypher
text. Or if we want to write this in math,
we'll write C equals the encryption of the
message M with a key K, which is simply
defined as M XOR G of K. And then when we
want to decrypt, basically we do exactly
the same thing. It's basically the cypher
text XOR G of K, just like in the one-time
pad except then instead of XOR-ing with K,
we XOR with the output of the generator
applied to K. So the first question to ask
is why is it secure? So, basically you
now, we only have one notion of security
so far, which we called perfect secrecy.
And so let's just quickly ask can a stream
cipher have perfect secrecy. Remember in
the stream cipher the key is much, much
shorter than the message. And so, never
the less, can it have perfect secrecy. So
I hope everybody said the answer is, no.
The key is much shorter than the message.
And we said that in a, in a perfectly
secure cypher, the key must be as long as
the mesage. And therefore, it's not
possible that a, that a stream cypher
actually has perfect secrecy. So the
question is, then, well, why is it secure?
First of all we would need a different
definition of security to argue that
Stream Safe is, is secure and in
particular, the security property is going
to depend on the specific generator that
we used. So in fact the definition of
privacy that we'll need to argue the
security of Stream Cipher is we'll see in
the next lecture, but for now let me show
you one particular property. That a
generator must have a minimum property
needed for security. This property is
called unpredictability. So let's we
suppose for one second that in fact a
stream cycle is predictable. So, what does
that mean? Both the PRG is predictable.
What that means is essentially that there
is some pi. Such that if I give you the
first I bits of the outputs. This notation
Bar one to I means look at the first
I-bits of the output of the function.
Okay, so I give you the first I bits of
the stream. There is some sort of an
algorithm, there's an efficient algorithm
that will compute the rest of the string.
Okay, so given the first I bits, you can
compute the remainder of the bits. I claim
that if this is the case, then the stream
cypher would not be secure. So let's see
why. Suppose an attacker actually
intercepts a particular cypher text, let's
call it c. If this is the case, then in
fact, we have a problem. Because suppose
that just by some prior knowledge, the
attacker actually knows that the initial
part of the message happens to be some
known value. For example, we know that in
the mail protocol, smtp, the standard mail
call used in the internet, you know that
every message starts with a word from
colon. Well, that would be a prefix that
the adversary knows. That the site, that
the message must begin with from a colon.
What it could do is it could [inaudible]
the cipher text with the words from colon,
with the little prefix of the message that
it actually knows. And what that would
give it is a prefix of. Of the pseudo
random sequence. And I would learn as a
result of this, it would learn a prefix of
the pseudo random sequence but then we
know that once it has a prefix of the
pseudo random sequence it can predict the
remainder of the pseudo random sequence
and that would allow it to then predict
the rest of the message end. Okay, so for
example if the pseudo random generator was
predictable given five bits of the pad.
Then every email encrypted using the
stream cypher would be decryptable
because, again, the attacker knows the
prefix of the message from which he
deduces the prefix of the pad, which then
allows him to compute the rest of the pad,
which then allows him to recover the
entire plain text. Okay, so this is an
example that shows that in fact if a PRG
is predictable then already there are
security problems. Because a small prefix
would reveal the entire message. As it
turns out, even if I could predict just
one bit of the outputs. Even if given, you
know, the first I bits, I can predict the
next bits, the I plus first bits. Already,
this is a problem. Because that would say
that given again, the first couple of
letters in a message can predict, can
decrypt essentially, and recover the next
bit of the message, or the next layer of
the message, and so on. So this
predictability property shows that, you
know, if we use a PRG that's going to be
used in a stream cypher, it had better be
unpredictable. So what does it mean that a
PRG is unpredictable? So let's define more
precisely what it means for a PRG to be
unpredictable. Well first we'll define
more precisely what it means for a PRG to
be predictable. So we say that G is
predictable, if there exists an efficient
algorithm. Let's call it A and there is
some position. There's a position I
between one and N minus one such that if
we look at the probability over a random
key. Probability if I generate a random
key. You remember, this notation means
choose a random key from the set k. So
this arrow with r just means choose a
random key from the set k. Basically, if I
give this algorithm the prefix of the
output, if I give it the first I bytes of
the output, the probability that it's able
to predict the next bit of the outputs,
this probability is greater than half plus
epislon. For some non-negotiable. For some
non-negligible. >> [inaudible]. >> A non
[inaudible], for example, would be
epsilon, which is great than one over two
to the 30. One over a billion, for
example, we would consider it not
negligible. So these terms, negligible and
non negligible will come back at the end
of the lecture, and define them more
precisely. But for now, let's just, stick
with the intuitive notion of what non
negligible means. And so this is what it
means, for an algorithm, for a generator
to be, predictable. Basically, there is
some algorithm that is able to predict the
I plus first bits, even the mutual prefix,
okay? And then we say that an algorithm,
that a P or G is unpredictable. If in
fact, well, if it's doesn't satisfy the
property that we just defined. In other
words, it is not predictable. But what
does it mean, more precisely for it not to
be predictable. It means that, in fact,
for all positions, for all i there is
no efficient adversary no efficient
algorithm A that can predict the i + 1
bit with non negligible probability.
Excellent. Okay and this has to be true
for all I. So no matter which prefix I
give you, you're not gonna be able to
predict the next bit that follows the
prefix. Okay, so let's look at some
examples. Here is a silly, silly example.
Suppose I give you a generator, and I ask
you, is it predictable? Well, this
generator happens to have the property,
that if I XOR all the bits of the
outputs, I always happen to get one. Okay,
so I x over all the bits. Bit number one,
x over bit number two, x over bit number
three. If I x over all those bits, I
happen to get one. The question is, is
that a predictable generator? And again, I
hope everybody answered yes, that
essentially given the first n minus one
bits of the outputs, I can predict the nth
bit because it would just be the bits
that's needed to make the x over all the
bits be one. In other words, I give you
all but one of the bits of the generator,
you can actually predict the last bit of
the generator. Now that we've seen that
PRGs have to be unpredictable, I just want
to mention a couple of weak PRGs that
should never ever be used for crypto. This
is a very common mistake and I just want
to make sure none of you guys make this
mistake. So a very common PRG that should
actually never be used for crypto is
called a linear congruential generator. So
let me explain what a linear congruential
generator is. Basically it has parameters.
It has three parameters. I'll call them A,
B and P. A and B are just integers and P
is a prime. And the generator is defined
as follows, essentially I'll say R zero is
the seed of the generator. And then the
way you generate randomness is basically
you [inaudible] run through the following
steps. You compute a times r of I minus
one plus b modular p. Then you output a
few bits of the current states, output few
bits of our i. Then, of course, you
increment I and you iterate this again and
again and again. Okay? So you can see how
this generator proceeds. It starts with a
particular seed. At every step there is
this leaner transformation that's being
applied to the seed. And then you output a
few bits of the current state and then you
do that again and again and again and
again. Unfortunately even though this
generator has good statistical properties
in the sense that, for example, the number
of zeroes it outputs is likely going to be
similar to the number of ones and so on;
it has, you can actually argue all sorts
of nice statistical properties about this,
nevertheless it is a very easy generator
to predict. And in fact should never ever
be used. In fact, just given a few
outputs, a few output samples, it's easy
to predict the remainder of the sequence.
And as a result, this generator should
never ever be used. Another example is a
random number generator that is very
closely related to the linear congruential
generator. This is a random number
generator implemented in glibc, very
common library. That you can see. I just
wrote down the definition here. You can
see that is basically outputs a few bits
at every ideration and it just does this
simple linear transformation at every
step. Again, this is a very easy generator
to predict and should never ever be used
for crypto. And so the lesson I want to
emphasize here is never ever use the
built-in glibc function random. For crypto,
because it doesn't reduce,
cryptographic randomness, in the sense
that it is easy to predict. And, in fact,
systems like Kerberos version four have
used random and, have been bitten by that.
So, please don't make that mistake
yourself. We will talk about how to do
secure random number generation actually in
the next lecture. Before we conclude this
lecture I just want to give a little bit
more detail about these concepts of
negligible and non-negligible values, so
different communities in crypto actually
define these concepts differently, for
practitioners basically these the term
negligible and non-negligible,
are just, particular scalers that are used in the
definition. So, for example, a
practitioner would say, that if a value is
more than one over, one over a billion,
one over two to the 30, we say that the
value is non-negligible. The reason is,
the reason that's so, is, because if you
happen to use a key, for example, for, for
encrypting a gigabyte of data, a gigabyte
of data is about two to the 30 or maybe
even two to the 32 bytes. Then an event
that happens with the probability one over
two to the thirty will likely happen after
about a gigabyte of data. So since a
gigabyte of data is within reason for a
particular key, this event is likely to
happen. Therefore one over two to the
thirty is non-negligible. On the other
hand, we'll say that one over two to the
eighty. Which is much, much, much smaller
is an event, an event that happens with
this probability is an event that's
actually not going to happen over the life
of the key. And therefore we'll say that
that's a negligible event. As it turns
out, these practical definitions of
negligible and non-negligible are quite
problematic and we'll see examples of why
they're problematic later on. So in fact
in the more rigerous theory of
cryptography, the definition of negligible
and non-negligible are somewhat different.
And in fact, when we talk about the
probability of an event, we don't talk
about these probabilities as scalers, but
rather we talk about them as functions of
a security parameter. So let me explain
what that means. So these functions,
essentially, are functions that map, that
outputs, positive real values. So, are non
negative real values that are supposedly
probabilities. But they're functions that
act on non negative integers, okay? So,
what does it mean for a function to be
non-negligible? What it means is that the
function is bigger than some polynomial
infinitely often. In other words, for
many, for infinitely many values, the
function is bigger than some, one over
polynomial, okay? So I wrote the exact
definition here, and we'll see an example,
in just a minute. Okay? So if something is
bigger, is often bigger than one of that
polynomial, we'll say that it's non-negligible.
However, if something is
smaller than all polynomials, then we'll
say that it's negligible. So, what this
says here, basically, for any degree
polynomial, for all d, there exists some
lower bound lambda-d such as, for all
lambda bigger than this lambda-d, the
function is smaller than one over the
polynomial. So all this says is that the
function is negligible if it's less than
all polynomial fractions. In other words, is
less than one over lambda-d for
sufficiently large lambda. So let's look
at some examples. And we'll see
applications of these negligible and
non-negligible concepts later on. But I
just want to make, wanted to make it clear
that this is how you would rigorously find
these concepts. Basically either smaller
than one over poly or bigger than one over
poly, one would be negligible, the
other would be non-negligible. Let's look
at some examples. So, for example, a
function that drops exponentially in
lambda clearly would be negligible because
for any constant d there is a sufficiently
large, large lambda. Such as one over two
to the lambda is less than one over lambda
to the d. Okay. So this is clearly less
than all polynomials. Over the function,
say, one over lambda to a thousand, right.
This is a function that grows very, very,
very slowly. It barely ever moves.
Nevertheless, this function is
non-negligible because if I set d to be
10,000, then clearly this function is
bigger than one over lambda to the 10,000.
And so this function is bigger than some
polynomial fraction. And lets look at a
confusing example, just to be tricky. What
do you think? Suppose I have a function that for
an odd lambda it happens to be exponentially small,
for even lambda, it happens to be
polynomially small. Is this a negligible or
non-negligible function? Well, by our
definition this would a non-negligible
function. And the intuition is, if a
function happens to be only polynomially
small, very often, that actually means
that this event, you know, an event
that happens with this probability, is
already too large to be used in a real
cryptosystem. Okay, so, the main points to
remember here, are that these terms,
basically, correspond to less than
polynomial or more than polynomial, but
throughout the course, we'll mostly use
negligible to mean less than, than an
exponential. And non-negligible to mean,
less than one over polynomial. So now we
saw the core idea for converting the one
time pad into a practical cipher. And I
mean, the stream cipher. And then, in the
next lecture, we're gonna see how to
actually argue that the stream cipher is
actually secure. That's gonna require a
new definition of security, since perfect
secrecy is not good enough here, and we
will see that in the next lecture.