Now that we understand stream ciphers,
we're gonna move on and talk about a more
powerful primitive called a block cipher.
So a block cipher is made up of two
algorithms, E and D. These are encryption
and decryption algorithms. And both of
these algorithms take, as input, a key K.
Now, the point of a block cipher is that
it takes an N bit plain text as input, and
it outputs exactly the same number of bits
as outputs. So it maps N bits on inputs to
exactly N bits of outputs. Now there are
two canonical examples of block ciphers.
The first one is called triple-DES. In
triple-DES the block size, namely the
number of input bits, is 64. So triple-DES
will map 64-bit blocks to 64-bit blocks
and it does it using a key that's 168 bits long.
We're gonna talk about how Triple DES is built in the next segment.
Another block cipher, which is more
recent, is called AES. Now, AES has
slightly different parameters. So, here
the block size is 128 bits.
So, AES will map a 128 bits of input to 128 bits of output.
And it actually has three possible sizes of keys, and I wrote down these sizes over here.
Basically the longer the key, the slower the cipher is,
but presumably the
more secure it is to break and we're gonna
talk about what it means for block ciphers
to be secure in just a minute. Now block
ciphers are typically built by iteration. They
take in as input a key K, for example
in the case of AES the key could be 128
bits long, and the first thing that
happens to the key is that it gets expanded
into a sequence of keys K1 to Kn called
round keys. Now, the way the cipher
uses these round keys is by iteratively
encrypting the message again and again and
again using what's called a round
function. So here we have this function R
that take two inputs. This function R is
gonna be called a round function. It takes
as input the round key, and it takes as
input the current state of the message.
So here we have our input message. Say,
for AES, the message would be 128 bits
exactly, because each block in AES is
exactly 128 bits. And then the first thing
that happens is we apply the first round
function using the key K1 to the
message. And we get some new message out,
as a result. Then we take this message m1, we apply the next round function to
it using a different key, using the key k2.
Then we get the next round message out.
And so on and so forth until all the
rounds have been applied and then the
final output is actually the result of the
cipher. And again this would be also
in the case of AES, this was 128 bits. And
the resulting cipher text would also be
128 bits. Now, different ciphers have
different number of rounds, and they have
different round functions. So, for
example, for triple DES the number
of rounds is 48. And we're gonna see
exactly how the round function for triple
DES works. For AES, for
example, the number of rounds
is only ten, and again, we're gonna look
at how the round functions for AES
work as well in just a minute.
Before we do that, I just wanted to mention performance numbers.
So you can see here, these are the performance numbers
for the two typical block ciphers, triple DES and AES.
And these are the corresponding numbers for the stream ciphers
that we looked at in the previous module.
And if you see that the block ciphers are
considerably slower than stream ciphers. But we'll see that we can
do many things with block ciphers that we
couldn't do very efficiently with,
constructions like RC4. Now my goal for
this week is to show you how block ciphers work,
but more importantly I want to show
you how to use block ciphers correctly,
for either encryption or integrity or
whatever application you have in mind.
So to show you how to use block ciphers correctly, it actually
makes a lot of sense
to abstract the concept a little bit so we have a clean,
abstract concept of a block cipher
to work with. And then we can argue and reason
about what constructions are correct and
what constructions are incorrect. And so
an abstraction, it's a very elegant abstraction of a
block cipher is what's called a pseudorandom function, a pseudorandom
permutation. So let me explain what these
things are. So a pseudorandom function
basically is defined over a key space, an
input space, and an output space.
And all it is, is basically a function that takes
a key and an input as inputs and outputs
some element in the output space. Okay, so
it takes an element in K, an element in X,
and outputs an element in Y. And the only
requirement essentially, is that there's
an efficient way to evaluate the function.
For functions we're not requiring that
they be invertible, we just need them to
be evaluatable, given the key and the input x.
Now, a related concept that more accurately captures what a block cipher is
it's called a pseudo-random
permutation. So a pseudo-random
permutation is, again, defined over a key
space, and then just a set X. And what it
does is it takes an element in the key
space, an element of X, and outputs,
basically, one element in X. Now, as
usual, the function E should be easy to
evaluate. So there should be an algorithm
to evaluate the function E. But more
importantly, once we fix the key K, it's
important that this function E be one-to-one.
In other words, if you think of the
space X as the set here, and here's the
same set X again, then basically the
function E, what it does, is, it's a one-to-one
function, so every element in X
gets mapped to exactly one element in X.
And then because it's one to one, of
course it's also invertible. So given some
output there's only one input that maps to
that output. And the requirement is that
there is an efficient inversion algorithm,
call it D, that given a particular output,
will output the original preimage that
mapped to that output. So really, a
pseudorandom permutation captures very
accurately and syntactically what a block
cipher is, and often I'll use the terms
interchangeably, either a block cipher or
a pseudorandom permutation. I'll use
whichever term depending on the context
where we're discussing things. Okay,
so we have two examples, as we said, of
pseudorandom permutations, triple DES and
AES, say for AES-128. The key space would
be 128 bits and the output space would be
128 bits. For Triple DES, as we said, the
block size is only 64 bits. And the key
size is 168 bits, okay. So we'll use
these running examples actually throughout, so whenever I say a PRP, concretely
you should be thinking AES or
triple DES. Now one thing that I
wanted to point out is that in fact any
pseudo-random permutation, namely any block
cipher, you can also think of it as a PRF.
In fact a PRP is a PRF that has more structure.
In particular, a PRP is a PRF where
the input space and the output space are
the same, so X is equal to Y, and in
fact is efficiently invertible once you
have the secret key k. Okay. So
in some sense a PRP is a special case of a
PRF, although that's not entirely accurate, and we'll see why in just a second.
So, so far, we just described the,
kind of, the syntactic definition of what
is a pseudo random permutation and a
pseudo random function? So now, let's talk
about what it means for a PRF or a PRP to
be secure. And this concept will
essentially capture what it means for a
block cipher to be secure, okay? So this
is why I wanted to show you these
definitions, before we look at actual
block cipher constructions, so at least
it's clear in your mind what it is we're
trying to construct. Okay, so here we have
a PRF. And I'm gonna need a little bit of
notation, not too much though, so I'm gonna
need to define the set "Funs of X, Y".
This is basically the set of all functions from
the set X to the set Y, denoted here as a
big circle, Funs[X, Y]. Now this set is
gigantic. Its size is basically, you know,
the size of Y to the size of X, so for
example for AES, remember both X and Y
would be 2 to the 128, so for AES the
size of the set is enormous. It'll be
2 to the 128 times 2 to the 128.
So it's kind of a double exponential.
So this is a gigantic number, this is more
particles than there are in the universe.
But regardless, we can kind of think of this set abstractly. We never have to kind of
write it down, we can just keep it in our head and not worry about computing on it.
So this is a particular gigantic set of the set of all functions from X to Y.
Now we're gonna look at a much smaller set of functions, namely I'll call this set
S sub F, and that's gonna denote the
set of all functions from X to Y that are
specified by the PRF as soon as we
fix the particular key k. Okay so,
we fixed the key k, we let the second
argument float, and that basically defines
a function from X to Y. Then we're going
to look at the set of all such functions
for all possible keys in the key space.
Okay, so, if you think about it again,
for AES, if we're using 128-bit keys, the size of
this, I'll say S-AES, is basically going to be
2 to the 128, so much, much, much
smaller than the set of all possible
functions from X to Y. And now, we say
that a PRF is secure, basically if a
random function in, from X to Y. So we
literally, we pick some arbitrary function
in this gigantic set of all functions from
X to Y. And we say that the PRF is secure,
if, in fact, a random function from X to Y
is indistinguishable from a pseudo-random
function from X to Y. Namely, when we pick
a random function from the set SF.
Okay. So, more precisely basically again,
the uniform distribution on the set of pseudorandom functions
is indistinguishable from the uniform distribution on the set of all functions.
Let me be just a little bit more precise,
just to give you a little bit more intuition about what I mean by that and then we'll
move on to actual constructions. So let me
a bit more precise about what it means for
a PRF to be secure. And so what we'll do
is basically the following. So we have our
adversary, who's trying to distinguish
truly random function from a pseudo-random
function. So what we'll do is let them
interact with one of the two. So here in
the top cloud, we're choosing a truly
random function. In the bottom cloud,
we're just choosing a random key for a
pseudo-random function. And now what this
adversary's gonna do is he's gonna submit
points in X. So he's gonna submit a bunch
of Xs. In fact, he's gonna do this again
and again and again. So he's gonna
submit X1, X2. X3, X4, and then for each
one of, of those queries, we're gonna give him
either the value of the truly random
function at the point X, or the value of
the pseudorandom function at the point X.
Okay, so the adversary doesn't know which
ones he's getting. By the way, for all
queries, he's always getting either the truly
random function, or the pseudorandom function. In other words, he's either
interacting with a truly random function
for all his queries, or he's interacting
with a pseudorandom function for all his
queries. And we say that the PRF is
secure if this poor adversary can't tell the
difference. He cannot tell whether he's
interacting with a truly random function
or interacting with a pseudo random
function. Okay, and we're gonna come back
actually later on and define PRFs more
precisely but for now, I wanted to give
you the intuition for what it means for PRFs to be secure
so you'll understand what it is that we're
trying to construct when we construct
these pseudorandom functions. And I
should say that the definition for a
pseudorandom permutation is pretty much
the same, except instead of choosing a
random function, we're going to choose a
random permutation on the set X. In other
words, a random one-to-one function on the
set X. The adversary can either query this
random function on the set X, or he can
query a pseudorandom permutation, and the
PRP is secure if the adversary cannot
tell the difference. Okay, so again the
goal is to make these functions and
permutations look like truly random
functions or permutations. Okay. So let's
look at a simple question. So suppose we
have a secure PRF. So we know this PRF
F. Happens to be defined in the set X. And
it so happens, you know, it outputs 128
bits every time. It so happens that this
PRF cannot be distinguished from a truly
random function from X to  to the 128.
Now we're gonna build a new PRF. Let's
call this PRF G. And the PRF G is gonna be
defined as follows. We say, if x is equal
to zero, always output zero. Otherwise,
if x is not equal to zero, just output the
value of F. So, my question to you is,
do you think this G is a secure PRF?
Well, so, the answer, of course, is that its very easy
to distinguish the function G from a random function. All the adversary has to do
is just query the function at X=0.
For a random function, the probability
that the result is gonna be zero is one
over 2 to the 128. Whereas for the
pseudo-random function, he's always gonna
get zero. Because at zero, the function is
always defined to be zero, no matter what
the key. And so all he would do is he
would say, hey, I'm interacting with a
pseudo-random function if he gets zero at X=0,
and he'll say I'm interacting with
a random function if he gets nonzero at X=0.
So it's very easy to distinguish
this G from random. So what this example shows
is that even if you have a secure PRF, it's enough that on just one known input
the output is kinda not random, the
output is fixed, and already the PRF is broken,
even though you realize that
everywhere else the PRF is perfectly
indistinguishable from random. Okay, so
let's just show you the power of PRFs.
Let's look at a very easy application. I want to
show you that in fact pseudorandom functions
directly give us a pseudorandom generator. Okay. So, let's assume we have
a pseudo random function. So this one
happens to go from N bits to N bits. And then,
let's define the following generator. Its seed space is going to be the
key space for the PRF, and its output
space is gonna be, basically, t blocks of
n bits each. Okay, so you can see the
output is a total of n times t bits for
some parameter T that we can choose. And
it turns out, basically, you can do this
very simple construction, this is
sometimes called counter mode,
where essentially, you take the PRF and you
evaluate it at zero, you evaluate it at one,
you evaluate it at two, at three, at
four, up to T, and you concatenate all these values.
That's the generator, okay?
So we basically took the key for the PRF
and we expanded it into n times t bits.
Okay. A key property of this generator is
that it's parallelizable. What I mean by that
is if you have two processors or two cores
that you can compute on, then you can have
one core compute the even entries of the
output, and you can have another core
compute the odd entries of the output.
So basically, if you have two cores, you can
make this generator run twice as fast as
it would if you only have a single core.
So the nice thing about this is, of
course, we know that pseudo-random
generators give us stream ciphers, and so
this is an example of a parallelizable stream
cipher. And I just wanted to point out
that many of the stream ciphers that we
looked at before, for example, RC4,
those were inherently sequential. So even if you
had two processors, you couldn't make the
stream cipher work any faster than if you
just had a single processor. Now the main
question is why is this generator secure?
And so here I'm only gonna give you a
little bit of intuition and we're gonna
come back and argue this more precisely
later on. But I'll just say that security
basically falls directly from the PRF property.
And the way we reason about security, is we say, well this PRF by definition
is indistinguishable from a truly random function on 128 bits.
So in other words, if I take this generator and
instead I define a generator using a truly
random function, in other words, I'll
write the output of the generator as
f(0) concatenated f(1), and so on
and so forth, using a truly random function,
then the output of the
generator using the truly random function
would be indistinguishable from
the output of the generator using
a pseudorandom function. That is the essence of
the security property of a PRF. But with
a truly random function, you notice that
the output is just truly random. Because
for a truly random function, f(0) is
a random value. f(1) is an independent
random value. f(2) is an independent
random value, and so on and so forth.
So the entire output is a truly random
output. And so with a truly random function,
a generator produces truly random outputs,
and is therefore a perfectly secure
generator. And so you see how the PRF
security property lets us argue security.
Basically, we argue that when we replace
the PRF with a truly random function, the
construction is necessarily secure, and
that says that the construction with a
pseudorandom function is also secure.
Okay? And we're gonna see a couple more
examples like this later on. So now you
understand what a block cipher is, and you
have intuition for what security
properties it's trying to achieve.
And in the next segment, we're gonna look at
constructions for block ciphers.