Over the years it became clear that DES
and triple DES are simply not designed for
modern hardware and are too slow. As a
result, NIS started a new process to
standardize in a new block cypher called
the Advanced Encryption Standard or AES
for short. Nis started it's effort in 1997
when it requested, proposals for a new
block cipher. It received fifteen
submissions a year later. And finally in
the year 2000, it adopted the cypher
called Rindall as the advanced encryption
standard. This was a cypher designed in
Belgium. We already said that it's block
size is 128 bits and it has three possible
key sizes. 128 bits, 192, and 256. Now,
the assumption is that the larger the key
size is, the more secure the block cipher
is as a pseudo random permutation. But
because it also has more rounds involved
in its operation. The slower the cipher
becomes. So the larger the key supposedly,
the more secure the cipher, but also the
slower it becomes. So for example, AES 128
is the fastest of these ciphers and AES
256 is the slowest. Now AES is built as
what?s called a substitution permutation
network. It's not a Faistl network.
Remember that in a Faistl network, half
the bit were unchanged from round to
round. In a substitution permutation
network all the bits are changed in every
round. And the network works as follows,
so here we have the first round of the
substitution permutation network, where
the first thing we do is we X or the
current state with the round key. In this
case the first round key. Then we go thru
a substitution layer, where blocks of Date
are replaced with other blocks based on
what the substitution table says. And then
we go through a permutation layer where
bits are permuted and shuffled around. And
then we do this again. We XR with an X
round key, we go thru a substitution
phase, and we're permute to dance around.
And so on, and so on, and so forth Until
we reach the final round where we x or
with the very last around key, and then
out comes the output. Now, and important
point about this design. Is that, in fact,
because of how it's built, every step in
this network needs to be reversible, so
that the whole thing is reversible. And so
the way we would, decrypt, essentially, is
we would take the output and simply apply
each step of the network in reverse order.
So we start with the permutation step, and
we have to make sure that step is
reversible. Then we look at the
substitution layer, and we have to make
sure this step is reversible. And this is
very different from DES. In DES, if you
remember, the substitution tables were not
reversible at all. In fact, they
map six bits to four bits. Whereas
here, everything has to be reversible,
otherwise it would be impossible to
decrypt. And of course the x or with the
round key is reversible as well. Okay? So
inversion of a substitution permutation
network is simply done by applying all of
the steps in the reverse order. So now
that we understand the generic
construction. Lets look at the specifics
of AS. So AS operates on a 128 bit block.
Which is sixteen bytes. So what we do with
AS is we write those sixteen bytes as a
four by four matrix. Each cell in the
matrix contains one byte. And then we
start with the first round so we X over
with the first round key and then apply a
certain function. That, includes
substitutions and permutations and other
operations on the state. And again, these
three functions that are applied here have
to be invertible so that in fact the
cypher can be decrypted. And then we xor
with the next round key and we do that
again. Again we apply the round function
and xor the round key. And we do that
again and again and again. We do it ten
times. Although interestingly in the last
round, the mix column step is actually
missing. And then finally, we XOR with the
last rounds key, and out comes the output.
Again, in every phase here, we always,
always, always keep this four by four
array. And so the output is also four by
four, which is sixteen bytes, which is 128
bits. Now the long key themselves of
course come from a sixteen byte AS key
using key expansion. So the key expansion
maps from a sixteen bytes AS key
into eleven keys, each one being sixteen
bytes. So these keys themselves are also a
four by four array that's XORed into the
current state. Okay, so that's the
schematic of how AES works. And the only
thing that's left to do is specify these
three functions, byte sub, shift row, and
mixed column. And those are fairly easy to
explain. So I'm just gonna give you the
high level description of what they are.
And, those interested in the details can
look it up online. So the way byte
substitution works, is literally it's one
S box containing 256 bytes. And
essentially, what it does is it applies
the S box to every byte in the current
states. So, let me explain what I mean by
that. So the current state is gonna be
this four by four, table. So here we have
the four by four table. And to each
element in this table, we apply the S box.
So let's call it the A table. And then
what we do is, essentially, for all four
by four entries, essentially, the next
step, Aij. Becomes the current step
evaluated at the look up table. So we use
the current cell as an entry, as an index,
into the look up table. And then the value
of the look up table is what's output.
Okay. So, that's the first step. The next
step that happens is a shift pro step,
which is basically just a permutation. So
essentially we kind of do a stick lick
shift on each one of the rows. So you can
see the second row is stick lick shifted
by one position. This third row is
[inaudible] shifted by two positions and
the third row is [inaudible] shifted by
three positions. And the last thing we do
is mix columns where literally we apply a
linear transformation to each one of these
columns. So there's a certain matrix that
multiplies each one of these columns and
it becomes, the next column. So these
linear transformation is applied
independently to each one of the columns.
Now, I should point out that, so far,
shift rows and mixed columns are very easy
to implement in code. And I should say
that the [inaudible] institution itself is
also easily computable, so that you can
actually write code that takes less than
256 bytes to write. And you can kind of
shrink the description of AES by literally
storing code that computes the table
rather than hardwiring the table into your
implementation. And in fact, this is kind
of a generic fact about AES, that if you
can have allowed no pre computation at
all, including computing the S box on the
fly. Then in fact you get a fairly small
implementation of AES, so it, it could fit
on very constrained environments where
there isn't enough room to hold,
complicated code. But of course, this will
be the slowest implementation, because
everything is computed now on the fly, and
as a result, the implementation,
obviously, is gonna be, slower than things
that were pre-computed. And then there is
this trade off. For example if you have a
lot of space, and you can support large
code. You can actually precompute quite a
bit of the three steps that I just
mentioned. In fact, there are multiple
options of pre-computation, you can build
a table that's only four kilobyte big. You
can build a table that is even longer,
maybe 24 kilobytes. So basically you will
have these big tables in your
implementation. But then your actual
performance is going to be really good,
because all your doing is just table
look-ups and XORs. You're not doing
any other complicated arithmetic. And as a
result, if you can do a lot of
pre-computation, these three steps here,
[inaudible] should. [inaudible] and mixed
columns can be converted just into a
number, a small number of table lookups
and some [inaudible]. All you can do is
just compute the S box, so now your
implementation would just have 256 bytes.
Hard coded The rest would just be code
that's actually computing these three
functions. The performance would be slower
than in the previous step but the code
footprint would also be smaller. So in
overall, there's this nice tradeoff
between code size and performance. So on
high-end machines, on high-end servers,
where you can afford to have a lot of
code, you can precompute and store these
big tables and get the best performance.
Whereas on low-end machines like eight
byte smart cards or think of like an eight
byte wristwatch, you would actually have a
relatively small implementation of AES.
But as a result of course it won't be so
fast. So here's an example that's a little
unusual, suppose you wanted to implement
AES in Javascript so you can send an AES
library to the browser and have the
browser actually do AES by itself. So in
this case what you'd like to, to is you'd
like to both shrink the code size, so that
on the network there's minimum traffic to
send a library over to the browser but, at
the same time, you'd like the browser
performance to be as fast as possible. And
so this is something that we did a while
ago essentially the idea is that the code
that actually gets send to the browser
doesn't have any pre computer table and as
a result is fairly small code. But then
the minute it lands on the browser, what
the browser will do is actually pre
compute all the tables. So in some sense
the code goes from just being small and
compact. It gets bloated with all these
precomputed tables. But those are stored
on the laptop, which presumably has a lot
of memory. And then once you have the
precomputed tables you actually encrypt
using them. And that's how you get the
best performance. Okay? So if you have to
stand in implementation AES over the
network, you can kind of get the best of
all worlds. Whereas, the code over the
network is small, but when it reaches the
target client, it can kind of inflate
itself. And then get the best performance
as it's doing encryption on the clients.
Now AES is such a popular block cipher,
now essentially when you build crypto into
products essentially your supposed to be
using AES, and as a result Intel actually
put AES support into the processor itself.
So since Westmere there are special
instructions in the Intel processor to
help accelerate AES. And so I listed these
instructions here. They come in two pairs,
aesenc and aesenclast. And then, there's aesekygenassist. So, let me explain
what they do. So, aesenc essentially
implements one round of AES. Namely, apply
the three functions in the XOR with the
round key. And aesenclast basically
implements the last round of AES.
Remember, the last round didn't have the
mix columns phase. It only had the subs
bytes and shift rows. And so that's why
the aesenclast does. And the way you
call these instructions is using 128 byte
registers which correspond to the states
of AES. And so you would have one register
containing the states and one register
containing the current round key. And then
when you call AES on these two registers,
basically, they would run one round of AES
and place the result inside of this XMM
one state register. And as a result if you
wanted to implement the whole AES. All you
would do is, call aesenc nine times. Then
you would call aesenclast one time. These
ten instructions are basically the entire
implementation of AES. That's it. It's that
easy to implement AES on this hardware
and they claim because these operations
are now done inside the processor not
using external instructions that are
implemented in the processor. They claim
that they can get a fourteen X speedup
over say an implementation that's running
in the same hardware but implementing AES without these special instructions. So
this is quite a significant speed up and
the facts are now lots of. Products that
make use of these special instructions.
And let's just say that this is not
specific to Intel, if you're in
[inaudible], and they also implemented
exactly kinda similar instructions in
their bulldozer architecture and further
and future architectures. Okay, so let's
talk about the security of AES. I wanna
mention just two attacks here. Obviously,
AES has been studied quite a bit. But the
only two attacks on the full AES are the
following two. So, first of all, if you
wanted to do key recovery, the best
attack, basically, is only four times
faster than exhaustive search. Which mean
that instead of a hundred and. 28 bits
key, really you should be thinking of AES.
Is 126 bit key. Cause exhaustive search,
really it's gonna four times faster than
it should. Of course due to the 126, it's
still. More time than we have to compute,
and this really does not hurt the security
alias. The more significant attack is,
actually, on AES-256. It turns out there's a
weakness in the key expansion design of
aes which allows for, what's called a
related key attack. So, what's a related
key attack? Essentially, if you give me
about two to the 100 input output pairs
for aes, but from four related keys. So,
these are keys that are very closely
related, namely key number one. Is just
one bit flip of key #two, which is just
one flip, bit flip of key #three, which is
just one flip bit flip of key #four. These
are very closely related keys, if you like
your [inaudible] distances very short. But
if you do that, then, in fact, there is a
two to the 100 attack. Now you should say,
well, two to the 100 is still impractical.
This is still more time than we can
actually run today. But nevertheless, the
fact that it's so much better than an
exhaustive search attack, it's so much
better than two to the 56, is kind of a
limitation of the cipher. But generally,
it's not a significant limitation, because
it requires related keys. And so, in
practice, of course, you're supposed to be
choosing your keys at random, so that you
have no related keys in your system. And
as a result, this attack wouldn't apply.
But if you do have related keys, then
there's a problem. So this is the end of
the segment, and in the next segment we're
gonna talk about more provably secure
constructions for block ciphers.