So now that we understand what block
ciphers are, let's look at a classic
example called the Data Encryption
Standard. So, just a quick reminder. Block
ciphers basically map N bits of input to N
bits of output. And we talked about two
canonical examples, triple DES and AES. In
this segment, we're gonna talk about DES,
and we'll talk about triple DES, actually,
in the next segment. And then I also
mentioned before that block ciphers are
often built by iteration. In particular,
we're gonna look at block ciphers that are
built by a form of iteration where a key K
is first expanded into a bunch of round
keys. And then a round function is applied
to the input message, again and again and
again. And essentially, after all these
round functions are applied, we obtain the
resulting cipher text, okay? And again,
what we're gonna look at, how DES, the
data encryption standard, uses this
format. I just wanna be clear that, in
fact, to specify a block cipher of this
type, one needs to specify the key
expansion mechanism, and one needs to
specify the round function. In the segment
here, I'm gonna focus on the round
function, and I'm not gonna talk much
about key expansion. But I just wanted to
mention that, in fact, key expansion is
also a big part of describing how block
cipher works. Okay, so let's talk about
the history of DES. Essentially, in the
early 1970s, IBM realized that their
customers are demanding some form of
encryption. And so they formed a crypto
group, and the head of that group, was
Horst Feistel, who, in the early 70s,
designed a cipher called Lucifer. Now,
it's interesting. In fact Lucifer had a
number of variations but one of the later
variations in fact had a key length that
was 128 bits and a block length that's
also 128 bits. Okay, in 1973 the governor
realized that it's buying many commercial
off-the-shelf computers and so it wanted
its suppliers to actually have a good grip
to algorithm that they could use in
products sold to the government. So in
1973 the National Bureau of Standards as
it was called at the time put out a
request for proposals for a block cipher
that is going to become a federal
standard. And in fact IBM submitted a
variant of Lucifer. That variant actually
went through some modification during the
standardization process and then finally
in 1976, the national bureau standard
adopted DES as a federal standard. And, in
fact, for DES it's interesting that the
key length was far reduced from Lucifer.
It's only 56 bits. And the block length
was also reduced to 64 bits. And in
fact, these decisions, especially the
decision to reduce the key length, is
going to be a key length yield of DES and
was a source of many complaints over its
life. In particular, already back in 1997,
DES was broken by exhaustive search
meaning that a machine was able to search
through all two to the 56 possible keys to
recover a particular challenge key. And in
fact we're going to talk about exhaustive
search quite a bit. It's quite an
interesting question, and there are
various ways to defend against exhaustive
search. And basically this 1997 experiment
kinda spelled the doom of DES. It meant
that DES is itself, is no longer secure.
And as a result, the National Institute of
Standards, as it became known, issued a
request for proposals. For our next
generation's block cipher standard and in
2000 it standardized on a cipher called Rijndael.
Which became the advanced encryption
standard, AES. And we'll talk about AES
later on. But in this segment, I wanna
describe how DES works. Now, DES is a
cipher, it's an amazingly successful
cipher. It's been used in the banking
industry. In fact, there's a classic
network called the Electronic
Clearinghouse, which banks use to clear
checks with one another. And DES is used
for integrity in those transactions. It's
also used in commerce. In fact, it was
very popular up until recently, as the
main encryption mechanism for the web. Of
course, now, that's been replaced with AES
and other ciphers. Overall, it's a
very successful cipher in terms of
deployment. DES also has a very rich
history of attacks, which we'll talk about
in the next segment. Okay, so now, let's
talking about the construction of DES. So,
the core idea behind DES is what's called
a Feistel network, due to Horst Feistel.
And basically, it's a very clever idea for
building the block cipher out of arbitrary
functions, F1 to FD. Okay so imagine we
have these functions F1 to FD
that happens to match n bits to n bits.
Now these are arbitrary functions,
they don't have to be invertible or
anything. What we want to do is build an
invertible function out of those D
functions and the way we'll do it is by
building a new function we'll call capital
F that maps 2n bits to 2n bits.
And the construction is described right
here. So here we have our inputs. You
notice, there are two blocks of n bits.
In other words, the input is actually
2n bits. The R and L stand for right and
left. Typically, people describe a
Feistel network from top to bottom. In
which case, these n bits really would be
right and left. But here it is more
convenient for me to describe it
horizontally. So if we follow the R
inputs. You realize it basically gets
copied into the L output, without any
change at all. Okay? However, the L
inputs, is changed somewhat. What happens
is, basically, the R inputs is fit into
the function F1 and the result is then
XORed with L0 and that becomes the new R1
input. Okay, so this is called one round
of a Feistel network, and is done using
the function F1. Now we do this again with
another round of the Feistel network
with the function F2, and we do it again
and again and again, 'till we get to the
last round, and we do it again with the
function FD. And finally, the output is
Rd Ld. Okay. So, if you like, we can write
this in symbols. That basically, Li is
simply equal to Ri-1. And Ri,
let's see, that's the more complicated
one. Ri is equal, well, let's just follow
the lines here. Ri is just equal to Fi
applied to, Ri-1 XOR Li. Okay?
So this, and this is basically, i goes
from, 1 to d. So this is the, equation
that defines a Feistel network, mapping a
2n bit input to 2n bit outputs. So
here we have the, again, I just copied the
picture of the Feistel network. And the
amazing claim is that, in fact, it doesn't
matter which functions you give me. For
any functions, F1 to FD that you give me,
the resulting Feistel network function is,
in fact, invertible. And the way we're
going to prove that is basically we're
going to construct an inverse, because not
only is it invertible, it's efficiently
invertible. So let's see. So let's look at
one round of a Feistel network, so
here, this is the inputs, Ri Li, and this
is the output Ri+1, Li+1. And now what I'm
going to ask you is to invert this.
So let's see. So suppose now the input that
we're given is Ri+1, Li+1 and we want to
compute Ri Li. So we want to compute the
round in the reverse direction. So let's
see if we can do it. Well, let's look at
Ri. So, Ri is very easy. Basically, Ri is
just equal to Li+1. So Li+1 just becomes
Ri. But now, let me ask you, to write the
expression for Li in terms of Ri+1, and Li+1.
So I hope everybody sees that, basically, Li+1
is fed into the function Fi+1.
The result is XORed with Ri+1,
and that gives the Li input.
So this the inverse of one round
of a Feistel network.
And if we draw this as a diagram, let's just
write the picture for the inverse.
So here you notice the input is Ri+1, Li+1
and the output is Ri Li. Right?
So we're computing, we're inverting, the
rounds. So you notice that the inverse of
a Feistel round looks pretty much the
same as the Feistel round in the
forward direction. It's literally, you
know, just for a technical reason, it's
kinda the mirror image of one another. But
it's basically, the same construct. And
when we put these inverted rounds back
together. We essentially get the inverse
of the entire Feistel network. So you
notice we start off with the round number D
with the inverse of round number D,
then we do the inverse of round number D-1
and so on and so forth until we
get to the inverse of the first round. And
we get our final outputs which is R0, L0,
like this is the inputs and we manage to
invert basically Rd, Ld and get R0, L0
and the interesting thing is that
basically these inversion circuits look
pretty much the same as the encryption
circuits and the only difference is that
the functions are applied in reverse order.
Right we started with Fd and ended with
F1. Whereas when we were encrypting, we
started with F1 and ended with Fd. So, for
hardware designers, this is very
attractive, because, basically, if you
wanna save hardware, you realize that your
encryption hardware is identical to your
decryption hardware. So you only have to
implement one algorithm, and you get both
algorithms the same way. The only
difference is that the functions are
applied in reverse order. Okay. So this
Feistel mechanism is a general method
for building invertible functions from
arbitrary functions F1 to Fd and in fact,
it's used in many different block ciphers.
Although, interestingly, it's not actually
used in AES. So, there are many other
block ciphers that use a Feistel
network. Or, of course, they differ from
DES in the functions F1 to Fd. But AES
actually uses a completely different type
of structure that's actually not a
Feistel network. We'll see how AES
works in a couple of segments. So now that
we know what Feistel networks are, let
me mention an important theorem about the
theory of Feistel networks that shows
why they're a good idea. This theorem is
due to Luby and Rackoff back in 1985, and it
says the following. Suppose I have a
function that is a secure pseudorandom
function, okay. So it's indistinguishable
from random and happens to act on N bits.
So it maps N bits to N bits and uses a
key K. Then, it turns out, that if you use
this function in three rounds of a Feistel
network. What you end up with is a secure
pseudo random permutation. In other words,
what you end up with is an invertible
function that is indistinguishable from a
truly random invertible function. And I
hope you remember that the true definition
of a secure block cipher is that it needs
to be a secure pseudo random permutation.
So what this theorem says, is that if you
start with a secure pseudo random
function, you end up with a secure block
cipher. Basically, that's what this is.
And let me explain in a little bit more
detail what's actually going on here. So,
essentially, the PRF is used in every
round of the Feistel network. So, in
other words, here, what's actually
computed is the PRF using one secret key,
K0. Here, what's computed is the PRF
using a different secret key, of course
applied to R1. And here we have yet
another secret key, K1 applied, K2 applied
to R2. And you notice, this is why,
basically this Feistel construction,
uses keys in K cubed. In other words, it
uses three independent keys. So it's very
important that the keys are actually
independent. So really, we need three,
independent keys. And then we end up with
a secure pseudorandom permutation. Okay,
so that's the theory behind Feistel
networks. And now that we understand that,
we can actually look at the specifics of DES.
So DES is basically a sixteen round
Feistel network, okay. So there are
functions F1 to F16 that map 32 bits to
32 bits, and as a result, the DES itself
acts on 64 bit blocks, 2x32. Now the
sixteen round functions in DES are
actually all derived from a single
function F. Just used with different keys.
So in fact, these are the different round
keys. So Ki is, a round key. And it's
basically derived from the key K, derived
from the 56 bit DES key K. Okay and I'll
describe what this function F is in just a
minute. But basically that, you see that
by using sixteen different round keys, we
get sixteen different round functions. And
that gives us the Feistel network. So just
on a high level how the DES works
basically you have a 64 bit input. The
first thing it does is, this initial
permutation that just permutes the 64 bits
around. Namely it maps bit number one to
bit number six. Bit number two to bit
number seventeen, and so on. This is not
for security reasons, this is just
specified in the standard. Then we go into
the sixteen round Feistel network. That
actually, you now know how it works.
Basically uses the function F1 to F16, as
specified before. And then, basically we
have another permutation, it's called the
final permutation. That's just the inverse
of the initial permutation. Again,
it just permutes bits around, this is not
necessary for security reasons. And then
we finally get, the final outputs. Okay.
Now, as we said, there's a key expansion
step, which I'm not gonna describe. But
basically, this 56-bit DES key is expanded
into these rounds keys. Where each round
key, is 48 bits. Okay, so we have sixteen
48 bit round keys, and they're basically
used in the sixteen rounds of DES. And
then when you want to invert the cipher,
all you do is you use these, round keys,
these sixteen round keys, in reverse
order. Okay, so now that we understand the
DES structure, the only thing that's left
to do is specify the function, capital F.
So let me explain how this function works.
So basically, it takes, as inputs, its, 32
bit value, let's call it X. But in
reality, you remember, this is R0,
R1, R-2, R3, so on and so
forth. These are 32 bit values. And then
it takes, also, a 48 bit round key. So
here we have our key Ki, which happens to
be 48 bits. The first thing it does, is it
goes through an expansion box. And this
expansion box basically take thirty two
bits, and maps them into 48 bits. Now, all
the expansion box does is just replicates
some bits, and move other bits around. So,
for example, bit #1 of X is replicated
into positions 2 and 48 in the output.
Bit #2 of X is positioned in as bit
#3 of the output. And so on and so
forth, just by replicating some of the
bits of X, we expand the input into 48
bits. The next thing we do is we compute
an XOR with the round key.
Sometimes people say that cryptographers
only compute XORs. This is an example of
that, where, well, we just do XORs in this
function. And then comes the magic of DES,
where, actually, these 48 bits are broken
into eight groups of six bits. Six, seven,
eight. And so let me draw, and then what
happens is, so yes. Each one of these,
each one of these wires is, six bits. And
then they, they go into what, what are
called S boxes. And I'll explain S boxes
in just a minute. The S boxes are kind of
the smarts of, DES. And then, the S
box is basically a map, six bits to four
bits. So, the outputs of the S boxes are
these four bits. They're collected. This
gives up 32 bits, right? Eight groups of
four bits, gives us 32 bits and then
finally this is fed into yet another
permutation which just maps the bits
around. So, for example bit number one
will go to bit number nine, bit number two
will go to bit number fifteen and so on.
So it just permutes the 32 bits around and
that's the final 32 bit output of this F function.
Okay? So by using different
round keys, essentially, we get different
round functions, and that's how we form
the sixteen round functions of DES. Now,
the only thing that, left to specify are
these S boxes. So the S boxes, literally,
are just functions from six bits to four
bits. They are just implemented as a look
up table. Right? So describing a function
from six bits to four bits basically
amounts to writing the output of the
function on all two to the six possible inputs.
Two to the six is 64. So we just
have a table that literally contains 64 values.
Where each value is four bits. So
here is an example, this happens to be the
fifth S box, and you see that this is a
table that contains 64 values right?
It's four by sixteen. So, 64 values. For
example, if you wanna look at, the output,
that corresponds to 0-1-1-0-1-1. Okay, then
you look at these two bits. This is 01,
and these four bits are 1101, and you see
that the output is 1001. The four bits
output 1001. Okay, so the S boxes are just
implemented as these tables.
Now the question is, how are these S boxes chosen.
How are these tables actually chosen by
the designers of this. So to give you some
intuitions for that, lets start with a
very bad choice for S boxes. So imagine
the S boxes were linear. What do I mean by
that? I mean that imagine that these six
bit inputs literally were just
XORed with one another in different
ways to produce the four bit outputs.
Okay, another way of writing that is that
we can write the S box as a matrix vector product.
So here you have the matrix Ai.
And the vector, the six bit vector X.
And you can see that, if we write this matrix
vector product, basically, we take the
inner product of this vector with the
input vector. Remember, these are all bits.
So the six bits vector inner
product. Another six bit vector, and we do
that modulo two, you realize, basically,
what we're computing is X2 XOR X3.
Right? Because only position two and
position three have 1's in it.
And similarly the next, inner product will
produce X1 XOR X4 XOR X5 and so on and
so forth. Okay. So you can literally see
that if the S boxes are implemented this
way. Then, all they do, is just apply the
matrix A to the input vector X. Which is
why we say, that in this case the S boxes
are completely linear. Now, I claimed that
in fact that if the S boxes were linear, then DES
would be totally insecure. The reason is,
if the S boxes are linear, then all that
DES does is just compute XOR of various
things and permute and shuffle bits
around. So it's just XORs and bit
permutations, which means that as a
result, all of DES is just a linear
function. In other words, there will be a
Matrix B. Of these dimensions. Basically,
it's a matrix B that has width 832.
Basically what I will do is I will write
the 64 bit message plus the sixteen round
keys as one long vector. Alright, so the
message is 64 bits and there are sixteen
round keys. Each one is 48 and that, if
you do the math, it's basically 832. Okay?
So I write these values, the keys and the
message, as one long vector and then there
will be this matrix that essentially when
you compute these matrix vector products.
Essentially you get the different bits of
the ciphertext. So there's 64 of these
rows and as a result, you get 64 bits of
ciphertext. Okay, so this is what it
means for DES to be linear. So if you
think a little bit about this, you realize
that the S boxes are the only nonlinear
part of DES. So if the S boxes were
linear, then the entire circuit is linear
and therefore can be expressed as this
matrix. Now if that's the case then DES
would be terrible as a secure pseudorandom
permutation. And let me give you a very
simple example. Basically if you did the
XOR of three outputs of DES, well
let's think what that means. Basically we
would be looking at B times, the matrix B
that defines DES, times, one vector
XOR B times another vector,
XOR B times a third vector. We
could take the B out of the parentheses so
we'd be basically doing B times this
vector over here. But of course K XOR K XOR K,
this is just K. And so if you
think about what that means, basically we
just got back DES of K at the point M1 XOR M2 XOR M3. But this means that now DES
has this horrible relation. That can be
tested. Right? So, basically, if you
XOR the output of three values,
M1, M2, M3, you'll get the value of
DES, at the point M1 XOR M2 XOR M3. Now this
is not a relation that is going to hold
for a random function. A random function
is not going to satisfy this equality.
And so you get a very easy test to tell you
that DES is not a random function.
In fact, maybe you can take that as a small
exercise. It's not even difficult to see,
that given enough input output pairs, you
can literally recover the entire secret key.
Yeah. You just need 832 input output
pairs, and you'll be able recover the
entire secret key. And so if the S boxes
were linear, DES would be completely
insecure. It turns out, actually, even if
the S boxes were close to being linear. In
other words, the S boxes were linear most
of the time. So maybe for 60 out of the 64
inputs, the S boxes were linear. It turns
out that would also be enough to break
DES, and we're gonna see why later on. In
particular, if you choose the S boxes at
random, it turns out they'll tend to be
somewhat close to linear functions. As a
result, you'll be able to totally break
DES. You'll just be able to recover the
key, in basically, very little time. And
so, the designers of DES actually
specified a number of rules they use for
choosing the S boxes. And it's not
surprising, the first rule is that these
functions are far away from being linear.
Okay. So, in other words, there is no
function that agrees with a large fraction
of the outputs of the S box. And then
there are all these other rules, for
example, there are exactly four to one
maps, right? So, every output has exactly
four pre-images and so on and so forth. So
we understand now why they chose the S
boxes they way they did and in fact its
all done to defeat certain attacks on DES.
Okay. So that's the end of the
description of DES, and in the next few
segments we are going to look at the
security of DES.