In this segment and the next, I wanna show
you two very cute attacks on deployed
authenticated encryption systems. But
first let's do a quick recap. So recall
that authenticated encryption means that
the system provides CPA security plus
cipher text integrity. And authenticated
encryption means that we can preserve
confidentiality in the presence of an
active adversary, and moreover, the
adversary can't modify the cipher text in
any way without being detected. We also
showed that authenticated encryption
prevents these very powerful chosen cipher
text attacks. Unfortunately, authenticated
encryption has a pretty significant
limitation in that it simply can't help a
bad implementation. If you implement
authenticated encryption incorrectly, then
your implementation will be vulnerable to
active attacks. And then we looked at
standards constructions. I mentioned these
three standards that provide authenticated
encryption. And I want to point out, when
you need to use authenticated encryption
in practice, you should just be using one
of these three standards. You shouldn't
try to implement authenticated encryption
by yourself, and I hope that the attack
that I'll show you in this segment
convinces you that this is not something
you should do yourself. Just use one of
GCM, CCM or EAX. However, it's good for
you to know that in general, when you want
to provide authenticated encryption, the
correct way to do things is encrypt, then
MAC, because then no matter which
encryption and MAC algorithms you combine.
The result will be authenticated
encryption, again assuming the encryption
and Mac algorithm are implemented
correctly. Okay, so let's look at a very
acute attack on the TLS record protocol.
In particular, when CBC encryption is
used. Let me just briefly remind you that
the way TLS decryption works, is, first of
all, an incoming cipher text is CBC
decrypted. Then the next thing that
happens is the implementation will check
if the pad has the correct format. For
example, if the pad is of length five, the
format should be 55555. And if it's not of
the correct format. Then the cipher text
is rejected. So this basically checks that
the ending of the decrypted record
contains the correct pad. And then if the
pad has the correct format, then the next
thing that happens is that the MAC is
checked, the tag is checked. And if the
tag turns out to be incorrect, again, the
record is rejected. If the tag is valid,
then the remaining data is considered to
be authentic and is given to the
application. So what I wanted to point out
is there are two types of errors in TLS
decryption. One is a padding error and one
is a MAC error. And it turns out it's very
important that the adversary not be told
which of these errors occurred. And let me
briefly explain why. So, suppose an
attacker can actually differentiate the
two types of errors. In other words, he
can tell if a pad error occurred, or a Mac
error occurred. The result is what we call
the padding oracle. ?Cause now, imagine
the adversary has a certain cipher text
that it intercepted. And it wants to try
and decrypt that cipher text. What it
could do, is it could take that cipher
text as is, and submit it to the server.
The server is gonna decrypt the cipher
text and then look to see if the pad has
the correct format. If the pad doesn't
have the correct format, we'll get one
type of error. If the pad has the correct
format, it's very likely since this is
just some random cipher text that the
adversary concocted himself, it's very
likely the mac will be incorrect, and then
the adversary will observe a mac error. So
if the pad is invalid, we'll see a pad
error, whereas if the pad is valid we'll
see a mac error. As a result, the
adversary, after submitting the cipher
text to the server, the adversary can tell
whether the last bytes in the decrypted
cipher text have a valid pad or not. In
other words, whether the last bites in the
decrypted cipher text are end with one. Or
2-2, or 3-3-3, or 4-4-4-4, and so on. So
the adversary learns something about the
decrypted cipher text, just by submitting
the cipher text to the server. So this is
a beautiful example of what's called a
chosen cipher text attack. Where again,
the address that you submit the cipher
text and then he gets to learn something
about the resulting plain text. And now
the question is whether he can use that
information to completely decrypt a given
cipher text. And I want to show you that a
padding oracle can actually be used to
completely decrypt a given cipher text.
But before I say that, I want to remind
you that older versions of TLS. Actually
leaked the type of error simply in the
alert message that was sent back to the
peer. Different types of alerts were sent
depending on which type of error occurred.
As soon as this attack came out, SSL
implementations simply always reported the
same type of error, so just looking at the
alert type wouldn't tell the adversary
which error occurred. Nevertheless, there
was still a padding oracle. So let me
explain why. So this was observed by Canvel
et. al. Canvel et. al. realized that
the way TLS decryption is implemented is
first of all, the record is decrypted,
then the pad is checked, and if the pad is
invalid, decryption is aborted and an
error is generated. If the pad is valid.
Then the Mac is checked. And then if the
Mac is invalid, decryption is aborted, and
an error is generated. As a result, this
causes a timing attack. You realize that
if pad is invalid, then the alert message
is sent very quickly. And you notice here,
that, in fact, you see that, within 21
milliseconds, the cipher text is rejected.
However, if the pad is valid. Then now the
math needs to be checked, and when it's
discovered to be invalid, the alert is
only generated at that point. In other
words, then in that case it takes a little
bit longer until the alert is generated,
and you see that on average this takes
about 23 milliseconds. So even though the
same alert is sent back to the peer. The
adversary can simply observe the time
until the alert message is generated. If
the time is short, it knows the pad was
invalid. If the time is long, it knows the
pad was valid, but the Mac was invalid.
And as a result the adversary still has a
padding oracle that can tell it whether
the pad was valid or invalid. So now let's
see how to use a padding oracle. So I
claim that if the attacker has a certain
cipher text C, he can completely decrypt
the cipher text just using the padding
oracle. So let's see how to do it. And
just as an example, suppose he wants to
obtain M1, in other words, a decryption of
the second block of the cipher text. So
let's see what he would use. So here we
have the cipher text that the attacker
intercepted. And this just happens to be
the decryption of that cipher text. And
the reason I wrote this down is I wanted
you to remember how CBC decryption works.
So you should keep in mind that one cipher
text block is directly [inaudible] into
the decryption of the next cipher text
block. Okay, so the adversary here wants
to basically learn just this part of the
plain text. So, here's what he's gonna do.
So first of all he's going to throw away
C2 so that, that last block really is just
C1, which is the one he's interested in
decrypting. Now let's suppose that he has
a certain guess, G, for the last byte of
M1, in other words, he just has a guess
for this very, very, very last byte. G is
a value between zero and 255. What the
attacker will do is the following, he will
XOR the value G XOR 01 into the last byte
of the block C0, the previous block. Yes
so all he did is he took the last byte of
the previous block and [foreign] that with
his guest [foreign] 01. Now lets think for
just a second and see what happens when
this two block cipher text is decrypted.
Well C0 is gonna get decrypted to whatever
its decrypted to that's just gonna be some
garbage that we don't care about but, now
when C1 is decrypted the last byte is
gonna be [foreign] with this modified C0,
and the result the last byte of the plain
text. Is gonna be also XORed with this
extra value that we stuck into C zero. So
what goes in here is the actual original
last byte in the plain text M1. But now it
gets XORed with G XOR zero X zero one. So
now you see where I'm going with this. If
the guess G for the last byte of M1 is
correct, then these two guys will cancel
one another. Last byte XOR G is just zero.
And what we'll get is the last byte of the
plaintext is just 0x01. I should mention,
by the way, 0x01 just means hex notation
for 01. So literally this is just a one
byte representation of the number one.
Good. So, again, what this means, is if
our guess for the last byte of M1 is
correct, then we get a pad that's well
formed. It's just a number one. The number
one is a well formed pad, and therefore,
the pad is valid. And the padding oracle
will say the pad is valid. If the guess is
incorrect then we'll get a value here
that's not equal to one and then it's very
likely that we have an invalid pad. And as
a result the padding worker will say the
pad is invalid. So again you see that if
our guess for the last byte of M1 is
correct, we learn that G was in fact a
correct guess. Whereas if our guess is
incorrect, then we learn that G is an
incorrect guess. So what the attacker is
gonna do is he's gonna create his modified
cipher text. You notice he only modifies
the second block of the cipher text. We're
gonna send this to the padding oracle and
then based on the results of the padding
oracle, we learn whether the last byte is
equal to G or not. Well, now we can simply
repeat this again and again for G from
zero to 255. This basically requires 256
chosen cipher text queries. Actually, I
guess on average we'll only have to do 128
chosen ciphers and squares until we find
the right G. Then, we learn the last byte
of M1. Well, so now we know the last byte
of M1. I claim that we can now use the
exact same process to learn the second to
last byte of M1. Let me ask you, what pad
are we gonna use to learn the second to
last byte of M1? Well, it shouldn't be
surprising that, instead of just using the
pad containing the byte one, we're gonna
use a two byte pad containing the bytes
2-2. That's a well formed pad. And now we
can always make sure because we know the
last byte of m1, when we do our XORing trick
we can always make sure that the last byte
of the plain text is in fact 02 and now we
can guess the second to last byte of m2 by
simply trying lots of values in g until we
find one that makes the pad, in fact, be
0202. And by issuing 256 additional
queries to the padding oracle we will get
to learn the second to last byte of m1.
And now we can iterate this again and
again, and basically since the length of
the block is sixteen bytes after sixteen
times 256 queries. We get to learn all of
them one. So this is a pretty significant
attack that is able to decrypt blocks of
the TLS record. So those of you who know
the inner workings of TLS should complain
that this attack isn't gonna work. The
problem is that when TLS receives a record
with a bad pad or a bad Mac, it shuts down
the connection, and renegotiates a new
key. As a result, the attacker is now
stuck with a cipher text encrypted using
an old key. And that key is no longer used
anywhere, so it cannot submit any more
queries. So with TLS, basically, it can
only submit one query, and that's it. Even
a single query still leaks information
about the plain text to the attacker. But
it doesn't expose the entire plain text
block m1. However this attack is so acute
that whenever there's a mistake like this
in a protocol there will be some settings
in which it comes up and in this case the
setting is in the case of an imap server.
So imap is a popular protocol for reading
email from an imap email server, and it's
very common to protect the imap protocol
by running it on top of a tls protocol.
Now, it turns out an imap. Every five
minutes, the IMap client will connect to
the IMap server, and check whether there's
new email. And the way it does it is by
first logging in to the IMap server, by
sending this login username password
message. And then it goes ahead and check
if there's new email available. Well, what
this means is that every five minutes, the
attacker gets an encryption of exactly the
same message in particular, I guess, an
encryption of the password. And so every
five minutes, it can mount one guess on
the block that contains the password. And
so, if your password is eight characters
long, the attacker simply needs to recover
those eight characters. And he's gonna
recover them one byte at, at a time, by
doing one guess per five minutes. And so
Canvel et. al. showed that, within a few
hours, you can basically recover the
user's password. Just by mounting one
guest every five minutes. So this is a
pretty significant attack against an
implementation of TLS and the defense
against this was to always check the Mac,
whether the pad is valid or invalid. And
as a result it takes the same amount of
time to respond whether the pad is valid
or invalid. So this removes the timing
attack and makes this attack much harder
to mount. So there are two lessons here.
First of all, you notice that if TLS had
used encrypt then MAC, rather than MAC
then encrypt, then this whole issue would
be completely moot, because if I encrypt
then MAC then MAC is checked first, and
only then does decryption and pad-checking
take place. In encrypt then MAC, the
cipher-text is discarded because the MAC
is invalid and we never even get to a pad
check. As a result, any tampering or gain
is with a cipher-text will be discarded
immediately because the MAC is simply
gonna fail. And second lesson to remember
is that remember I told you that MAC10CBC
actually does provide authenticated
encryption but only if you don't reveal
why the cryption failed. In this case the
padding wall [inaudible] completely
destroyed the authenticating encryption
property and basically I showed you an
attack this shows that now this mode does
not provide authenticated encryption. So
let me ask you the following question.
Supposing TLS instead of using MAC then
CBC, TLS did MAC then counter mode
encryption. Would the padding oracle
attack still be possible or not? The
answer is it wouldn?t be possible, simply
because counter-mode doesn't use any
padding at all. So this padding oracle
attack only effects CBC encryption modes
in TLS. Tls also supports counter-mode
encryption, and counter-mode encryption
modes are simply not affected by these
padding attacks. So that's the end of this
segment. In the next segment I want to
show you another very, very clever attack on
authenticated encryption systems.