In the last segment we defined
authenticated encryption, but I didn't
really show you why authenticated
encryption is the right notion of
security. In this segment I want to show
you that authenticated encryption in fact
is a very natural notion of security and
I'll do it by showing you that it defends
against a very powerful attack called a
chosen cipher text attack. So in fact we
already saw a number of examples of a
chosen cipher text attack so imagine the
adversary has some cipher text C that
it wants to decrypt. And what it can do
is, for example, fool the decryption
server into decrypting some cipher text
but not actually the cipher text c. So we
already saw some examples of that. If you
remember in the first segment, we looked
at an adversary that can submit arbitrary
cipher text, and if the plaintext happened
to start with destination equals 25, then
the adversary is actually given the
plaintext in the clear. So that's an
example of an adversary that can obtain
the decryption of certain cipher texts but
not all cipher texts. Another example we
saw is an adversary that can learn
something about the plaintext by
submitting cipher texts to the decrypter.
So we have this example where the
adversary submits encrypted TCP/IP packets
to the decryption server, and if the
decryption server sends back an ACK, the
adversary learns that the decrypted plain
text had a valid check sum. And otherwise,
the decrypted plain text didn't have a
valid check sum. So this is, again, an
example of a chosen cipher text attack,
where the attacker submits cipher text,
and learns something about the decryption
of that cipher text. So to address this
type of threats, we're gonna define a very
general notion of security, called chosen
cipher text security. So here, we're gonna
give the adversary a lot of power, okay?
So he can do both chosen plain text
attack, and a chosen cipher text attack.
In other words, he can obtain the
encryption of arbitrary messages of his
choice. And he can decrypt any cipher text
of his choice, other than some challenge
cipher texts. And as I showed you before,
this is actually a fairly conservative
modeling of real life. In real life,
often, the attacker can fool the, the
decrypter, into decrypting certain cipher
texts for the attacker, but not all cipher
texts. So the model here is that the
attacker has a certain cipher text that it
wants to decrypt. It can interact with
the decrypter by issuing these chosen
cipher text queries to the decrypter.
Namely, to decrypt various cipher text
other than the challenge cipher text. And
then the adversary's goal is to break
semantic security of the challenge cipher
text. So you notice that we're giving the
adversary a lot of power. And all we're
asking you to do is break semantic
security. So it's going to be fairly
difficult to design systems that are
secure against such adversaries.
Nevertheless, we're going to do it. So
let's define the chosen cipher text
security model more precisely. So, as
usual, we have a cipher (E, D). And we're
gonna define two experiments, experiment
zero and experiment one. So this should
look somewhat familiar by now. The
challenger is gonna start off by choosing
a random key. And now the adversary is
gonna submit queries to this challenger.
Every query can be one of two types. It
can be a chosen plain text query, or it
can be a chosen cipher text query. So a
chosen plain text query, as we already
know. Basically, the adversary submits two
messages, M zero and M1. They have to be
the same length. And the adversary
receives the encryption of either M zero
if we're in experiment zero, or M1, if we're
in experiment one. So he receives the
encryption of the left or the right
depending on whether we were in experiment
zero or in experiment one. The second type
of query is the more interesting one. This
is where the adversary submits an arbitrary
cipher text of his choice and what he gets
back is the decryption of that cipher
text. So you notice the adverary's allowed
to decrypt arbitrary cipher texts of his
choice. The only restriction is that the
cipher text is not one of the cipher texts
that were obtained as a result of a CPA
query. And of course this wouldn't be fair
otherwise, because the attacker can simply
take one cipher text that was obtained
from a CPA query. That's gonna to be
either the encryption of M0 or the
encryption of M1. If he could submit a CCA
query for that particular cipher text, he
will in response either obtain M0 or M1,
and then he'll know whether he is in experiment
zero or experiment one. So this wouldn't
be fair. So we say that the CPA cipher
texts that he received are the challenge
cipher texts. And he's allowed to decrypt
any cipher texts of his choice, other than
these challenge cipher texts. And as
usual, his goal is to determine whether
he's in experiment zero, or in experiment
one. So I'm gonna emphasize again, that
this is an extremely powerful adversary.
One that can decrypt any cipher text of
his choice, other than the challenge
cipher text. And still, he can't
distinguish whether he is in experiment
zero, or in experiment one. So, as usual,
we say that the cipher is CCA secure,
chosen cipher text secure, if the
adversary behaves the same in experiment
zero as it does in experiment one. Namely, it
cannot distinguish the two experiments. So
let's start with a simple example, and
show that, in fact, CBC with a random IV,
is not CCA secure, is not secure against
chosen cipher text attacks. So let's see
why that's the case. So what the
adversary's gonna start by doing, he's
gonna simply submit two distinct messages,
M0 and M1. And let's just pretend that
these messages are one block messages. And
what he's gonna get back is the CBC
encryption of either M0 or
M1. You notice the cipher text only has
one block, because the plain texts were
only one block long. Now what is the
attacker gonna do? Well, he's gonna modify
this cipher text C that he was given into
C prime simply by changing the IV. Okay?
So he just takes the IV and XORs it with
one. That's it. This gives a new cipher
text, C prime, which is different from C
and as a result it's perfectly valid for
the adversary to submit C prime as its
chosen cipher text query. So he
asks the challenger please decrypt this C
prime for me. The challenger, because c
prime is not equal to c, must decrypt c
prime. And now let's see, what happens
when he decrypts c prime? Well, what's the
decryption of c prime, let me ask you. So
you probably remember from the first
segment that if we xor the IV by one, that
simply xors the plaintext by one. So now
that adversary received M0 xor one, or M1
xor one, and now he can perfectly tell
whether he's in experiment zero and, or in
experiment one. So the advantage of this
adversary is basically one, because he can
very easily tell which experiment he's in.
And as a result he can win the chosen
cipher text security game. So if you think
about it for a second, you'll see that
this attack game exactly captured the first
active attack that we saw, where the
adversary slightly changed the cipher text
that he was given. And then he got the
decrypter to decrypt it for him. And
therefore, he was able to eavesdrop on
messages that were not intended for the
adversary. So I wanna emphasize again that
this chosen cipher text game really does
come up in real life, where the adversary
can submit cipher texts to the decrypter
and the decrypter can reveal information
about the plain text, or it can give the
plain text outright to the adversary for
certain cipher texts but not others. So
this is a very natural notion of security,
and the question is, how do we design
crypto-systems that are CCA secure? So I
claim that this authenticated encryption
notion that we defined before actually
implies chosen cipher text security, and
this is why authenticated encryption is
such a natural concept. Okay? So the
theorem basically says, well, if you give
me a cipher that provides authenticated
encryption, the cipher can withstand
chosen cipher text attacks. And more
precisely, the theorem says the following.
If we have an adversary that issues Q
queries, in other words, at most, q CPA
queries and q chosen cipher text queries,
then there are two efficient adversaries,
B1 and B2, that satisfy this inequality
here. So since the scheme has
authenticated encryption, we know that
this quantity is negligible because it's
CPA secure. And we know that this
quantity is negligible because the
encryption scheme has cipher text
integrity. And as a result, since both
terms are negligible we know that
adversary's advantage in winning the CCA
game is also negligible. So let's prove
this theorem. It's actually a very simple
theorem to prove. And so let's just do it
as proof by pictures. Okay, so here we
have two copies of the CCA game, so this
would be experiment zero. And the bottom
one is experiment one. You can see the
adversary's issuing CPA queries, and he's
issuing CCA queries, and at the end he
outputs, you know, a certain guess b,
let's call it b prime, and our goal is to
show that this b prime is
indistinguishable in both cases. In other
words, probability that b prime is equal
to one in the top game is the same as the
probability that b prime is equal to one
in the bottom game. Okay, so the way we're
gonna do it is the following. Well, first
of all, we're gonna change the challenger
a little bit, so that instead of actually
outputting the decryption of CCA queries,
the challenger is just gonna always output
bottom. So every time the adversary
submits a CCA query, the challenger says
bottom. And I claim that these two
games are, in fact, indistinguishable. In
other words, the adversary can't
distinguish these two games, for the
simple reason that, because the scheme has
cipher text integrity, the adversary
simply cannot create a cipher text that's
not in C1 to CI-1 that decrypts to
anything other than bottom. That is the
definition of cipher text integrity. And
as a result, again, because of cipher text
integrity, it must be the case that every
chosen cipher text query that the
adversary issues results in bottom. If the
adversary, in fact, could distinguish
between the left game and the right game,
that would mean that at some point he
issued a query that decrypted to something
other than bottom. And that we could use
to then break cipher text integrity of the
scheme. And since the scheme has
cipher-text integrity, these left and
right games are indistinguishable. Okay,
so that's kind of a cute argument that
shows that it's very easy to respond to
chosen cipher-text queries when you have
cipher-text integrity. And the same thing
exactly applies on the bottom, where we
can simply replace the chosen cipher-text
responses by just always saying bottom.
Okay, very good. But now, since the chosen
cipher text queries always respond in the
same way, they're not giving the adversary
any information. The adversary always
knows that we're always gonna just respond
with bottom. So we might as well just
remove these queries, 'cause they don't
contribute any information to the
adversary. But now, once we remove these
queries, the resulting game should look
fairly familiar. The top right game, and
the [bottom right] game are basically the two
games that come up in the definition of
CPA security. And as a result, because the
scheme is CPA secure, we know that the
adversary can't distinguish the top from
the bottom. And so now, by this change of
reasoning, we've proven that all of these
games are equivalent. And in particular,
the original two games that we started
with are also equivalent, and therefore,
the adversary can't distinguish the top
left from the bottom left. And therefore,
the scheme is CCA secure. So this gives
you the intuition as to why authenticated
encryption is such a cool concept. Because
primarily it implies security against
chosen cipher test attacks. Okay, so as we
said authenticated encryption
ensures confidentiality. Even if the
adversary can decrypt a subset of the
cipher text, and more generally, even if
he can mount a general chosen cipher text attack,
he still is not going to be able to break
semantic security of the system. However,
it is important to remember the two
limitations. First of all, it does not
prevent replay attacks on its own. We're
going to have to do something in addition
to defend against replay attacks. We're
going to see several examples where if the
decryption engine reveals more information
about why a cipher text is rejected, it
doesn't just output bottom, but it
actually outputs more information, say, by
timing attacks. And that explains why the
cipher text is rejected. Then in fact that
can completely destroy security of the
authenticated encryption system. So we'll
see some cute attacks like this in a later
segment. Okay. So, in the next segment
we're gonna turn to constructing
authenticated encryption systems.