Now that we're done with message
integrity, we're gonna back and talk about
encryption, and we're gonna show how to
construct encryption schemes that provide
much stronger security guarantees than
what we had before. But first let's do a
recap of where we are. So in previous
segments, we talked about confidentiality,
in particular how to encrypt messages such
that we achieve semantic security against
what's called a chosen plaintext attack.
Now I kept mentioning again and again that
security against chosen plaintext attacks
only provides security against
eavesdropping. In other words, this only
provides security against adversaries that
listen to network traffic. But don't
actually change any packets, or don't
inject their own packets, and so on. In
this module, our goal is actually to
design encryption schemes that are secure
against adversaries that can tamper with
traffic by blocking certain packets, and
injecting other packets and so on. And
then we also looked at how to provide
message integrity where the message itself
is not confidential. We just want to make
sure that the message is not modified
while it's en route. And so we talked
about message authentication codes, MAC
algorithms that provide existential
unforgeability against a chosen message
attack. In other words, even though the
attacker is able to obtain the MACs on
arbitrary messages of his choice, he can't
build MACs for any other messages. And we
looked at a number of MAC constructions,
in particular CBC MAC, HMAC, a Parallel mac
construction. And a fast MAC construction
called a Carter-Wegman MAC. In this
module, we're going to show how to combine
these confidentiality and integrity
mechanisms to obtain encryption schemes
that are secure against a much, much
stronger adversary, namely an adversary that
can tamper with traffic while it's in the
network, inject its own packets, block
certain packets, and so on. And our goal
is basically to insure that even against
such powerful adversaries, we maintain
confidentiality. In other words, the
adversary can't learn what the plain text
is and the adversary can't even modify the
cipher text. And cause the recipient to
think a different plain text was actually
sent. So before we do that I want to give
you a few examples of adversaries that can
tamper with traffic. And as a result
completely break security of CPA secure
encryption. This will show you that,
actually, with that providing integrity,
confidentiality can also be destroyed. In
other words, the two must go together,
integrity and confidentiality, if we're
going to achieve security against active
adversaries. So let's look at an example
from the word of networking. In
particular, let's look at TCP/IP. I'm gonna
use a highly simplified version of TCP/IP
just so we can quickly focus on the attack
and not get bogged down by the details. So
here we have two machines communicating
with one another. A user sits at one
machine, and the other machine is a
server. Now, the server, of course, has a
TCP/IP stack that's receiving packets. And
then, based on the destination field in
those packets, it forwards the packets to
the appropriate place. So here we have,
for example, two processes listening to
these packets. A web server, say, over
here, and another user, we'll call him
Bob, over here. The web server listens on
port 80, and here, this user Bob, listens
on port 25. Now, when a packet comes in,
the TCP/IP stack looks at the destination
port. In this case, it would be
destination 80, and as a result, the stack
forwards the packets over to the web
server. If the destination port said port
25, the TCP/IP stack would forward the
packet over to Bob, who's listening on
port 25. Now, a fairly well known security
protocol called IPsec, encrypts these IP
packets between the sender and the
recipient. So here, the sender and the
recipients basically have a shared key.
And when the sender sends IP packets,
those IP packets are encrypted using the
secret key K. Now when a packet arrives at
the destination, and I mean it arrives at
the server, the TCP/IP stack will go ahead
and decrypt the packet, and then look at
the destination port and send it to the
appropriate place decrypted. You notice
the data here is decrypted. So in this
case it would send it to the webserver
because the destination port is port 80.
If the destination port happens to be port
25, the TCP/IP stack will decrypt the
packet, look at the destination port, and
send the data in the clear to the process
who's listening on port 25. So now I wanna
show you that without integrity, in this
setup, we can't possibly achieve any form
of confidentiality and let's see why. So
imagine the attacker intercepts a certain
packet that's intended for the web server.
In other words, it's an encrypted packet
intended for port 80. Remember that the
attacker can actually receive the
decryption of any packets that's intended
for port 25 because the TCP stack will
happily decrypt packets for port 25 and
send them over to Bob who's listening over
here. So what Bob is going to do, Bob here
is the attacker, what he's going to do is
he's gonna intercept this packet en route,
prevent the packet from reaching the
server as is, and instead, he's going to
modify the packet. So now the destination
port is going to read like port 25. This
is done on the cipher text and we're going
to see how to do that in just a minute.
When this packet now arrives at the
server, the destination port says 25, the
server will decrypt the packet, see that
the destination is 25 and forward the data
over to Bob. So now Bob was simply by
changing the destination ports, Bob was
able to read data that was not intended
for himself, but rather was intended for
the web server. So, if the data is
encrypted using a CBC encryption with a
random IV, remember this is a CPA secure
scheme. Never the less if that's the case,
I'm gonna show you that it's trivial for
the attacker to change the decipher text.
So that now he can obtain new cipher text
where the destination port is 25 instead
of 80. The only thing that's gonna change
is just the IV field. In fact, everything
else is gonna remain the same. So, let's
see how to do it. So here, just to remind
yourself, that, in fact, what the attacker
captured is a CBC encrypted packet. Where
he knows that the destination port is port
80, but he doesn't know what the data is.
The attacker has no clue what the data is
but he does know that his packet is
intended for the web server. His goal is
to build a new encrypted packet where now
the destination port is port 25. So the
way he's gonna do is as we said is just by
changing the IV, and let me remind you that
the way you decrypt CBC encrypted data is
essentially the first plain text block is
simply decryption of the first cipher
text block XORed with IV. And we
know that in the original packet this is
gonna read dest equals 80. Cuz in the
original packet the destination port is
port 80. So now my question to you is how
will the attacker have changed the IV so
now the destination port will read dest
equals 25. So it's pretty easy to see that
if the attacker simply takes the original
IV, XORs it with here, there are a bunch
of zeros over here, and a bunch of zeros
over here. He's XORs it with the zeros,
and then 80 XORs with zeros, and then 25,
in the appropriate place. Namely, in the
port's bytes in the encrypted packets. Then
it's easy to see that when this new IV prime
is sent along with the original
cipher text, when the attacker decrypts,
you can see that the original cipher text
would decrypt to port 80, but now the new
IV will cancel out this 80, this 80 here
cancels out the 80 that would be obtained
in the original plain text and then by
XORing with 25, essentially the
destination now becomes 25. So this is a
nice example, where with the simple change
to the IV field, the attacker was able to
divert the packet. So that now, after
decryption, the packet goes to the
attacker, instead of the actual web
server. And as a result now the attacker
can read the plaintext data, that was
intended for the server. So this nice
example shows that without integrity it's
simply impossible for a CPA secure
encryption to provide confidentiality,
when the attacker can modify packets
en route. CPA secure encryption only
provides confidentiality if the attacker is
only eavesdropping on data, but can't
actually modify a cipher text en route.
Where, as you see, if you can modify
cipher text, a simple modification,
completely reveals the plaintext. I want
to show you another tampering attack that
only requires network access to traffic.
It doesn't actually require the attacker
to be present on the decryption machine.
So let's look at an example where there's
a remote terminal application, where every
time the user hits a keystroke, basically
an encrypted keystroke is sent over to the
server, and let's pretend that the
encrypted keystroke is encrypted using
counter mode. So here you have the
TCP/IP packet. D here corresponds to the
one byte keystroke. And as we said, it's
encrypted using counter mode, and as you
probably know every TCP/IP packet actually
contains a checksum. This is a sixteen bit
checksum that's just used to detect
transmission errors. So, the server, if it
receives a packet that has the wrong
checksum, it simply drops it on the floor
and ignores it. Now the TCP header
including the checksum in the keystroke,
all are encrypted using counter mode. Now
the attacker wants to learn what the
keystroke was, and let me show you what he
can do. The attacker is gonna intercept
this packet and he's not actually gonna
modify it, he's gonna send it over to the
server. But he's gonna record the packet.
Later on he's gonna modify the packet and
send a modified packet over to the server.
What he's going to do is he's gonna XOR
the encrypted checksum field with a
value T and he's going to XOR the
encrypted data field with a value S. And
he's going to do this for lots and lots of
T and S. Now remember, a property
of counter mode is that if you XOR the
cipher text with T after decryption, the
result in plain text is also XOR with T.
Similarly, if You XOR the encrypted data with s after decryption.
the resulting decrypted data will also be
encrypted with s. Now, the server's gonna
decrypt this modified packet. And the
resulting packet is gonna have the
check sum XORed with t, and the data XORed with s. Now what happens if the
modified check sum is correct for this
modified packet, the server will send an
ACK back. If the modified check sum
is incorrect for this modified packet, the
server will just drop the packet on the
floor and do nothing. So the attacker can
simply observe, look for an ACK packet or
not, and in doing so, he learns whether
this particular XOR of T and XOR of S
pairs corresponds to a valid checksum or not.
Now the attacker's going to do
this for lots and lots of T's and S's.
And you notice what he learns is if I
modify the data by XORing it with this
particular value S, that changes the
checksum by a particular value T. And
he learns this for lots and lots of T and
S pairs. So it turns out for certain
checksums, by looking at a sequence of
equations of this type. You can actually
figure out what the value D is. I should
point out that for the TCP checksums on this,
actually, might not be true, But
certainly, they're easy checksums for
which this is actually absolutely true. So
again by looking at a lot of equations of
this type the attacker can recover D. And
this is a really nice example of what's
called a chosen cipher text attack. The
attacker basically submitted cipher text
of his choice that was derived from that
cipher text that he wanted to decrypt. And
then by looking at how the server
responded he was able to learn something
about the resulting plaint text. And by
repeating this for many different values
of T and S he was actually eventually able to
recover what the actual full plain text is.
So in this segment we are gonna look
at many more examples of attacks of this
type. These are called active attacks,
where the attackers actually modify
traffic in route. And I hope that these
two simple example convinces you that all
you provide is CPA security other words
security against eavesdropping. You can't
even guarantee secrecy against an active
attacker. Not only does your cipher text
not have integrity, in other words the
recipients might obtain a message
different from the one sent by the sender.
But you don't even have confidentiality.
And I showed you two examples where
without integrity the attacker can simply
decrypt the packet by using the recipient
as an oracle for decrypting certain parts
of the data. And so the lesson that I'm
gonna repeat again and again and again
throughout this module is that if your
message needs integrity but no
confidentiality, just use a MAC. But if
your message needs integrity and
confidentiality, you have to use what's
called an authenticated encryption mode,
which is precisely the topic of this
module. So the next thing we're gonna do
is define what authenticated encryption
means. And we're gonna build authenticated
encryption systems. But the point I want
you to remember is that the CPA security
modes we discussed before should never
actually be used to encrypt data by
themselves. So CBC with a random IV is a
building block towards authenticated
encryption, but should never be used on
its own. Okay. So we're gonna define
authenticated encryption in the next
segment.