So I want to show you how authenticated
encryption is used in the real world, so
let's use TLS as an example and see how
TLS works. So data encryption in TLS is
done using a protocol called a TLS record
protocol. In this protocol, every TLS
record starts with a header, we'll see the
structure of the header in just a minute,
followed by encrypted data that is sent
from one side to the other. In TLS, it so
happens that the records are at most
sixteen kilobytes and if more data than
sixteen kilobytes needs to be sent, then
basically the record is fragmented into
multiple records. Now TLS uses what's
called unidirectional keys, meaning that
there's one key from browser to server,
and there's a separate key from server to
browser. So one key is used for sending
messages from a browser to the server, and
the other key is used from sending
messages from the server to the browser,
and of course both sides, both the server
and the browser, know both of these keys.
And just to be clear I'll say the browser
will use this key to send data to the
server and we'll use this key to read data
from the server and the server basically
does exactly the same thing just with the
opposite keys. Now these keys, both of
these keys are actually generated by the
TLS key exchange protocol which we're
gonna talk about in the second part of the
course. Right now I'm gonna assume that
these keys have already been established.
They're known to both the server and the
browser, and now the browser and server
want to exchange information using those
keys. So the TLS record protocol uses
what's called stateful encryption, which
means that the encryption of every packet.
Is done using certain state that's
maintained inside of the browser and the
server. In particular the state that's of
interest to us are these 64 bit counters,
again there are two 64 bit counters. One
for traffic from browser to server, and
one from traffic from the server to the
browser. These counters are initialized to
zero when the session is first
initialized, and they're incremented every
time a record is sent. So every time the
browser sends a record to the server, the
browser will go ahead and increment this
counter. When the server receives that
record, it'll go ahead and increment the
counter on its side. And when the server
sends a record to the browser, he'll go
ahead and increment the second counter and
again when the browser receives this
record it'll go ahead and increment its
copy of this counter. So this state these
two counters basically this state exists
both on the browser and on the server and
it's updated appropriately as records as
sent from one to the other and received
by the appropriate side. Now the purpose
of these counters as we'll see in just a
minute is to prevent replay attacks so
than an attacker can't simply record the record
and then replay at a later time because by
then the counters will have to be
incremented. Okay, so let's look at the
details of how the record protocol works.
In particular I'll show you kind of the
mandatory cipher suit which is encryption
using AES-CBC and MACing using HMAC-SHA1. Okay,
so remember, TLS uses a MAC, then encrypt,
where the MAC algorithm is HMAC-SHA1, and the encryption
algorithm is AES128 in CBC mode. Okay, so
let's look at how the browser sends data
to the server, which, as I said, is done
using the browser to server key. Now, the
browser to server key itself, is made up
of a MAC key and an encryption key. Two
separated keys that are again as I said
negotiated during session setup. And again
I wanna be absolutely clear. There is a
separate key for browser to server and a
separate key from server to browser. So
there, overall, there are four keys. Two
MAC keys, and two encryption keys, each
one used in the appropriate direction.
Okay, so here I wrote down the diagram of
what a tls packet looks like. It begins
with a header that contains the type of
the packet, the version number for the
protocol, and the length of the packet.
Notice the length of the packet it sends
in the clear. Now, when the encrypting
data, a certain record, the encryption
procedure works as follows. Of course, it
takes key as input, and it takes the
current status input. And then it works as
follows. What it'll do is first of all is
it would MAC the following data, while
here's the actual payload that's MACed but
the heather is also MACed. In addition the
counter, the current value of the counter
is also MACed and of course, it's all the
counters implemented during the
[inaudible] fact that one more record has
been sent. Now the interesting thing here
is that even though the value of the
counter is included in the tag. You notice
the value of the counter is actually never
sent in the record, and the reason it
doesn't need to be sent in the record is
that the server on the other side already
knows what the value of the counter needs
to be. So it doesn't need to be told in
the record what the value of the counter
is. It implicitly already knows what it
is, and when it's gonna verify the MAC, it
could just use the value that it thinks
the counter should be and verify the MAC
in that fashion. Okay, so this is kind of
an interesting approach, where even though
the two sides maintain these counters that
function as nonces, there is no
reason to send the nonces in the record,
because both sides actually already know
what counters they're expecting every
record that they receive. Okay, so that's
the tag. The tag is computed, as we said,
over this triple data. The next thing that
happens is that the tag is concatenated to
the data. Remember, this is MAC-then-Encrypt. So here, we computed the MAC. Now
we're gonna encrypt the data along with
the tag. So the header, the data, and the
tag are padded to the AES block, and I
think we already said that this pad, if
the pad length is five, then the pad is
done by simply writing the byte five, five
times. If the pad link leads to B5, the
pad would just be 55555. And then we CBC
encrypt using the encryption key, we CBC
encrypt the data and the tag. And we do
that using a fresh random IV, which is
later embedded in the cipher text. And
then we prepend the header, the type,
the version and the length. And that gives
us the entire TLS record, which is then
sent over to the server. So the grayed out
fields in this diagram correspond to
encrypted data, and the white fields
correspond to plaintext data. So you can
see that this is TLS's implementation of
MAC then encrypt. The only difference from
basic MAC then encrypt is the fact that
there is a state, namely this counter is
being included in the value of the MAC.
And again as I said that's done to prevent
replays. So let's see why that prevents
replays. In particular, let's see how the
record protocol decrypts an incoming
record. So, here comes an incoming
encrypted record. And again, the server is
going to use it's own key that corresponds
to data, from browser to server. And it's
own browser to server counter. And the
first thing it's going to do, is it's
going to decrypt the record using the
encryption key. After encryption, it's
going to check the format of the pad. In
other words, if the pad length is five
bytes, it's going to check that it really
is five, five, five, five, five. And if
it's not, it's gonna send a bad record mac
alert message and terminate the
connection. So that a new session key will
have to be negotiated if more records need
to be sent. If the pad format is correct,
then removing the pad is really easy. All
the server does is it looks at the last
byte of the pad, say the last byte is
equal to five, and, then, it removes the
last five bytes of the record. By doing
that it strips off the pad. The next thing
it's gonna do is it's gonna extract the
tag from the record. So, this would be the
web sequence bytes inside of the record.
So, this would be the, the trailing bytes
in the record after we remove the pad, and
then it's gonna verify the pad on the
header, the data and its value of counter.
And if the Mac doesn't verify again, it's
gonna send an alert, bad record Mac, and
tear down the connection. And if the pad
does verify, it's gonna remove the tag,
remove the header, and the remaining part
of the record is the plain text data
that's given to the application. Now, you
can see if a record is ever replayed, in
other words if an attacker records a
particular record and then replays it to the
server at a later time, then, by then the
value of the counter would have changed
and as a result the tag on the replayed
record would simply not verify because the
tag was computed using one value of the
counter but with the replayed record as
received at the server The value of the
counter of the server is different from
the value that was used to compute a tag
and as a result the tag was not verified.
So these counters are very elegant and
simple way for preventing replays and the
nice thing about this is because both
sides know the value of the counter implicitly
there's never a need to send the
counter in the record itself. So the
counter itself doesn't increase the length
of cipher text L. Now, we already
mentioned that this particular approach
to, authenticated encryption, namely, MAC,
then encrypt, using CBC encryption, is, in
fact, authenticated encryption. However,
it's only authenticated encryption if no
other information is leaked during
decryption. And we're going to see some
acute attacks on TLS if there is
information being leaked during
decryption. I should say that this bad
record MAC alert basically corresponds to
the decryption algorithm outputting this
reject symbol, the bottom symbol. Meaning
that the cipher text is invalid. And as
long as there's no way to differentiate
between why the cipher text was rejected,
in other words the decrypter only exposes
the fact that a rejection took place but
it doesn't say why the rejection happened
this is in fact an authenticated
encryption system. However, if you
differentiate and expose why the cipher
text was rejected whether it was because
of a bad pad or because of a bad mac then
it turns out there's a very acute attack.
Which we're gonna see in the next segment.
What I showed you so far is called TLS
Version 1.1. It turns out that earlier
versions of TLS actually had significant
mistakes in it, and as a result, the
earlier Record Protocol is vulnerable to a
number of attacks. The first mistake is
that the IV used in CBC Encryption is
predictable. And we said earlier that in
CBC, if the IV is predictable then the
resulting CBC Encryption is not CPA
Secure. Well, in this older version of
TLS, TLS 1.0 and earlier, the IV for the
next record is simply the last cipher text
record of the current record. And as a
result, if the adversary can observe the
current record, he knows the IEV for the
next record and that will allow him to
break the semantic security of the next
record. So the resulting scheme is not CPA
secure. But not only is it not CPA secure,
in fact, there is a very acute attack
called a BEAST attack that's able to decrypt
the initial part of the TLS record
simply based on the fact that this scheme
is not semantically secure. So, I should
say that this method of choosing the iv to
be the last block of the previous record
is called chained iv's. And you should
remember that this, actually should not be
used in practice because it always, always
leads to an attack. Because of this TLS
1.1 moved to what's called, explicit iv's
where every TLS record has its own random
unpredictable iv. And that's fixed the
problem as soon as browsers and servers
move to TLS 1.1, this will no longer be an
issue. Now another mistake that was done
in TLS 1.0 and earlier, enabled what's
called a padding oracle. Which is
something that we're going to talk about
in the next segment, were what happened
was, that if the cipher text was rejected
due to an invalid pad The server was sent
back an alert message saying decryption
failed. Whereas if the cipher text was
rejected due to a bad Mac, the server will
send back a bad record Mac alert. As a
result, and adversary who observes the
alert sends back from the server, can tell
whether the pad in the cipher text was
valid or invalid. And this introduces a
very significant attack called a padding
attack, which we're gonna talk about in
the next segment. The solution to this and
TLS 1.1, was basically to say that,
instead of reporting decryption failed
here, we're gonna report a bad record Mac,
even if the pad is incorrect. And, as a
result, simply looking at which alert is
sent back from the server, an attacker
can't tell if a cipher text is rejected
because of a bad pad or a bad MAC. So this
tries to mask this information. Now the
lesson from this is that when decryption
fails, you should never ever explain why,
I guess this is something that comes out
of networking protocols where if there is
a failure you wanna tell the peer why the
failure occurred, where in cryptography if
you explain why the failure occurred that
very often leads to an attack. In other
words when decryption fails just output
reject and don't explain why the reject
actually happens just reject the ciphertext.
Okay, so now that we've seen TLS 1.1,
let's see a broken protocol. So of course
I always like to pick on 802.11b WEP,
which pretty much got everything wrong. So
let's see how not to provide authenticated
encryption. So let me remind you how
802.11b WEP works. Basically there's a
message that the laptop wants to send to
the access point. The first thing that
happens is it, the laptop computes a
cyclic redundancy checksum on the message
and concatenates the CRC checksum to the
message. Then the result is encrypted
using a stream cipher, in particular RC4.
If you recall, the key that's used is the
concatenation of an initial value IV
that changes per packet and the long term
key K. And then the IV along with the
cipher text are transmitted to the other
side. Now we've already saw two
problems with this approach. One was if
the IV is ever repeated and in fact it is
gonna be repeated then you get a two time
pad attack. And the other problem
is that [inaudible] uses very closely
related keys. In other words, the key is
simply IV concatenated to K and the only
thing that changes are the IV so the key
is always fixed, which means that these
PRG keys are very closely related to one
another and as we said, the PRG that's
used here, RC4 is not designed for this
type of use and it completely breaks
if you use it with related keys, and as a
result WEP has no security at all.
What I want to show you. Is that even the
crc mechanism that's used here. In an
attempt to provide integrity and prevent
an adversary from tampering with the
cipher text, even that mechanism is
completely broken, and it's actually very
easy to tamper with cipher texts en route.
So let's see how that's done. The attack
uses a particular property of the CRC
check sum. Mainly the CRC is linear. What
that means is if I give you CRC of M, and
I ask you to compute CRC of M XOR P, then
it's very easy to do. Basically you'll
just compute some well known and public
function of F(P), you XOR these two together,
and that in fact will give you CRC of
M XOR P. So it [inaudible] the xor comes out
of the parenthesis, and that basically
means the CRC is linear. Now here is how the
attack works, suppose the adversary
intercepts a particular, packet that's
destined to the access point. Now the
packet say, sais it's destined for
destination port 80, and the attacker
knows that it's intended for destination
port 80 and what he wants to do is
modify the cipher texts such that now the
destination port will say 25 instead of
80. And maybe the attacker can read
messages for port 25 and that's how he
actually obtains the actual data in the
packet. So recall that the CRC checksum
is there to make sure that exactly the
attacker cannot change data inside of the
cipher text. But I want to show you that
in fact it's really easy to modify data in
the cipher text and CRC basically provides
no security against tampering at all. So
let's see how to do it. Well, what the
attacker would do is, he would basically
Xor some, a certain value XX into the byte
that represents the eight zero in the
cipher text. Now what he'll Xor in will
basically be the string 25 Xor 80 and you
remember that if I Xor a certain string XX
into the cipher text. That was created
using a stream cipher. When that cipher
gets, is decrypted, the plain text at this
position will also be Xored by XX. And as
a result after decryption the plain text
at this position basically will be the
original 80XR 25 XR 80 which gives us 25.
Okay? So after decryption the plain text
of this position will now be 25. The
problem is that if that's all we did then
this attack would fail because the CRC
check sum would now would not validate.
The CRC check sum. Was built with 80 as a
plain text but 25 is a different plain
text and needs a different CRC. But it's
not a problem because what we can do is we
can easily correct the check sum, the CRC
check sum, even though the CRC check sum
is encrypted. What we do is we XOR
F of XX into the cipher text at the place
where the CRC is supposed to be and as a
result, when the cipher text is decrypted
what will happen is we'll get the correct
CRC check sum after decryption. So, the
interesting thing that happened here is
even though the attacker doesn't know what
the crc value is, he's able to correct it
using this linearity property such that
when the cipher text is decrypted the
correct crc value appears in the plain
text. Okay? So the linearity property of
CRC plays a critical role in making this
attack works. The end conclusion here is
basically that a CRC check sum provides
absolutely no integrity at all against
active attacks and it should never, ever,
ever be used as an integrity mechanism.
And instead if you want to provide
integrity you're supposed to use a
cryptographic mac not an ad hoc mechanism
like CRC. Okay, so now we've seen how
authenticated encryption is implemented in
a real world protocol, like TLS. In the
next segment, we're gonna look at real
world attacks on authenticated encryption
implementations that happen to implement
authenticated encryption incorrectly.