The next thing I want to do is show you
the general attack on collision resistant
hash functions. If you remember when we
talked about block cyphers. We saw a
general attack on block cyphers which we
called exhaustive search. And that attack
forced the key size for a block cypher to
be 128 bits or more. Similarly on
collision resistance there is a general
attack called the birthday attack which
forces the output of collision resistant
hash functions to be more than a certain
bound. So let me show you the attack and
we will see what those bounds come out to
be. So here's the general attack that can
work on arbitrary collision resistant hash
functions. So here we have our collision
resistant hash functions, supposedly, but
lets suppose that it outputs N bit values.
In other words, the output space is
roughly of size two to the N. Now, the
message space is gonna be much, much
larger than N bits. Let's just say that
the messages that are being hashed are
say, you know, a hundred times N bits. I
wanna show you an algorithm that can find
the collision for this hash function H in
time roughly two to the N over two. Okay,
so roughly the square root of the size of
the outputs space. So here's how the
algorithms gonna work: what we'll do is
we'll choose random two to the N over two
messages in our message space that's
called an M-one to M-two to the N over
two. Now because the messages themselves
are much bigger than N bits, they're
hundred times N bits, it's very likely
that all these messages are distinct. So
they'll be distinct with high probability.
But for each one of these messages we're
gonna apply the hash function and obtain
the tag T sub I. So this is of course the
T sub I's are N-bit long strings. And now
we're gonna look for a collision among the
T sub I's. In other words, we're gonna
find an I and a J such that T sub I equals
to T sub J. And once we've done that we've
basically found the collision because, as
we said, with very high probability, M-I
is not equal to M-J. But the hash of M-I
is equal to the hash of M-J and therefore
we found the collision on the function H.
Now if it so happens that we looked
through all the two to the N over two T
sub I's and we don't find the collision,
we go back to step one and try another set
of two to the N over two messages. So the
question is how well will this work, in
other words how many times do we have to
iterate this process until we actually
find the collision? And I wanna show you
that in fact the number of iterations is
gonna be very, very small which means that
this algorithm will find the collision in
time that's roughly proportional two to
the N over two. So to analyze this type of
attack, I have to tell you a little bit
about the birthday paradox. I imagine some
of you have already heard about the
birthday paradox. Here stated as a
theorem, and I wanna prove it to you
because everybody should see a proof of
the birthday paradox at least once in
their lives. So here it is, so imagine we
have N random variables R-one to R-N in
the interval one to B. And the only thing
I'm gonna assume about them is that
they're actually independent of one
another. That's crucial that these N
samples R-one to R-N in this interval are
independent of one another. And they also
happen to be distributed identically. So
for example, they might all be uniform in
the interval one to B, but again these
would be independently uniform variables.
Now it so happens that if we set N to B
about the square root of B, in other words
if we sample roughly the square root of B
samples from the interval one to B, And to
be precise, it's one point two times the
square root of B. Then the probability
that two of those samples will be the same
is at least a half. Okay, then it turns
out in fact the uniform distribution is
the worst case for the birthday paradox.
In other words, if the distribution from
which the R-I's are sampled from is
non-uniform, that in fact fewer than one
point two times the square root of B
samples are needed. The uniform
distribution is the worst case. So we're
gonna prove this for the uniform
distribution and that basically also
proves it for all other distributions. But
the proof that I wanna show you here will
hold just for the uniform distribution.
Okay, so let's do the proof that's
actually not difficult at all. So we're
asking what is the probability that there
exists an I that is not equal to J such
that RI is equal to RJ. Well, let's negate
that so it's basically one minus the
probability that for all I not equal to J
we have that RI is not equal to RJ. This
basically means that no collision occurred
among the N samples that we chose. Well
let's try to write this out more
precisely. Well we're gonna write this as
one minus. And now when we choose R-one,
basically it's the first one we choose so
it's not gonna collide with anything. But
now let's look at what happens when we
choose R-two, when we choose R-two, lemme
ask you, what is the probability that
R-two. Does not collide with R-one. Well,
R-one takes one slot so there are B minus
one slots that if R-two falls into it's
not gonna collide with R-one. So in other
words the probability that R-two does not
collide with R-one is B minus one slot
divided by all B possible slots.
Similarly, when we pick R-three What is
the probability that R-three does not
collide with either R-one or R-two? Again,
R-one and R-two take up two slots. And so
there are B minus two slots that remain
for R-three if it falls into either one of
those B minus two slots it's not gonna
collide with either R-one or R-two. So I
imagine you see the pattern now, so R-four
it's probability of not colliding with
R-one, R-two, or R-three is B minus three
over B. And so on and so forth until we
get to the very last R-N and the
probability that R-N does not collide with
the previous R-I's, well, there are N
minus one slots taken up by the previous
R-I's. So, if R-N falls into any of the
remaining B minus N plus one slots It's
not gonna collide with any of the previous
R-one to R-N minus one. Now you notice
that the reason I was able to multiply all
these probabilities is exactly because the
R-I's are all independent of one another.
So it's crucial for the step That the
R-I's are independent. So let me rewrite
this expression a little bit. Let me write
it as one minus the product of I goes to N
minus one of one minus I over B. Okay. All
I did is I just rewrote this as a big
product as opposed to writing the terms
individually. So now I'm gonna use the
standard inequality that says that for any
positive X, one minus X is less than E to
the minus X. And that's actually easy to
see because E to the minus X, if you look
at it's Taylor expansion, is one minus X
plus X squared over two minus and so on
and so forth. And so you can see that
we're basically ignoring this latter part
of the Taylor expansion, which happens to
be positive and as a result the left side
is gonna be smaller than the right-hand
side. Okay, so let's plug this inequality
in, and what do we get? We get that this
is greater than one minus the product of I
goes from one to N minus one of E to the
minus I over B okay, simply plugged in X
equals I over B for each one of those
terms. And the next thing about
exponentials is that we multiply them, the
exponents add. As a result this is simply
equal to one minus E to the power of, here
let me take the one over B out of the
parentheses, sum of I goes from one to N
minus one of I. Okay. So, all I did was I
took the minus one over B out of the
parentheses and we're left with simple sum
of one to N minus one. And so the sum of
the integers from N to N minus one is
simply N times N minus one over two which
it can bound by N squared over two. And so
really what I get at the end here is one
minus E to the power of minus N squared
over two B. Okay, I literally downed it to
sum here by N squared over two. Okay, very
good. So now what do we do about N squared
over two B? Well, we can derive exactly
what N squared over two B is from the
relationship here. So if you think about
it, let's look at N squared over two.
Well, N squared over two is 1.2 squared
over two. 1.2 squared is 1.44 divided by
two is .72 times the square root of B
squared which is B. Okay so N squared over
two is .72B, and as a result, N squared
over 2B is just .72. So we get 1-E, which
is a power of minus 0.72. Well so now you
just plug this in to your calculator and
you get 0.53, which as far as i know, is
always bigger than F. So this proves the
Birthday Paradox and you notice that it
was crucial to a string that the samples
are independent of one another, we only
proved that for the uniform distribution.
But as i said it is actually fairly easy
to argue now that any distribution that is
away from the uniform distribution will
satisfy this with even a lower balance. So
if you have. 1.2 squared of B, the theorem
will certainly hold for none uniform
distributions. The reason it is called a
paradox is because it is very paradoxical
that the square root function grows very
slowly. In particular if you try to apply
this to birth dates, so lets assume that
we have a number of people in a room, and
lets assume that their birth dates are
independent of one another and are uniform
in their interval one through 365. Then
what the Birthday Paradox says is that we
need roughly 1.2 times the square root of
365. Which i believe is something like 23,
which says we need roughly 23 people in a
room, and then with probability one half,
two of them will actually have the same
birth date. The reason it is called a
paradox is because the number 23 seems
really small to people, and yet by this
theorem we just proved, with probability
one half, there will be two people with
the same birth date. By the way the
intuition for why this fact is true is
because really what the collision is
counting is it is looking at all possible
pairs of people. And if you have a square
root of B people, then there are square
root of B squared pairs. Roughly, Which is
roughly B pairs total and so it's very
likely that each pair collides probability
one over B and if you have B pairs, it's
likely that one of the pairs will collide.
So hopefully this gives the intuition for
where the square root comes from. Its
basically from the fact that if you have N
people in the room, there are N squared
possible pairs. I should say by the way
that even though the Birthday Paradox is
often applied to birth dates, birth dates
are actually not uniform at all. If you
actually look at the birth dates of
people, you see that there is a very clear
bias towards being born in September, and
for me bazaar reason there is also a
biased towards being born on a Tuesday.
And so when we apply the birthday paradox
to birthdays, in fact the actual bound is
going to be smaller than one minus two
square root of B because we said that for
non even form distributions you need even
fewer samples before you get a collision.
So let me show you how to graph the
Birthday Paradox, its quite interesting
how it behaves. So here set B to be a
million, in other words we are picking
random uniform samples in the range one to
a million. And the X axis here, is the
number of samples that we are picking, and
the Y axis, is the probability that we get
a collision among those N samples. So we
see that the probability of one half
happens around 1.2 square root of B.
Roughly twelve hundreds, 1.2 square root
of B. And you see that if we look at
exactly the square root of B, the
probability of a collisions is around .4
or .41. And you notice that the
probability goes up to one extremely fast.
For example, already at roughly two square
root of B, but the probability of a
collision is already 90%. Similarly, when
we go bellow square root of B, the
probability of a collision very, very
quickly drops to zero. Okay, so there is
kind of a threshold phenomena around
square root of B, where the probability of
a collision goes to one very quickly,
above square root of B drops to zero very
quickly below square root of B. So now we
can analyze are attack algorithms, so let
me remind you, here we chose, two to the
interval two random elements in the
message space, we hashed them. And so we
started off with a random distribution in
the message base, after we hashed them, we
end up with some distribution, this
distribution over tags might note be
uniform, but we don't care, the point is
that all these tags T1 to T2 to the N over
two, are independent of one another. If we
choose. Two to the N over two or 1.2 to
the N over two, tags, the probability that
the collision will exist is roughly one
half. So let me ask you then, in that
case, how many times do we have to iterate
this algorithm before we actually find a
collision? Well then since each iteration
is going to find a collision with
probability one half, we have to iterate
about two times in expectation. And as a
result the running time of this algorithm
is basically two to the N over two
evaluations of the hash function. Okay so
notice also this algorithm takes a lot of
space but we're gonna ignore the space
issue and we're just gonna focus on the
running time. Okay so this is kinda cool,
this says that if your hash
function outputs N-bits outputs
there will always be an attack algorithm
that runs in time two to the N over two.
So for example if we output 128 big
outputs Then a collision could be found in
time two to the sixty four, which is not considered
sufficiently secure. Okay, this is why
collision resistant hash functions,
generally are not going to output 128
bits. So let me show you some examples.
The first three are actually federal
standards, SHA-1, SHA-256, and SHA-512
and the fourth one is an example from
the designers of AES, called Whirlpool,
and so you can see SHA-1 outputs 160
bits and as a result there is a generic
attack on it that runs on
time two to the eighty. SHA-256 outputs 256
bits so the generic attack will run
in time two to the 128 and so on and so
forth. I also listed the speed of these
algorithms and you notice that the bigger
the block size actually the slower the
algorithm is [and?] so there's a
performance penalty but nevertheless
there's quite a bit of benefit in terms of
security. Now you notice the SHA
function is actually greyed out. The
SHA function although nobody has
found collisions for SHA-1 yet
It is still recommended that in a new
project, and hopefully programing projects
in this class, you don't use SHA-1,
instead you use SHA-256. In particular
there is actually a theoretical collision
finder on SHA-1 that works in time two
to the 51. So it is probably just a matter
of time until someone finds a collision
for SHA-1, and just kills altogether,
but the current advice is that SHA-1 is
still a collision resistant hash function
because nobody has found collisions for
it, but it is probably just a matter of
time, just a few months, or few years,
until a collision is found. It is a result
a new product and new projects SHA-1
should not be used and only use
SHA-256 or if you wanna be even
more cautious then use SHA-512. So this is the end of this
segment, and now we are going to turn
building collision resistant hash