So now we're gonna look at a very general
paradigm called the Merkle-Damgard
paradigm, that's used for constructing
collision-resistant hash functions. Before
we do that, let me just remind you what
our goals are. So as usual we say that H
is a hash function that maps some large
message space into a small tag space. And
we say that a collision for a hash
function is basically a pair of distinct
messages that happen to map to the same
value under this hash function. And our
goal is to build collision-resistant hash
functions namely functions where it's hard
to find even a single collision. Even
though we know many collisions exist. No
efficient algorithm can even output a
single collision. So we're gonna construct
these hash functions, these collision
resistant hash functions, in two steps.
The first step, which we're gonna do in
this segment, is to show that if you give
me a collision resistant hash function for
short messages, we can extend it and build
a collision resistant hash function for
much, much, much longer messages. In the
next segment, we'll actually build
collision-resistant HASH functions for
short messages. Okay so let's look at the
construction. The construction is actually
very general and in fact all
collision-resistant hash functions follow
this paradigm. It's actually a very
elegant paradigm and let me show you how
it works. So here we have our function H
which we're gonna assume is a
collision-resistant hash function for
small sized inputs. So the way we're gonna
use this little function h, this h is
sometimes called a compression function,
is we're gonna take a big message M and
break this message in to blocks. And then
we use a fixed value called the IV. Here
is the case the IV is fixed forever. And
it's basically embedded in the code and in
the standards, it's just a fixed ID that's
part of the fin-nation of the function.
And then what we do is we apply the small
compression function H to the first
message block along with this ID. What
comes out of that is what's called a
chaining variable that's gonna be fed into
the next compression function which
compresses the next block along with the
previous chaining variable and out comes
the next chaining variable, and the next
message block is compresses, and so on and
so forth until we which the final message
block And then the final message block,
the one special thing that we do, is that
we must append this padding block, this
PB, which stands for padding block (and
I'll explain what the padding block is in
just a second). But after we append the
padding block we again compress the last
[inaudible] variable with the last message
block, and the output of that is the
actual output of the hash function. So
just to summarize, in symbols, we have
this compression function that elements in
T. This is the opposite of the hash
function. Plus message blocks, this x
corresponds to message blocks, and outputs
the next chaining variables. So as I said,
this is what the compression functions do.
And then from this compression function
we're able to build a hash function for
large inputs, namely inputs is the space x
to some power of l namely up to l blocks
of x. And of course these are variable
lengths so we could have different length
messages that are being given input to
this function h and what comes out of it
is basically a tag in tag space. So the
only thing left to define is the padding
block. So the padding block is actually
very important as we're gonna see in just
a minute. What it is, is basically, well
it's a sequence of 1000 that denotes the
end of the actual message block. And then
the most important part of the message
block is that we encode the message length
In this padding block. And the message
length field is basically fixed to be 64
bits. So in all the [inaudible] hash
functions, so in all the [inaudible] hash
functions the maximum message length is
two to the sixty four minus one so in fact
the message length fits into a 64 bit
block. An upper bound of two to the sixty
four minus one bit on the message length
is actually sufficiently long to handle
all of the messages we're gonna throw at
it. Okay, so that's the padding block, and
of course the question is: what do we do
if the last block really is a multiple of
the compression function of block length?
Where are we gonna fit the padding block?
And the answer, as usual, is basically if
there's no space for the padding block in
the last block of the message, then we're
gonna have to ass another dummy block and
stick the padding block in there. And of
course put the one zero, zero, zero in the
right place. Okay so the point is that
it's very, very important that the padding
block contains the message length as we'll
see in just a minute. So this is the
Merkle-Damgard construction, the last
piece of terminology I'll say is that we
have these chaining variables. So H0 is
the initial value. H1, H2, H3, up to H4
which is the actual final output of this
hash function. So as I said, all standard
hash functions follow this paradigm for
constructing a collision resistant hash
function from a compression function. The
reason that this paradigm is so popular is
because of the following theorem, which
says basically that if the little
compression function is collision
resistant, then the big Merkle-Damgard
hash function is also collision resistant.
So, in other words, if we're going to build
collision resistant functions for large inputs, all
we have to do is just build compression
functions that are collision resistant. So
let's prove this theorem. It's a elegant
proof and it's not too difficult. So the
way we're gonna prove it is using the
contrapositive, that is, if you can find
me a collision on the big hash function
then we're gonna deduce a collision on the
little compression function. Therefore, if
little h is a collision resistant, so will
be the big H. So suppose you give me a
collision on the big compression function,
namely two distinct messages M and M',
that happen to hash to the same output,
we're going to use M and M' to build
a collision on the little compression
function. So the first thing is we
have to remember how the Merkle-Damgard
construction works and, in particular,
let's assign names to the chain variables
when we hash M versus when we hash M'.
So here are the chain variables that come up
when we hash the message M, so H0 is the
fixed IV that starts the whole process, H1
would be the result of hashing the first
message block with the IV, and so on and
so forth, until H sub t+1 is the
final chain variable, which is the final
output of the Merkle-Damgard chain. And
then similarly for M', let's define H0'
to be the first chaining variable, H1'
to be the result after compressing
the first message block of M', and so
on and so forth, up until we get to H'
of r+1, which is the final hash of
the message M'. Now you notice the
length of the messages M and M'
don't have to be the same. In particular, M
has length t, whereas M' has length r.
Now because the collision occurred, we
know that these two values here are the
same. H(M) is equal to H(M'). In
other words, the last chaining variables
are actually equal to one another. So now
let's look carefully how H t+1 and
H' r+1 were calculated. Well
H t+1 is calculated as the
compression function applied to the
previous chaining variable along with the
last message block of M, including the
padding block. You'll notice here I'm
assuming that the padding block fits with
the last message block of M even if the
last padding block is in its own block,
it's not going to make any difference. So
for simplicity, let's assume that the
padding block fits with the last message
block with capital M. So, by hashing the
last message block with a padding block
and the last chaining variable, we obtain
H t+1 and, similarly, the same thing
happens with M'. By hashing the last
message block, the last chaining variable,
we obtain H' r+1. And we know
that, since these two values are equal, all
of a sudden we have a candidate collision
for the compression function. Here, let me
circle the candidate collision, this is one
part of it and this is the other part of
it. Okay, so we have an equality
between two arguments given to the
compression function that happen to
produce the same value. The only way we
would not get a collision is if the
arguments happen to be the same. In other
words, what we're seeing here is if the
arguments to the compression function are
distinct, then we get a collision for
little h. So let's write it out more
precisely: so if H t is not equal to H' r,
or Mt is not equal to M' r,
or the padding blocks are distinct, then
we have a collision for the compression
function h and we're done, we're done and we can stop.
So, the only way we need to continue is if
this three-way disjunction doesn't hold.
So what does it mean that this disjunction
doesn't hold? well, so the only reason we
need to continue is if the second-to-last
chaining variables are equal, the last
blocks of the messages are equal and the
two padding blocks are equal. So what does
it mean that the two padding blocks are
equal? Remember that the message lengths
were encoded in the padding block. So, in
particular, this means that the length of M
and the length of M' is the same,
namely the t is equal to r. So from now on
I can assume t is equal to r. Whenever I
wrote r, I'm just gonna write t. But now we
can apply exactly the same argument to the
second to last chaining variables. In
other words, how was H t computed? Well
H t is computed by hashing the previous
chaining variable, namely H t-1,
with the second to last message block. And
similarly, H' t was computed, you
notice I replaced r by t, so H' t was
computed by hashing the previous chaining
variable along with the second to last
message block of M'. And because
these two are equal, now we get another
candidate collision for the compression
function. In other words, if H t+1 is not
equal to H' t-1, or M t-1 is not equal to
M' t-1, then basically we
have a collision for h, and we can stop,
we're done. So now, the only case when we
need to continue is if this condition over
here doesn't hold, namely, so let's suppose
that H t-1 is equal to H' t-1
and we already know that, let's
see, so M t is equal to M' t and
M t-1 is equal to M' t-1.
Suppose it so happens that these two
conditions hold, well, you can see that now
we can continue to iterate. In other
words, we can now apply exactly the same
argument to H t-1 and H' t-1
and so iterating this again and
again, we can iterate all the way to the
beginning of the message. Iterate to the
beginning of the message, and one of two
things must hold, either we find the
collision for the compression function
or it so happens that all the message blocks
of M and M' are the same. In other
words, for all i, M i is equal to M' i.
But this means, because the messages, we'd
reprove the messages are the same length,
this means that M is actually equal to M'.
But then, this contradicts the fact
that you gave me a collision to begin
with, so, in other words, this condition
over here, can't actually happen because
it contradicts the fact that M and M'
are actually a collision for the big
Merkle-Damgard function H. And, as
a result, this means that we have to find a
collision for the compression function, so
that, as we work our way from the end of
the message, all the way to the beginning,
at some point we must find the collision
for little h. Okay, so this basically
completes the proof of the theorems, I can
put a little QED block here, so basically
what this proof is, that if the little
compression function h is collision
resistant, then the big Merkle-Damgard
function H must also be collision
resistant. So, again, the reason why people
like this construction is it shows that
to construct big hash functions,
it suffices to construct just compression
functions for small inputs, and we're
gonna do that in the next segment.