So our goal for this segment is to build
secure compression functions. So
compression functions are collision
resistant. So just to remind you where we
are we looked at this Merkle Damguard
construction which takes a little
compression function and builds from it a
hash function for much, much larger
inputs. We proved this cute theorem that
in fact if a little compression function h
is collision resistant then plugging in
into the Merkle Damguard construction
gives us a collision resistant hash
function for larger inputs. So now in this
segment our goal is basically to build a
compression function that is collision
resistant. So we're going to see a couple
of constructions. And so the first
question that comes to mind is well, can
we build compression functions from
primitives that we already have? In
particular, we spent a lot of work to
build block cyphers and the question is
can we build compression functions from
block cyphers. And the answer is yes. And
let me show you how to do it. So assume we
have a certain block cypher here that
operates on N bits blocks, so the input is
an N bits, output is N bits. And then
there's this classic construction called a
Davies-Meyer construction which I wrote
down in symbols here. Basically says that
what you would do is, given the message
block and the chaining variable, all we do
is we encrypt the chaining variable using
the message block as the key. And then we
kind of do one more xor on the output. So
this might seem a little bizarre, because
remember the message block is something
that's completely under the control of the
adversary. He's trying to find the
collision so he can choose the message
blocks however he wants. And yet we're
using this message block as a key into a
block cypher. But nevertheless, we can
argue that this construction, at least
when E is what's called an ideal cypher,
we can argue that this construction is in
fact as collision resistant as possible.
So let me state the theorem. The theorem
states that, as I said, if E is an ideal
block cypher, meaning that it's a random
collection of K random permutations from
01 to the N to 01 to the N. Then under
that assumption that E's an ideal block
cypher, in fact, finding the collision for
this compression function H takes time,
two to the N over two. In particular, we
can show that anyone who is finding
collisions has to evaluate the encryption
and decryption functions at least 2 to
the N over 2 times. And if you think
about what that means, since the output of
this compression function is only N bytes
long, we know that there's always a
generic birthday attack that finds
collisions in time 2 to the N over 2.
So basically this theorem says that this
collision resistant function is as
collision resistant as possible. We can
find the collision in time 2 to the N
over 2 using the birthday attack but
there is no algorithm that will do better
than 2 to the n over 2. So this
is actually a very common compression
function used in collision resistance
hashing in fact of a SHA
functions all used Davies-Mayer. It turns
out that there is something special about
the Davies-Mayer construction that
makes collision resistant. If you just try
to guess the construction very likely you
will end up with something that is not
collision resistant. And so let me ask you
the following puzzle. Suppose we actually
define the compression function as
follows, namely all we do is we encrypt
the chaining variable H using the current
message block as the key. So the
difference is that we dropped this 'xor' H
in Davies-Mayer, we simply ignored it. So
it's not there. And the puzzle for you
is show me that this compression function
then is actually not collision resistant.
So, let's see, so we're trying to build a
collision, namely a distinct pair of HM
and H' M' that happen to collide
under this later function H. And my
question to you is how would you do it? So
I'm already going to tell you that you're
going to choose H, M, and M'
arbitrarily. The only requirement is that
M and M' are distinct. And then my
question is, how would you construct an H'
that would cause a collision to pop
out? So the answer is the first choice and
an easy way to see it is if we apply the
encryption function using M' to both
sides. Then we get that this is basically
E of M' applied to H', right.
this is what we get by applying encryption
using M' to the left hand side. And
if we imply encryption using M' to
the right hand side, the decryption
operator cancels out and we simply are
left with the encryption of M, H, which is
exactly the collision that we wanted to
find. So there. You can see that it's
basically by using the decryption function
D, it's very easy to build collisions for
this compression function. Now I should
tell you that in fact Davies-Meyer is not
unique. There are other ways to build
collision resistant compression functions
from block ciphers. For example, here's a
method called Miyaguchi Preneel. Miyaguchi
Preneel actually is used in WHIRLPOOL hash
function that we saw earlier. Here is
another method that happens to result in a
collision resistant compression function.
And there are twelve variants like this
playing with XORs and placing the
variables in different slots that will
actually give a collision resistant
mechanism. But there are also many, many
variants of this like we saw in the
previous puzzle that are not collision
resistant. So here's. Another example,
that's not collision resistant. And I'm
gonna leave it as a homework problem to
figure out a collision for this
construction. So now, basically, we have
all the ingredients to describe the
[inaudible] 256 hash function. I'll tell
you that it's a Merkel-Damgard
construction, exactly as the one that we
saw before. It uses a Davies-Mayer
compression function. And so the only
question is, what's the underlying block
cipher for Davies-Mayer? And that block
cipher is called SHACAL-2. And I'll
just tell you it's parameters. It uses a
512 bit key. And remember the key is taken
from the message block. So, this is really
what the message block is. And it so
happens to be 512 bits. Which means the
SHA-256 will process its input
message 512 bits at a time. And in the
block size, for this block cipher is
256 bits. And these are the chaining variable.
So this would be H i-1.
And this would be successive chaining variable.
So now you have a complete
understanding of how SHA-256 works.
Module of this cipher SHACAL-2 I'm not going to describe here.
So as I said, one class of compression functions is built from block cyphers. It
turns out there's another class of
compression functions that's built using
hard problems from number theory, and I
want to very briefly show you one example.
And we call these compression functions
provable because if you can find the
collision on this compression function
then you're going to be able to solve a
very hard number theoretic problem which
is believed to be intractable. And as a
result, if the number theory problem is
intractable, the resulting compression
function is provably a collision
resistant. So here's how this compression
function works. Basically we're going to
choose a large prime piece, so this is a
gigantic prime, something like 700 digits,
2,000 bits. And then we're going to
choose two random values, U and V, between
one and P. And now let's define the
compression function as follows. It takes
two numbers between 0, and p-1,
and it's gonna output one number between
0, and  p-1. So it's compression
ratio is 2 to 1. And takes two
numbers. And outputs one number. In the
range 0 to p-1.
And it does it basically by computing double exponentiation. It
computes u to the H times v to the n.
And the theorem, which, right now, I'm just
gonna state as a fact. This fact actually
turns out to be fairly straightforward to
prove, and we're gonna do it later on when
we get to the number theoretic part of the
course. The fact is, that if you can find
a collision for this compression function,
then you can solve a standard heart
problem in number theory called a discreet
log problem. Everyone believes discrete
log is hard, and as a result, this
compression function is provably collision
resistant. So you might ask me why do
people not use this compression function
in practice. Why would we not use this for
SHA-256? And the answer is that this
gives very slow performance in comparison
to what you get from a block cipher. So
this is not really used for any
compression functions. However, if for
some reason you really only want to, say,
MAC or sign. Just one long message, and
you have a whole day to do it, then
certainly you can use this type of
compression function. And even though it's
slow, you'll get something that's provably
collision resistant. Okay, so that's the
end of this segment. And now we're finally
ready to talk about HMAC, which we're
gonna do in the next segments.