So now that we understand what collision
resistant hash functions are and we know
how to construct them, we're ready to
describe very popular MAC called HMAC. So
let me remind you what the Merkle-Damgard construction is. Basically we have a
small compression function h from which we
build a large hash function, which is
collision resistant assuming the
compression function is collision resistant.
The question we're gonna ask
this segment is can we use the large hash
function to construct a MAC directly
without having to rely on a PRF. So here's
the first thing that comes to mind.
Suppose I give you a Merkle-Damgard hash
function so you notice a mapped, it hashes
large messages into small digests and we
want to convert that directly into a Mac.
The first thing that comes to mind is well
why don't we just hash the concatenation
of the MAC key as long with the message
that we're trying to MAC? It turns out
that this is completely insecure so let me
ask you, why is this is insecure?
The answer is the standard extension of that, and if you think back to the
Merkle-Damgard construction, you realize
that if I tell you the tag of a particular
message, in other words I tell you the
value at this point. It's very easy for
the attacker to just add another block and
then compute one more application of the
compression function H. And now they'll be
able to get the tag for the original
message concatenated the padding block,
concatenated the word W that they added
themselves and as a result this is an
existential forgery. Yes, so basically
this is exactly what we get here. Where
after concatenating the padding block, the
attacker can actually concatenate whatever
he wants and he would get the tag on this
combined message. So this is totally
insecure and I cannot tell you how many
products have actually made this mistake
where they assumed that this is a secure
Mac. This is completely insecure and
should never ever, ever, ever be used.
Instead there's a standardized method to
convert a collision resistant hash
function to a MAC and that method is
called HMAC. So in particular we could use
the SHA-256 hash function to build
this MAC. The output is going to be 256
bits and in fact HMAC is believed to be a
pseudo-random function, so in fact out of
SHA-256 we get a pseudo-random
function that outputs 256 bit outputs. So
let me show the construction. Here's the
construction in symbols and it works as
follows. First we take our key k and we
concatenate what's we call an internal pad
to it, an ipad to it. This makes it into
one block of the Merkle-Damguard
construction, so for example this would be
512 bits in the case of SHA256. We prepend
this to the message M and then we hash.
Now this by itself we just said is
completely insecure, however what HMAC
does in addition, it takes the output,
which is 256 bits, it prepends to that the
key again XOR with, what's called the
outer pad, the opad. This also becomes
512 bits. It's one block. And then it
hashes the combination of these two to
finally obtain the resulting tag on the
message M. So it's more rather looking
into some symbols. It's more instructive
to look at HMAC in pictures. And so you
can see that here are the two keys k XOR
inner-pad, which is then fed into the
Merkle-Damgard chain. And then the
resulting output of this chain is fed into
another Merkle-Damgard chain and finally
the final output is produced. Okay, so
this is how HMAC works in pictures and
now I want to argue that we've already
seen something very similar to this. In
particular, if you can think of the
compression function H as a PRF where the
key is the first, the top inputs, then
what we're actually doing here is we're
evaluating this PRF H at a fixed IV and
the result here is a random value which
we're gonna call K1. And then we apply the
Merkle-Damgard chain and we can do the
same thing on the outer pad. If you think
of little h as a PRF where the key is the
upper inputs. Again, we're applying this
PRF using a different key to a fixed value
IV and as a result, we're gonna get
another random value K2 So now when we
compute HMAC using these keys, K1 and K2,
this would actually look very familiar
this is basically NMAC. It's identical to
NMac that we discussed in a previous
segment. And notice to argue that this is
an NMac construction we have to assume
that the compression function, little h,
is a PRF where the key is actually the
lower inputs to the function. Now let me
say that these pads, the ipad and the
opad , these are fixed constants that are
specified in the HMAC standard. So these
are literally just 512 bit constants that
never change. And so when we go back to
look at the complete HMAC construction,
you realize that the main difference
between this and NMAC is that these keys
here since they are dependent, you notice
they're both just the same key XORed
with different constants. Essentially, the
keys K1 and K2 are also somewhat dependent
because they're computed by applying a PRF
to the same fixed value, namely IV, but
with dependent keys. And so to argue that
K1 and K2 are pseudo random and
independent of one another, one has to
argue that the compression function not
only is a PRF where when the inputs, the
top input, is the key inputs, but it's
also a PRF when dependent keys are used.
But under those assumptions, basically the
exact same analysis NMAC would apply to
HMAC and we would get security argument
that HMAC is a secure MAC. So as I said,
HMAC can be proven secure under these PRF
assumptions about the compression function
H. The security bounds are just as they
are for NMAC, in other words you should
not have to change the key as long as the
number of messages you're MAC-ing Is
smaller than the size of the output tag to
the one-half, but for HMAC SHA256 the
output space is 2 to the 256. The square
root of that would put us at 2 to the
128. Which means that basically you can
use HMAC SHA256 for as many outputs as you
want, and you'll always maintain security.
And as a last point about HMAC I'll tell
you that TLS Standard actually requires
that one support HMAC SHA-196 which means that
HMAC built form the SHA1 function and
truncated to 96 bits. SHA-1 remember
outputs 160 bits. And we truncated to the
most significant 96 bits. Now you might be
wondering, remember we said before that
SHA-1 is no longer considered a secure
hash function, so how come we're using
SHA-1 in HMac? Well, it turns out it's
actually fine. Because HMAC the analysis
of HMAC doesn't need SHA-1 to be
collision resistant. All it needs is that
the compression function of SHA-1
one be a PRF when either input is allowed
to be the key. And as far as we know
that's still correct for the underlying
compression function for SHA-1.
Even though it might not be collision
resistant. As far as we know it's still
fine to use it inside of HMAC. So this is
the end of our discussion of HMAC and in
our next segment we're going to look at
timing attacks on HMAC.