In this module, we're gonna talk about a
new concept called collision resistance,
which plays an important role in providing
message integrity. Our end goal is to
describe a very popular MAC algorithm
called HMAC, that's widely used in
internet protocols. HMAC itself, is built
from collision resistant hash functions.
Before we do that, let's do a quick recap
of where we are. In the last module we
talked about message integrity where we
said that the MAC system is secure if it's
existentially unforgeable under a chosen
message attack. This means that even an
attacker who is given the tag on arbitrary
messages of his choice cannot construct a
tag for some new message. And then we
showed that in fact any secure PRF
immediately gives us a secure MAC. And so
then we turned around and said well can we
build secure PRFs that take large messages
as inputs? And so we looked at four
constructions. The first construction was
based on CBC, we call it when we looked at
two variants of it, one called encrypted
CBC and one called CMAC. And we said that
these are commonly used with AES. In fact,
in the 802.11i standard, a CBC-MAC is used
for message integrity. In particular, with
the AES algorithm. We looked at another
mode called NMAC, which also converts a
PRF for short inputs into a PRF that's
capable of taking very large messages as
inputs. And these two were both sequential
MAC-s. We then looked at the parallelizable
MAC called PMAC which again was able to
convert a PRF for small inputs into a PRF
for very large inputs. But it did so in a
parallel fashion so a multiprocessor
system would be more efficient with PMAC
than, say, with CBC-MAC. All three of
these built a MAC for large messages by
constructing a PRF for large messages. And
then we looked at the Carter-Wegman MAC
which is actually not a PRF. It's a
randomized MAC so a single message could
actually have many, many different valid
tags and therefore a Carter-Wegman MAC is
actually not a PRF. And if you remember,
the Carter-Wegman MAC was built by
first of all, taking the bulk message and
hashing it down to a small tag using a
fast one-time MAC and then encrypting that
tag using a PRF. The benefit of the
Carter-Wegman MAC was that, as we said, the
hashing of the bulk message is done using
a fast one time MAC. And then in this
module, we're gonna construct MAC-s from
this new concept called collision
resistance. And so the first thing we're
gonna do is construct collision resistant
hash functions. So let's first of all
start by defining what does it mean for a
hash function to be collision resistant.
So think of a hash function from some
message space to a tag space T, and you
should be thinking of the message space as
much, much bigger than the tag space. So
the messages could be gigabytes long, but
the tags would only be like 160 bits. Now
a collision for the function H is a pair
of messages m0, m1, that happen to be
distinct. However, when you apply the
function H to them, you end up with the
same output. So the image you should have
in your mind is essentially there are two
inputs, m0 and m1, and they belong to this
gigantic message space. However, when we
apply the hash function to them, they
happen to collide and they both map to the
same output in the tag space. Now we say
that the function is collision resistant
if it's hard to find collisions for this
function. Now this should seem a little
bit counterintuitive because. We know that
the output space is tiny compared to the
input space. So, by the pigeonhole
principle, there must be lots and lots and
lots of messages that map to the same
output. Just because there isn't enough
space in the output space to accommodate
all the messages without collisions. And
so, we know that there are lots of
collisions, and the question is, is there
an efficient algorithm that finds any such
collisions explicitly. So we say the, the
function is collision resistant, if, for
all explicit efficient algorithms A. And
these algorithms are not able to print the
collision for the function H, okay? And as
usual, we'll define the advantage as the
probability that the algorithm A is able
to output a collision. Now I'm not gonna
formalize a term explicit here. All I'll
say is that it's not enough to just say
that an algorithm exists, and algorithm
that simply prints a collision. Cause we
know many collisions exist. What we
actually want is an explicit algorithm
that we can actually write down and run on
a computer to generate these collisions.
There are ways to formalize that, but I'm
not gonna do that here. Now a classic
example of a collision resistant hash
function is SHA-256 which happens
to output at 256 bits but can take
arbitrary large input. For example, it can
take gigabytes and gigabytes of data and
it will map it all to 256 bits. And yet
nobody knows how to find collisions for
this particular function. So just to show
you that this concept of collision
resistance is very useful, let's see a
very quick application for it. In
particular, let's see how we can trivially
build a MAC given a collision resistant
hash function. So, suppose we have a MAC
for short messages. So you should be
thinking something like AES, which can MAC
sixteen byte messages. And then, suppose
we have a hash function, a collision
resistant hash function from a large message
space, that contains gigabyte messages
into our small message space. Say, into
sixteen byte outputs. Then, basically, we
can define a new MAC, let's call it Ibig,
which happens to be MAC-ing large
messages. And we'll define it simply by
applying the small MAC to the output of
the hash function. And how do we verify a
MAC? Well, basically, given a tag we
verify it by rehashing the given message
and then checking that small MAC actually
verifies under the given tag. Okay, so
this is a very simple way to show you how
collision resistance can take a primitive
that's built for small inputs and expand it
into a primitive that's built for very
large inputs. And in fact we're going to
see this not just for MAC-s. Later on when
we talk about digital signatures, we're
going to do the same thing. We're going to
build a digital signature scheme for small
inputs and then we're going to use
collision resistance to expand the input
space and make it as large as we want. So
the security theorem basically isn't
something that's trivial here. Basically
it says if the underlying MAC is secure
and H is collision resistant, then the
combination which can actually MAC large
messages, is also a secure MAC. And as
a quick example, let's apply this to AES.
So let's use the one example that we
mentioned, SHA-256. So in this
case SHA-256 outputs 256 bit outputs,
which is 32 bytes. So we have to build a
MAC that can MAC 32 byte messages. And the
way we could do that is basically by
applying the sixteen byte AES, plugging it
into a two block CBC. A two block CBC
would expand AES from a PRF on sixteen
bytes to a PRF on 32 bytes. And then take
the output of SHA-256 and plug it into
this two block CBC based on AES. And then
we get a very, very simple, MAC which is
secure assuming AES is a PRF and SHA-256
is collision resistant. So one thing I
wanted to point out is that in fact
collision resistance is necessary for this
construction to work. So in fact,
collision resistance is not just a made-up
term. Collision resistance really is kind
of the essence of why this combined MAC is
secure. And so let's just assume for a
minute that the function H, the hash
function we're using, is not collision
resistant. In other words, there is an
algorithm that can find two distinct
messages that happen to map to the same
output. In this case, the combined MAC. Is
not going to be secure because what the
adversary can do is simply use a chosen
message attack to get a tag for m0. And
then output m1 comma that tag as a forgery
and indeed T is a valid MAC for m1 because
H(m1) happens to be equal to H(m0). And
so in doing so just with a one chosen
message attack the attacker was able to
break this combined MAC simply because the
hash function was not collision resistant.
So it should be, again I want to emphasize
that if someone advertised even one
collision for SHA-256, you know two
messages, just one pair of messages that
happen to have the same output under
SHA-256 that would already make this
construction insecure cause an attacker
could then ask for the tag on one message
and in doing so he would obtain the tag on
the other message as well, and that would
count as an existential forgery. Okay, so
already, we see the collision resistance
is a very useful primitive, in that it
lets us expand the input space of
cryptographic primitives. I wanna show you
one more application where a collision
resistance is directly used for message
integrity. Imagine again, we have files that we
wanna protect. Let's imagine these files
are actually software packages that, we
wanna install on our system. So here are
three different software packages. You
know, maybe one is GCC, on is Emacs, and
another one is, I don't know, VI. Now the
user wants to download the software
package and he wants to make sure that he
really did get a version of the package
that he downloaded and it's not some
version that the attacker tampered with
and modified its contents. So what he
could do is basically refer to a read-only
public space that's relatively small. All
it has to do is hold small hashes of these
software packages. So there isn't a lot of
space needed here. The only requirement is
that this space is read-only. In other
words, the attacker cannot modify the
hashes stored in this space. And then,
once he consults this public space, he can
very easily compute the hash of a package
that he downloaded. Compare it to the
value in the public space. And if the two
match. Then he knows that the version of
the package he downloaded is, in fact, a
correct one. Why is that true? Well,
because the function H is collision
resistant. The attacker cannot find an F1
path, they would have the same hash as F1.
And as a result, the attacker cannot
modify F1 without being detected because
there's no way that the hash of his F1
[inaudible] would map to the value that's
stored in the public space. So, the reason
I brought up this example is, I wanted to
contrast this with the MAC example. We
kinda saw a similar situation with MAC-s.
In the MAC example, we needed a secret key
to verify the individual file tags. But we
didn't need a resource that was a read
only public space. With
collision-resistant hashes, we kind of get
the exact compliment where in fact we
don't need a key to verify. Anyone can
verify. You don't need a secret key for
it. However, now all of a sudden we need
this extra resource which is some space
that the attacker cannot modify. And, in
fact, later on, we're gonna see that with
digital signatures, we can kind get to the
best of both worlds, where we have both
public verifiability, and we don't need a
read only space. But so far, with either
MAC-s or collision resistance, we can have
one, but not the other. So, I'll tell you
that, in fact, this kind of scheme is very
popular. In fact, Linux distributions
often use public space where they
advertise hashes of their software
packages. And anyone can make sure that
they downloaded the right software package
before installing it on their computer. So
this is, in fact, something that's used
quite extensively in the real world. Okay,
so in the next segment we'll talk about
generic attack on collision resistance and
then we'll go ahead and build collision
resistant hash functions.