In this segment, we're going to construct
two classic MACS, the CBC-MAC and the
NMAC. Recall in the last segment, we said
that if you give me a secure PRF, then
that secure PRF can actually be used to
construct a secure MAC, simply by defining
the signature on the message m as the
value of the function at the point m. The
only caveat was that the output of the
PRF F had to be large. For example, it
could be 80 bits or 128 bits, and that
would generate a secure MAC Now we also
said that because AES is a secure PRF,
essentially AES already gives us a secure
MAC, except that it can only process
sixteen byte messages. And the question
now is, given a PRF for short messages
like AES for sixteen byte messages, can we
construct a PRF for long messages that are
potentially gigabytes long? And this is
shorthand for what's coming. I'm going to
denote by X, the set  to the N where N
is the block size for the underlying PRF.
So since we're always going to be thinking
of AES as the underlying PRF, you can
think of N as essentially 128 bits. So
the first construction is called the
encrypted CBC MAC, or ECBC for short.
Encrypted CBC MAC. So ECBC uses a PRF that
takes messages in the set X  to the N
and outputs messages in the same set X.
And what we're going to be building is a
PRF that basically takes pairs of keys. It
takes very long messages, in fact
arbitrarily long messages, and I'll
explain this in just a second and it
outputs also tags in  to the N. So
that's our goal. Now what is this X to the
less than or equal to L? The point here is
that in fact CBC MAC can take very long
messages up to L blocks. L could be a
million or a billion. But it could also
take variable length messages as inputs.
In other words, X less than or equal to L
means that we allow the input to be
messages that contain an arbitrary number
of blocks between one and L. So each CBC
can process messages that are one block
long, two blocks long, ten blocks long,
100 blocks long. It's perfectly fine to
give it variable size inputs. But just to
keep the discussion simple, we up our
bounds the maximum length by capital L. So
let's see how ECBC works. Well, we start
by taking our message and breaking it into
blocks, each block is as long as a block
of the underlying function f, and then
essentially we run through the CBC chain
except that we don't output intermediate
values. So you notice we basically encrypt
the first block and then feed the results
into the XOR with the second block and
then feed that into f again, and we do
that again and again and again and finally
we get a value out here. Which is called
the CBC outputs of this long chain. And
then, I would like to point your attention
to the fact that we do one more encryption
step. And this step is actually done using
an independent key, K1. That's different
and chosen independently of the key K, and
finally the output gives us the tag. So in
this case the tag would be N bits long,
but we also mentioned in the previous
segment that it's fine to truncate the tag
to less than N bits long as long as one
over two to the end is negligible. So now
you can see that FECBC takes a pair of
keys as inputs, it can process
variable length messages and it produces
an output in the set X. So you might be
wondering what this last encryption step
is for. And I'll tell you that the
function that's defined without this last
encryption step is called the raw CBC
function. In other words, if we simply
stop processing over here, and we take
that as the output, that's called raw CBC.
And as we'll see in a minute, raw CBC is
actually not a secure MAC. So this last
step is actually critical for making
the MAC secure. So another class of
construction for converting a small PRF
into a large PRF is called NMAC,
for Nested MAC. Now, the NMAC starts
from PRF that, as before, takes inputs
in X, but outputs elements in the key
space. And remember that for CBC, the
output has to be in the set X. Here, the
output needs to be in the key space K. And
again, we basically obtain the PRF F-NMAC, which takes pairs of keys as inputs.
Again, can process variable length
messages up until L blocks. And the output
is an element in the key space. And the
way NMAC works is kind of, starts as
before. We take our message, and we break
it into blocks. Each block is, again, as
big as the block length of the underlying
PRF. And now we take our key and we feed
our key as the key input into the function
F. And the message block is given as the
data input into the function F. What comes
out is the key for the next block of NMAC.
So now we have a new key for the next
evaluation of the PRF. And the data for
the next evaluation is the next message
block and so on and so forth until we
reach the final output. The final output
is gonna be an element in K. Okay? And
just as before, in fact, if we stop here.
The function that we obtain is called a
cascade function. And we're gonna look at
cascade in more detail in just a minute.
So cascade will output an element in K.
However, that, as we'll see again, is not
a secure MAC. To get a secure MAC, what we
do is we need to map this element T,
which is in K, into the set X. And so,
typically, as we'll see, NMAC is used
with, PRFs, where the block length, X, is
much bigger than the key length. And so
what we do is we simply append fixed pad.
fpad is called a fixed pad that gets
appended to this tag T. And then this
becomes, this input here, this block here
becomes an element of X. We feed this into
the function, and again, notice here that
there's an independent key that's being
used for the last encryption step. And
then finally, the last tag is an element
of K which we output as the output of
NMAC. So remember without the last
encryption step, the function is called a
cascade. With the last step as we'll see
which is necessary for security, we
actually get a PRF which outputs elements
in K, and can process variable length
messages that are up to L blocks long.
Alright so that is the NMAC
construction. So now we have two MACs. That
we can use to build a large PRF, from AES,
basically. So before I analyze the
security of MAC constructions, I'd like
you to understand better what the last
encryption step is for. So, let's start
with NMAC. So I explained that it
is actually very easy too see that if we
omitted the last encryption step. In other
words, if we just use the cascade
function, then the MAC will be completely
insecure. Okay so suppose we look at this
MAC to find over here. In other words, all
we do is we output directly the cascade
applied to m without the last encryption
step. So let me ask you how do you forge
tags in this MAC. And I guess I've kinda
given it away that this answer isn't
correct. So I hope everybody sees that the
answer is, that, in fact, given one chosen
message query, you can mount an
existential forgery. And the reason is,
I'll show you in a second in the diagram,
but let me write it out in symbols first.
The reason if, if you're given the output
of the cascade function applied to a
message M. I can derive from it, me being
the adversary, I can derive from it the
cascade applied to the message M
concatenated W for any message W, for any
W. So first of all, it should be clear
that this is enough to mount an
existential forgery because essentially by
asking for a tag on this message I obtain
the tag on this longer message which I can
then output as my forgery. Okay, so the
MAC is insecure because given a MAC in one
message, I can produce the MAC in another
message. But let's go back to the diagram
describing cascade, and see why this is
true. And so let's see what happens if
this last step isn't there. As an
attacker, what I can do, I can add one
more block here, which we called W. And
then, then basically, I can take the
output of cascade, which is this value T.
And we can simply apply the function F to
it again. So here I'll take this T value.
I'll plug it in to F. And plug my last
block W into it and what I'll get is T
prime which is, well, the evaluation of
cascade on the message M concatenated W.
In [inaudible] calculated t prime, which I can use
for my existential forgery. Okay, so this
kind of shows you why this property of
cascade holes. This is called an extension
attack, Where giving a tag of the message
m I can deduce the tag for the extension
of m. And in fact for any extension of my
choice. So basically, Cascade is
completely insecure if we don't do this
last encryption step, and the last
encryption step here basically prevents
this type of extension attack. I can tell
you by the way that in fact extension
attacks are the only attacks on a cascade
and that could be made to precise. But I'm
not gonna do that here. The next question
is, why did we have the extra encryption
block in the ECBC construction? So again,
let me show you that without this extra
encryption block ECBC is insecure. So
let's define a map that uses raw CBC. In
other words, it's the same as CBC MAC, but
without the last encryption step. And
let's see that, that MAC is also insecure.
Except now, the attack is a little bit
more difficult than a simple extension
attack. So suppose the attacker is given
this value, the raw CBC value for a
particular message M. And now, the
attacker wants to extend and compute the
MAC on some message M, concatenated on
with some word W. So here's our W well the
core attacker can take this value and try
to XOR the two together but now you
realize he has to evaluate the function.
At this point. But he doesn't know what
this key K is. And as a result, he doesn't
know what the output of the function is.
So he simply can't just depend on
block W, and compute the value of
raw CBC on N concatenated W. However, it
turns out they he can actually evaluate
this function. By using the chosen message
attack. And I wanna show you how to do
that. Okay, so we said that basically so
our goal is to show raw CBC is insecure.
So let's look at a particular attack. So
in the attack, the adversary is going to
start by requesting the tag on a
particular message m that's a one-block
message. So what does it mean to apply CBC
to a one-block message? Well basically,
all you do is you just apply the function
f directly. So what you get is the tag,
which is just the application of f
directly to the one-block message m. Good,
so now the adversary has this value T. And
now I claim that he can define this
message, M prime, which contains two
blocks. The first block is M, the second
block is T XOR M. And I claim that the
value T that he just received is a valid
tag for this two block message, M Prime.
So let's see why that's true. Well, so
suppose we apply the raw CBC construction
to this message M prime. So if you plug it
in directly what, let's see. The way it
would work is first of all, the first
message M is processed by encrypting it
directly using the function F. Then we XOR
the results with the second block
with is T-XOR-M. And then we apply F to
the results of that. That is the
definition of raw CBC. Now what do we know about
F(k,m)? F(k,m) is simply this value T by
definition. So the next step we get is
essentially T-XOR-T-XOR-M. But
this T- XOR-T simply goes away and what
we get is F(k,m). Which is, of course, T.
And as a result, T is a valid MAC for the
two block message, (M, T-XOR-M). So
the adversary was able to produce this
valid tag T for this two block message
that he never queried. And therefore, he
was able to break the MAC. So let's look
at the ECBC diagram for just one more
second. And let me point out that if you
don't include this last encryption step in
the computation of the MAC, essentially,
the MAC would be insecure because of the
attack that we just saw. And I'll tell you
that there are many products that do this
incorrectly. And, in fact, there are even
standards that do this incorrectly, so
that the resulting MAC is insecure. You
now know that this needs to be done, and
you won't make this mistake yourself. So
let's state the CBC and NMAC security
theorems. And so the statement is as usual
for any message length that we'd like to,
apply the MAC to. Essentially for every
PRF adversary A, there's an efficient
adversary B and, you know, these are kind
of the usual statements. Where, the facts
that you need to know are the error terms
which are kind of similar in both cases.
By the way, I'd like to point out that the
analysis for CBC actually uses the fact
that F is a PRP even though we never had
to invert F during the computation of
ECBC, the analysis is better if you assume
that F is actually a PRP. In other words,
it's invertible, not just a function. For
a MAC, the PRF need not be invertible.
So what these error terms basically say
is that these MACs are secure, as long as,
key is not used to MAC more than square
root of X or square root of K messages. So
for AES of course this would be a two to
the 64. But I want to show you an example
of how you would use these bounds. So
here, I've stated the security theorem again
for the CBC MAC, and Q here, again, is the
number of messages that are MACed with a
particular key. So suppose we wanted to
ensure that for all adversaries that the
adversary has an advantage of less than
one over two to the 32 in distinguishing
the PRF from a truly random function.
Suppose that is our goal. Well, by the
security theorem, what that means is we
need to ensure that Q squared over X is
less than one over two to the 32, right.
We want this term to be, well, I'm going
to ignore this two here just for
simplicity. We want to ensure this term is
less than one over two to the 32 and this
term, of course, is negligible, so we can
just ignore it. This would imply that this
term is also less than one over two to the
32. Okay, so if we want to ensure that the
advantage is less than one over two to the
32, we need to ensure that Q squared over
X is less than one over two to the 32. For
AES, basically this means that after MACing
two to the 48 messages, you have to
change your key. Otherwise, you won't
achieve the security level. So you can
MAC, at most, two to the 48 messages. You
notice that if I plug in triple DES, which
has a much shorter block, only 64 bits.
The same result says you now have to
change your key every 65,000 messages. So
this basically is quite problematic
whereas this is fine. This is actually a,
a very fairly large number. For
AES this means you have to change
your key only every 16 billion
messages which is perfectly reasonable.
And so this is one of the reasons why AES
has a larger block, than triple DES. Some of these modes remain
secure and you don't have to change your
key as often as you would with triple
DES. Okay, so I want to show you
that in fact these attacks are not just in
the statements in the security theorem, in
fact there really are real attacks that
correspond to these values. Now the macs
really do become insecure after you sign,
you know, square root of X or square root
of K messages. So I'm going to show you an
attack on both PRFs so either ECBC or
NMAC. Assuming that the underlying
function is a PRP, is actually a block
cipher like AES. Let's call F big, let's
say that F big is either F ECBC or F NMAC.
So F big means that it's a PRF for large
messages. Now, it turns out both
constructions have the following extension
property. Namely, if you give me a
collision. On messages X and Y. Then, in
fact, that also implies a collision on an
extension of X and Y. In other words, if I
append W to both X and Y, I'll also get a
collision on the resulting words. So it's
fairly easy to convince yourself that this
extension property holds, you do it just
by staring at the diagram for a second.
And so imagine I give you two messages
that happen to collide at this point. Now
remember, I assumed that F is a PRP. So
once you fix K1, it's a one to one
function. So if the two messages happen to
map to the same value at the output. This
means they also happen to map to the same
value at the output of the raw CBC
function. But if they map to the same
function, that means that if I add another
block, let's call it a W. And I take this
output here. Then I'm computing the same
value for both messages. And I'll get, for
both messages, I'll get the same value at
this point, too. And when I encrypt,
again, with K1, I'll also get, you know,
so there's one more F here. I'll also get
the same output, final output, after I've
appended the block W. Okay, so if the two
values happen to be the same for two
distinct messages. If I appended block W
to both messages, I'm still gonna get the
same value out. It's easy to convince
yourself that the same is true for NMAC
as well. Okay, so both of these, PRFs have
this extension property. So based on this,
we can define an attack. So here's the
extension property stated again. And the
attack would work as follows. Suppose I
issued square of Y chosen message
queries. So, for AES, remember, the value
of Y is basically  to the 128. So this
would mean that I would be asking, two to
the 64 shows in message queries. For just
arbitrary messages in the input space.
Well, what will happen is, I'll obtain,
well, I'll obtain two to the 64 message
MAC pairs. Now, we're gonna see in the
next module, actually, there's something
called a birthday paradox. Some of you may
have heard of it already. It basically
says that if I have two to the 64 random
elements of a space of size two to the
128, there's a good chance that two of
them are the same. So I'm gonna look for
two distinct messages. MU and MV, for
which the corresponding MACs are the same.
Okay, and as I said, by the birthday
paradox, these are very likely to exist.
Once I have that, now I've basically found
MU and MV to have the same MAC. And as a
result, what I can do is, I can extend MU
with an arbitrary word W, and ask for the
tag for the word MU concatenated W. But
because NU and NV happen to have the same
output, I know that NU concatenated W has
the same output as NV concatenated W. So
now that I've obtained the output for NU
concatenated W, I also have the output for
NV concatenated W. And therefore I have
obtained my forgery. Okay, so now T is
also a forgery for the message MV
concatenated W which I've never asked
before. And therefore, this is as valid as
a potential forgery. Okay, so this is kind
of an acute attack and the bottom line
here is that in fact after square root of
Y queries, I am able to forge a MAC with
fairly good probability. Okay, so what
does square root of Y mean? If we go back
to the security theorems, this means that
basically for ECBC after square root of X
or for NMAC after square root of K,
messages have been MACed, the MAC becomes
insecure and the attacker can actually
find new MACs for messages for which he
was never given a MAC for. So again, this
is an acute attack that shows the bounds
of the theorem really are real. And as a
result these downs that derived in this
example are real and you should never use
a single key to MAC more than, say, two
to 48 messages with AES based CBC. So to
conclude, I'll just mention that we've
seen two examples. We saw ECBC and NMAC.
ECBC is in fact, a very commonly used MAC
that's built from AES. 80211I, for example,
uses ECBC with AES for integrity.
There's also a NIST standard called CMAC,
that we'll talk in the next segment, that
also is based on the ECBC MAC. NMAC with
contrast is not typically used with a
block cipher. And the main reason is, in
order to [inaudible] in the NMAC construction,
the key changes from block to block. That
means that the whole AES key expansion has
to be computed and recomputed on every
block. And AES is not designed to perform
well when he changes key very rapidly. And
so, typically, when you use NMAC, you use
block ciphers that are better at changing
their keys on every block. And as a
result, NMAC typically is not used with
AES. But in fact, N Mac is a basis of a
very popular MAC called HMAC, which we're
also gonna look at next. And you'll see
very clearly, the NMAC underlying the HMAC construction. Okay, so that's the end
of this segment, and we'll talk about more
MACs in the next segment.