In this module, we're gonna stop talking
about encryption,
and instead discuss message integrity.
Next, we will come back to encryption, and show
how to provide both encryption and integrity.
So as I said, our goal here is to provide
integrity without any confidentiality.
There are actually in fact many cases in
the real world where this comes up.
For example, you can think of
operating system files on your disk.
Say if you're using Windows, all the Windows
operating system files on disk are not confidential,
they're public and known to the world,
but it is quite important to make sure that
they're not modified by a virus or some malware.
That's an example where you want
to provide integrity but you don't
care about confidentiality. Another
example is banner ads on web pages.
The provider of the ads doesn't care
at all if someone copies them
and shows them to other people.
So there's no confidentiality issue at all.
But they do care about modifying those ads.
So, for example, they do wanna prevent people from
changing the ads into different types of ads.
So that's another example where integrity matters
but confidentiality is not important at all.
So how do we provide message integrity?
The basic mechanism is what's called a MAC,
a message authentication code, MAC.
And the way we do it is as follows.
So here we have our friends, Alice and Bob.
They have a shared key, K, which is not known
to the attacker, but known to both of them.
And there's a public message M that Alice
wants to send to Bob,
such that an attacker along the way cannot
modify this message on its way to Bob.
The way Alice does it, is by using what's called
a MAC signing algorithm, we'll denote it by S,
where the MAC signing algorithm takes
as input the key and the message,
and produces a very short tag. The tag could
be like 90 bits or 100 bits, or so on.
Even though the message is gigabytes long,
the tag is actually very, very short.
Then, she appends the tag to the message
and sends the combination of the two to Bob.
Bob receives the message and the tag,
and then he runs what's called a MAC
verification algorithm on this tag.
So the MAC verification algorithm takes
as input to the key, the message,
and the tag and it says basically yes or no,
depending on whether the message is valid
or whether it's been tampered with.
Okay, so more precisely, what is a MAC?
Well, we said the MAC basically consists of
two algorithms,
a signing algorithm and a verification algorithm.
As usual, they're defined over a key space,
a message space, and a tag space.
And as we said, it's a pair of algorithms.
So the signing algorithm will output a
tag in the tag space, and the verification
algorithm, basically given the key, the
messages and the tag, will output yes or no.
And I want to remind you as usual there are
these consistency requirements, such that
for every K in the key space and for every
message in the message space,
it so happens that if I sign a message
using a particular key,
and then I verify the tag using the same
key, I shall get yes in response.
So this is the standard consistency
requirement which is the analog of
the one that we saw for encryption.
Now, one thing I'd like to point out is that
integrity really does require a shared
key between Alice and Bob.
And, in fact, there's a common mistake
that people make, where they try to
provide integrity without actually a
shared key. So here's an example.
So consider CRC. CRC stands for cyclic
redundancy check. This is a classic
checksum algorithm that's designed to
detect random errors in messages.
So imagine, instead of using a key to
generate the tag, Alice basically uses a
CRC algorithm which is keyless. Doesn't
take any key, to generate a tag.
And then she appends this tag to the
message, she sends it over to Bob,
Bob will basically verify that the CRC is
still correct. In other words, Bob will still
verify the tag is equal to CRC(m).
And if so the verification algorithm
will say yes, and otherwise the
verification algorithm will say no.
So the problem with this is this is
very easy for an attacker to defeat.
In other words, an attacker can very easily
modify the message and route,
and fool Bob into thinking that the
new message is a valid one.
The way the attacker will do it
is he'll cancel the message in the tag.
He'll simply block them. And then he'll
produce his own message,
M prime, and compute his own CRC
on this message M prime,
and then send the concatenation
of the two over to Bob.
Bob will run the verification algorithm,
verification will work properly because
in fact the right-hand side is in fact
a valid CRC for the left-hand side.
And as a result, Bob would think that this
message came from Alice but in fact its been
completely modified by the attacker and had
nothing to do with the original message that Alice sent.
Okay, so the problem is, because CRC
doesn't have a key, there's no difference
between Alice and the attacker. And as a result,
Bob doesn't know where the message came from.
Once we introduce a key, now Alice can do
something that the attacker can't do.
And as a result, she might be able to compute a
tag that the attacker can't modify.
So the point to remember is that CRC is designed
to detect random errors, not malicious errors.
And here our goal is to make sure that even a
malicious attacker cannot modify messages in route.
So next we want to define what it means
for a MAC system to be secure.
So as usual, we define security in terms of the
attacker's power. What can the attacker do?
And the attackers goal. What is he trying
to do? So in the case of MACs, the
attacker's power is what's called a chosen
message attack. In other words, the
attacker can give Alice arbitrary
messages of his choice, m1 to mq,
and Alice will compute the tag for him on
those messages, and give him those tags.
So again, you might wonder, why
would Alice ever do that?
Why would Alice ever compute the tag on a
message that the attacker gave her?
So just like in the case of chosen plaintext
attack, it's very common in the real world,
that the attacker can give Alice a message.
Alice will compute the tag on that message,
and then the attacker will obtain the resulting tag.
For example, the attacker might send Alice an email.
Alice might want to save the email to
disk in a way that will prevent someone
from tampering with the disk. So she'll
compute a tag on the message,
and save the message and the tag to disk.
Later on, the attacker might steal Alice's disk.
And now he's recovered Alice's tag on the
message that he sends to Alice.
So this is an example of a chosen message
attack in the real world, where the attacker
actually obtained a tag on a
message that he gave Alice.
Okay, so that's what the attacker can do,
basically, this chosen message attack.
And what is his goal? Well, his goal is to do
something called an existential forgery.
What he's trying to do is to produce some,
some new valid message tag there.
Okay, so some message tag pair
that's different from one of the
pairs that were given to him during
the chosen message attack.
And if he can do that, then we say that
the system is insecure, and if he can't,
then we'll say the system is secure.
So I wanna emphasize this existential
forgery means that the attacker cannot
produce a new message/tag pair,
even for a message that's completely gibberish.
And again, you might wonder, well,
why do we care if the attacker computes
a tag on a message that's gibberish?
That's not of any value to the attacker.
But we want to build MACs that are
secure under any usage settings.
And there are, in fact cases where, for example,
you might want to compute an integrity tag on
a random secret key. In which case, even if the
attacker is able to compute a tag on a completely
random message, he might be able to fool
a user into using the wrong secret key.
And as a result we want to make sure that
if the MAC is secure, the attacker can't
produce a valid tag for any message
whether it's gibberish or sensical.
Another property that's implied by the security
definition is if the attacker is given some
message tag pair he shouldn't be able to
produce a new tag for the same message.
In other words even though there might be
another tag t´ for the same message m,
the attacker given m and t shouldn't be able
to find this new t´ and again you
might wonder well why do we care the
attacker already has a tag on message M.
Why does it matter if he can produce
another tag for the message M he already
has one tag. But as we'll see, there are
actually applications where it's really important
that the attacker not to be able to produce
a new tag for a previously signed message.
In particular, this will come up when we
combine encryption and integrity.
So that we are gonna demand that given
one tag in the message it's impossible
to find another tag for the same message.
Okay, so now that we understand the
intuition of what we are trying to achieve, let's
define it as usual using a more precise game.
So here we have two algorithms S and V,
and we have an adversary A,
and the game proceeds as follows.
The challenger as usual just chooses
a random key for the MAC and the adversary
basically does his chosen message attack.
So he submits an m1 to the challenger
and receives the tag on that message m1.
Then he submits an m2 to the challenger
and receives a tag on that m2.
And so on and so forth, until, you know,
he submits Q messages to the adversary and
receives Q tags on all those messages. So
that's the chosen message attack part.
And then the adversary goes ahead and
tries to do an existential forgery.
Namely, he outputs a message tag pair,
a new message tag pair.
We say that he wins the game, in other words
b is equal to 1 means that he wins the game if,
first of all, the message tag pair that he
outputs is a valid message tag pair,
so the verification algorithm says yes.
And second of all, it's a fresh message tag pair.
In other words, it's not one of the message
tag pairs that we gave him before.
In other words we say that the attacker lost
the game. Namely b is equal to zero.
And as usual we say, we define the advantage
of an adversary as the probability that
the challenger outputs one in this game.
We say that the MAC system is secure
if for all efficient adversaries the advantage
is negligible. Okay, in other words,
no efficient adversary can win this
game with non negligible probability.
Alright, that's our definition of secure MACs,
and our goal is to build secure MACs like this.
Before we do that, I wanna ask you two questions.
So the first question is, suppose we have a MAC.
And it so happens that the attacker can
find two message, m0 and m1,
that happen to have the same tag
for about half of the keys.
In other words, if you choose a key at
random with probability one half, the tag
of the message m0 will be the same as the
tag of the message m1. And my question to
you is can this be a secure MAC. So I want
to emphasize the attacker doesn't know
what the tag on m0 and m1 is. All he knows
is that the two messages happen to have
the same tag with probability one half. So
the question is whether this is a secure MAC.
So the answer is no, this is not a secure
MAC and the reason is because of
the chosen message attack. Essentially the
attacker can ask for the tag on the message
m0, then he will receive m0, T from the
challenger and in fact T would be a valid
tag for message m0 and then what he would
output as his existential forgery is m1, T
and you notice that m1, T is different from
m0, T, so this is a valid existential forgery.
And as a result, the attacker wins
the game with advantage one-half.
So we conclude that this MAC is not secure.
The second question I'd like to ask you, is,
suppose we have a MAC that happens
to always output a five bit tag.
In other words, the tag space for this Mac
happens to be  to the five.
So for every key and for every message, the
signing algorithm will just output a five bit tag.
And the question is, can this MAC be secure?
Of course the answer is no, because the
attacker can simply guess the tag.
So what he would do is he wouldn't
ask any chosen message attacks.
All he would do, is he would output
an existential forgery as follows.
He would just choose a random tag. So
choose a random tag t at random in ^5,
and then he would just output his existential
forgery as say, the message zero and the tag t.
And now with probability of 1/2^5, this
tag will be a valid tag for the message zero.
And so the adversary's advantage is
1/32, which is non-negligible.
So this basically says that tags
can't be too short.
They have to have some length to them.
And in fact, the typical tag length would be,
say 64 bits. or 96 bits, or 128 bits. Here let's
for example use the tags that are 96 bits long.
If you try to guess the tag for a message
when the tag is 96 bits the probability of
guessing it correctly is 1/2^96.
So the adversary's advantage would
just be 1/2^96 which is negligible.
So now that we understand what MACs are,
I wanna show you a simple application.
In particular, let's see how MACs can be
used to protect system files on disk.
So imagine that when you install an operating
system, say, when you install Windows on
your machine. One of the things that,
Windows does, is it asks the user for a
password, and then derives a key K from
this password. And then for every file
that it writes to disk, in this case, the
files would be F1, F2, up to Fn, what the
operating system would do is it
would compute a tag for that file,
and then store the tag along with the file. So here
it concatenates the tag, to each one of the files.
And then it erases the key K.
So it no longer stores the key K on disc,
or on memory, or anywhere. Okay, so now
later imagine that the machine gets
infected with a virus and the virus tries
to modify some of the system files.
The question is whether the user can
detect which files were modified.
So here's one way to do it. Basically, the user
would reboot the machine into some clean OS.
Say you reboot from a USB disk or something.
And then, once the machine boots from this
clean OS, the user would supply his password
to this clean running operating system.
And then this new clean running operating
system would go ahead and check the MAC for
each one of the system files. Now, the
fact that the MAC is secure, means that
the poor virus couldn't actually create a
new file, let's call it F prime, with a valid tag.
So it couldn't actually create an
f´, t´. Because, if it could,
then that would be an existential forgery
on this MAC. And because, well,
the MAC is existentially unforgeable. The
virus couldn't create any F Prime, no
matter what the F Prime is. And
consequently, because of the security of
the MAC, the user will detect all the
files that were modified by the virus.
Now, there's one caveat to that. One thing
that the virus can do. Is actually swap
two files. So, for example, he can swap
this file, file F1, with the file F2 here,
just literally swap them. So when the
system, or when the user, tries to run
file F1, instead they'll be running file
F2. And of course that could cause all
sorts of damage. And so the way to defend
against that is essentially by placing the
file name inside of the MACed area, so in
fact we're computing an integrity check on
the file name as well as on the contents
of the file. And as a result, if the virus
tries to swap two files, the system will
say hey, the file that's located in
position F1 doesn't have the right name
and therefore it will detect that the virus
that did the swap even though the MAC
actually verifies. So it is important to
remember that MACs can help you defend
against file tampering. Or data tampering
in general. But they won't help you defend
against swapping of authenticated data,
and that has to be done by some other
means. Okay, so that concludes our
introduction to MACs, and in the next
segment, we'll go ahead and construct our
first examples of secure MACs.