In the last two segments we talked about
the CBC-MAC and NMAC to convert a PRF for
small messages into a PRF for much larger
messages. Those two constructions were
sequential, in the sense that if you had
multiple processors you couldn't make the
construction work any faster. In this
segment we're gonna look at a parallel MAC
that also converts a small PRF into a
large PRF, but does it in a very
parallelizable fashion. In particular we're
gonna look at a parallel MAC construction
called PMAC, that uses an underlying PRF
to construct a PRF for much larger
messages. In particular, the PRF can
process much longer messages that can have
variable length and have as many as L
blocks in them. Now the construction works
as follows. We take our message and we
break it into blocks. And then we process
each block independently of the other. So,
the first thing we do, is we evaluate some
function P and we XOR the result
into the first message block, and then we
apply our function F using a key k1.
We do the same for each one of the
message blocks and you notice that we can
do it all parallel, all message blocks are
processed independently of one another.
And we collect all these results into some
final XOR and then we encrypt one more time
to get the final tag value. Now for a
technical reason, actually on the very
last one. We actually don't need to apply
the PRF F, but as I said, this is just
for technical reason, and I'm going to
ignore that for now. Now, I want to
explain what the function P is for and
what it does. So imagine, just for a
second, that the function P isn't actually
there. That is, imagine we actually,
directly feed each message block into the
PRF without applying any other
processing to it. Then I claim that the
resulting MAC is completely insecure and
the reason is essentially no order is
enforced between the message blocks. In
particular, if I swap two message blocks,
that doesn't change the value of the final
tag. Because the XOR is commutative, the
tag will be the same whether we swap the
blocks or not. As a result, an attacker
can request the tag for a particular
message, and then he obtains the tag for a
message where two of the blocks are
swapped and that counts as an existential
forgery. So what this function P tries to
do is essentially enforce order on these
blocks. And you notice that the function
takes, first of all, it's a heed function,
so it takes a key as input. And second of
all, more importantly, it takes the block
number as input. In other words, the
value of the function is different for
each one of the blocks. And that's
actually exactly what's preventing this,
blocks swapping attack. So the function P
actually, is a very easy to compute
function. Essentially given the key and
the message block, all it is, is just a
multiplication in some finite fields. So
it's a very, very simple function to
compute. It adds very little to the
running time of PMAC. And yet, it's
enough in ensure that the PMAC is
actually secure. As we've said, the key
for PMAC is this pair of keys. One key for
the PRF, and one key for this masking
function P. And finally, I'll tell you
that if the message length is not a
multiple of the block length. That is,
imagine the last block is shorter than
full block length, then PMAC actually uses
a padding that's similar to CMAC, so that
there is no need for an additional dummy
block, ever. So that's the PMAC
construction and as usual, we can state
its security theorem. So the security
theorem, by now, you should be used to it.
Essentially, it says that if you give me
an adversary attacking PMAC, I can
construct an adversary attacking the
underlying PRF. Plus an additional error
term. And so, since again, the PRF is
secure, we know that this term is
negligible. And so if we want this term to
be negligible, we know that, we need this
error term to also be negligible. Here, as
usual, q is the number of messages that
are MAC-ed using a particular key. And L
is the maximum length of all those
messages. And PMAC is secure, as long as
its product is less than the square root
of the block size. So for A, yes, this would be
two to the 128, and the square root,
therefore, would be two to the 64th. So the
MAC would be secure, as long as Q times L
is less than two to the 64th. And every time,
as it gets closer to that value, of
course, you would have to change the key
in order to continue MAC-ing more
messages. So the main thing to remember is
that PMAC also gives us a PRF, and when it
processes the message blocks independently
of one another. Turns out that PMAC also
has a very interesting property. Namely,
that PMAC math is incremental. So let me
explain to you what that means. So suppose
the function F that's used to construct PMAC
is not just a PRF, but, in fact, a
permutation, PRP. So we can actually
invert it when we need to. Now suppose
we've already computed the MAC for a
particularly long message m. And now,
suppose just one message block of this
long message changes. So here, m[1] has
changed into m'[1]. But the
remaining message blocks all remain the
same. For other MAC-s, like CBC-MAC, even
though only one message block changed, you
would have to recompute the tag on the
entire message. Recomputing the tag
basically will take time that's
proportional to the length of the message.
It turns out, with PMAC, if we only
change one block, or a small number of
blocks, actually, we can recompute the
value of the tag for the new message very,
very quickly. And let me ask you a puzzle
to see if you can figure out how to do
that yourself. And remember, the function
F is a PRP, and therefore is invertible.
So let's see if you can figure out how to
compute the MAC in the new message by
yourself. So it turns out this can be
done. And you can quickly recompute the
tag on the new message using this third
line here. Just to make sure we all see
the solution let's quickly go back to the
original diagram for PMAC and I can show
you what I mean. So imagine this one
message block changed into some other
block, say, it changed into M'[1]. Then
what we could do is we can take the tag on
the original message before the change was
made. So we can invert the function F, and
determine the value before the function F
was applied. Now, well, since we now have
an XOR of a bunch of blocks, what
we can do is we can cancel out the XOR
that came from the original message block,
basically by XOR-ing this value that came
from the original message block into this
XOR-ed accumulator. And then XOR-ing again
the value that would come from the new
message block back into the XOR
accumulator. And then apply the function F
again. And that will give us the tag for
the new message, where just one block was
changed. So in symbols, basically, I wrote
the formula over here. You can see,
basically, we decrypt the tag, and then we
XOR with the block that comes from the
original message block. We XOR again with
the block that comes from the new message
block. And then we re-encrypt the final
XOR accumulator to get the new tag for the
message with a one block changed. So
that's kind of a neat property. It kind of
shows that if you have very large
messages, you can very quickly update the
tag. Of course you would need the secret
key to do the update, but you can quickly
update the tag if just a small number of
message blocks changed. Okay, so that
concludes our discussion of PMAC. And now
I wanna switch topics a little bit, and
talk about the concept of a one time MAC,
which is basically the analog of the one
time pad, but in the world of integrity.
So let me explain what I mean by that. So
imagine we wanna build a MAC that is only
used for integrity of a single message. In
other words, every time we compute the
integrity of a particular message, we also
change the key. So that any particular key
is used only for integrity of one message.
Then we can define the security game as
basically saying, the attacker's gonna see
one message. Therefore, we only allow him
to do one chosen message attack. So he
gets to submit one message query, and he
is given the tag corresponding to that one
message query. And now his goal is to
forge a message tag pair. Okay, so you
can see his goal was to produce one
message tag pair that verifies correctly and
is different from the pair that he was
actually given. As we'll see, just like
the one time pad and stream ciphers were
quite useful, it turns out one time MAC-s
are also quite useful for the same
applications when we only wanna use a key
to encrypt or to provide integrity for
just a single message. So as usual we
would say that a one time act is secure,
because basically no adversary can win
this game. Now the interesting thing is
that one time MAC-s, just like the one time
pad can be secure against infinitely
powerful adversaries. And not only that,
because they're only designed to be secure
for one time use, they can actually be
faster than MAC-s that are based on PRFs.
And so I just wanted to give you a quick
example of one one time MAC, this is a
classic construction for a one time MAC,
let me show you how it works. The first
step is to pick a prime that's slightly
larger than our block size. In this case
we're going to use 128-bit blocks, so
let's pick the first prime that's bigger
than two to the 128th. This happens to be
two to the 128th plus 51. And now the key
is going to be a pair of random numbers in
the range 1 to our prime, so 1 to q. So we
choose two random integers in the range 1
to q. Now we're given a message so we're
going to take our message and break it
into blocks where each block is 128 bits,
and we're going to regard each number as
an integer in the range 0 to 2 to the
128th minus 1. Now the MAC is defined as
follows. The first thing we do is we take
our message blocks and we kind of
construct the polynomial out of them. So
if there are L blocks in our message,
we're going to construct the polynomial of
degree L and you notice that the constant
term of the polynomial is set to zero. And
then we define the MAC very simply.
Basically what we do is we take the
polynomial that corresponds to the
message, we evaluate it at the point K
that's one half of our secret key, and
then we add the value A which is the
second half of our secret key. And that's
it. That's the whole MAC. So just
basically construct the polynomial that
corresponds to our message, evaluate that
polynomial at half of the secret key, and
add the other half of the secret key to
the result, and of course reduce final
result modulo q. Okay so that's it, so
the whole MAC, it's a one time secure MAC
and we will argue that this MAC is one
time secure, essentially by arguing that
if I tell you the value of MAC for one
particular message, that tells you nothing
at all about the value of the MAC at
another message. And as a result, even
though you've seen the value of the MAC on
a particular message, you have no way of
forging this MAC on some other message.
Now I should emphasize that this is a one
time MAC, but it's not two time secure. In
other words, if you get to see the value
of the MAC on two different messages, that
actually completely compromises the
secret key. And you can actually predict a MAC
for a third or fourth message of your
choice. So then the MAC becomes forgeable.
But for one time use, it is a perfectly
secure MAC, and I'll tell you that in fact
it's a very fast MAC to evaluate. So now
that we've constructed one time MAC-s,
turns out there's actually a general
technique that will convert one time MAC-s
into many time MAC-s. And I just wanted to
briefly show you how that works. So
suppose we have our one time MAC, let's
call it S and V for signing and
verification algorithms, and let's just
assume that the tags themselves are n bit
strings. In addition, let's also look at a
PRF, a secure PRF, that also happens to
output n bit strings but also takes as
inputs n bit strings. So let's now define
a general construction for a MAC. These
MAC-s are called Carter-Wegman MAC-s that
works as follows. Basically what we would
do is we would apply the one time MAC to
the message M and then we're going to
encrypt the results using the PRF. So how do
we encrypt the result? Well, we choose a
random r and then we compute kind of a
one time path from this r by applying the
PRF to it. And then we XOR the result
with the actual one time MAC. So the neat
thing about this construction is that the
fast one time MAC is applied to the long
message, which could be gigabytes long.
And the slower PRF is only applied to this
nonce r, which is then used to
encrypt the final results of the MAC. And
you can argue that if the MAC that was
given to us as a building block is a one
time secure MAC, and the PRF is secure,
then, in fact, we get a many time secure
MAC that happens to output 2n bit tags.
So we're gonna see Carter-Wegman MAC-s later
on when we talk about authenticated
encryption. And, in fact, one of the NIST standard
methods for doing encryption with
integrity, uses a Carter-Wegman MAC for
providing integrity. I want to mention
that this Carter-Wegman MAC is a good
example of a randomized MAC where this nonce
r is chosen afresh every time the tag is
computed. And so for example if you try to
compute a tag for the same message twice
each time you'll choose a different r and
as a result you'll get different tags both
times. And so this is a nice example of a
MAC that's actually not a pseudo random
function, not a PRF, because a single
message could actually be mapped to many
different tags all of which are valid for
that one message. To conclude our
discussion on the Carter-Wegman MAC, let me
ask you the following question. Here we
have the equation for the Carter-Wegman
MAC. As usual, you see the nonce r as
part of the MAC. And the second part of
the MAC I'm gonna denote by t. This is
basically the one time MAC applied to the
message M, and then encrypted using the
pseudo-random function applied to the
nonce r. So we'll denote the result of
this XOR by t. So my question to
you is, given the Carter-Wegman MAC pair r,t
for particular message m, how
would you verify that this MAC is valid?
And recall that its algorithm V here, is
the verification algorithm for the
underlying one time MAC. So this is the
right answer, and to see why, just observe
that this XOR here decrypts the quantity t
to its plain text value, which is
basically the original underlying one time
MAC. And so we can directly feed that into
the verification algorithm for the one
time MAC. The last type of MAC I wanted
to tell you about is one that is very
popular in internet protocols. It's called the HMAC. But before we talk about the HMAC we
have to talk about hash functions and in particular, collision resistant hash
functions and we are going to do that in
the next module. So this is the end of our
first module on MAC-s and I wanted to point
out that there's beautiful theory that
went into constructing all the MAC-s that
we saw. I gave you the highlights showed
you the main constructions, but
there's really quite a bit of theory that
goes into constructing these MAC-s, and if
you'd like to learn more about that, I
listed a couple of key papers you might
want to look at. Let me quickly tell you what they
are. The first one is, what's called the
three key construction, which is the basis
of CMAC. A very elegant paper that give a
very efficient construction out of CBC-MAC.
The second paper is a more technical
paper, but basically shows how to prove
that bounds of CBC-MAC as a PRF. The
third paper talks about PMAC and its
construction. Again, a very acute paper.
The fourth paper talks about security of
NMAC and HMAC as well. HMAC we're going to
cover in, the next module. The last paper
I listed asks an intriguing question.
Recall that all of our constructions, we
always assume that AES is a pseudo-random
function for sixteen byte messages and we
then built a pseudo-random function and
therefore a MAC for much longer messages.
This paper says well, what do we do if AES
is not a pseudo-random function, but still
satisfies some weaker security property
called an unpredictable function. And then
they ask if AES is only an unpredictable
function, but not a pseudo-random
function, can we still build MAC-s for long
messages? And so they succeed in actually
giving constructions just based on the
weaker assumption that AES is an
unpredictable function. But their
constructions are far less sufficient than
CBC-MAC or NMAC, or PMAC that we discussed
in these segments. And so if you're
interested in a different perspective on
how to build MAC-s from block ciphers like
AES, please take a look at this paper. And
there are actually some nice open
questions to work on in this area. So this
concludes our first segment on integrity.
And in the next segment, we're gonna talk
about collision resistance.