Now that we know how two users can protect
data using a shared secret key, the next
question is how did these two users
generate a shared secret key to begin
with? This question will take us into the
world of public key cryptography. In this
module, we will look at a few toy key
exchange protocols as a way to introduce
the main ideas of public key cryptography.
We're gonna come back and talk about key
exchange and design secure key exchange
protocols after we build a few more public
key tools. So imagine for a second that
there a N users in the world. And the
question is, how do these users manage
these secret keys that they're gonna use
to communicate with one another? So, for
example, let's assume N equals four and
there are four users in the world. One
option is that basically every pair of
users will share a shared secret key. And
so, for example, U1 and U3 will share a
shared, a shared secret key. I'll call it
K13. U1 and U2 will share a, a shared
secret key. We'll call it K12 so on and so
forth. K24 K34 and so on and so forth. K14
and finally K23. The problem with this
approach is that now there are many, many
shared keys that users have to manage. And
in particular, every user has to store on
the order of N keys if he's gonna talk to
N other parties in this world. So the
question is can we do any better than
storing N keys per user? And the answer is
yes. And one way to do that is what's
called an online trusted third party. I'll
use TTP to denote that trusted third
party. So the way we are going to use the
trusted third party is every user will now
share a single key with this trusted third
party. So user one will share a secret
key, user two will share a secret key. And
here are our friends Alice and Bob, let's
call their secret keys k sub A and k sub B.
Okay, so now the nice thing about
this design is that now every user only
has to remember one secret key. The
question is now, what happens when Alice
wants to talk to Bob? Somehow the two of
them have to engage in a certain protocol,
such that at the end of this protocol they
will have a shared secret key KAB that the
attacker wouldn't be able to know. And so
the question is how do Alice and Bob
generate this shared secret key KAB. So
let's look at an example toy protocol for
doing that. So here we have our friends
Alice and Bob. As usual Bob has his key
KB, which is shared with a trusted third
party. Alice has her secret key KA,
which is also shared with a trusted third
party. So here the trusted third party
has both KA and KB. And the question is,
how do they generate a shared key that
they both agree on, but the attacker would
have no idea what this shared key is? So
here we're only gonna look at a toy
protocol. In particular, this protocol is
only gonna to be secure against
eavesdropping. It's not gonna be secure
against more tampering or active attacks.
As I said, we're gonna come back and
design secure key exchange protocols later
on in the course. But for now, just to
introduce this idea of key exchange, let's
look at the simplest, simplest mechanism
that's only secure against eavesdropping.
So in other words, adversary that listens
to the conversation won't know what
the shared key KAB is gonna be. And so the
protocol works as follows. Alice is going
to start by sending a message to the
trusted third party saying, hey I want a
secret key that's going to be shared with
Bob. What the trusted third party will do
is it will actually go ahead and choose a
random secret key, KAB. So the trusted
third party is the one who's gonna
generate their shared secret key. And what
it will do with this key is the following.
It's gonna send one message back to
Alice. But this message consists of, of
two parts. The first part of the message
is an encryption using Alice's secret key,
using the key KA, of the message this key
is supposed to be used between parties
Alice and Bob, and she includes the secret
key KAB inside the message. Okay? So just
to be clear, what's happening here is that
the message that gets encrypted is the key
KAB plus the fact that this key is
supposed to be a shared key between Alice
and Bob. Okay. And this whole message is
encrypted using Alice's secret key. The
other part of the message that the TTP
sends to Alice is what's called a ticket.
And this ticket is basically a message
that's encrypted for Bob. So in other
words, the ticket is gonna be an
encryption under the key KB of, again, the
fact that this key is supposed to be used
between Alice and Bob. And she
concatenates to that the, the secret key,
KAB. Okay, so again, the message that's
encrypted inside of the ticket is the fact
that this key is to be used by Alice and
Bob. And, the secret key, KAB, is included
in the ticket as well. Okay, So these two
messages, Here, let me circle them. These
two messages are sent from the trusted
third party to Alice. Now I should mention
that the encryption system E that is
actually being used here is a CPA secure
cipher and we'll see why that's needed in
just a minute. So, this is the end of the
conversation between Alice and this
trusted third party. Basically as we
said at the end of this conversation,
Alice receives one message that's
encrypted for her and another message
called a ticket that's encrypted for Bob.
Now at a later time when Alice wants to
communicate securely with Bob what she
will do, is of course, she will decrypt
her part of the message. In other words
she will decrypt the cipher text that was
encrypted using the key KA and now she has
the key KAB. And then to Bob, she's going
to send over this ticket. Bob is going
to receive the ticket and he is going to
use his own secret key KB to decrypt it and
then he himself will also recover the
secret key KAB. So now they have the
shared secret key KAB that they can use
to communicate securely with one another.
And the first question to ask is, Why is
this protocol secure? Even if we only
consider eavesdropping adversaries. So,
let's think about that for a minute. So,
at the moment all we care about is just
security against an eavesdropper, So let's
think. What does an eavesdropper see in
this protocol. Well basically he sees
these two cipher texts. Right, he sees the
cipher text that's encrypted for Alice.
And then he sees the ticket that's
encrypted for Bob. And in fact he might
see many instances of these messages, in
particular if Alice and Bob continuously
exchange keys in this way he's gonna see
many messages of this type and our goal is
to say that he has no information about
the exchanged key KAB. So this follows
directly from the CPA security of the
cipher E D because the eavesdropper can't
really distinguish between encryptions of
the secret key KAB from encryption of just
random junk. That's the definition of CPA
security and as a result, he can't
distinguish the key KAB from, you know,
random junk which means that he learns
nothing about KAB. This is kind of a very
high level argument for why this is
eavesdropping security but it's enough for
our purposes here. So the bottom line is
that in this protocol the eavesdropper
would actually have no information about
what KAB is. And therefore it's okay to
use KAB as secret key to exchange messages
between Alice and Bob. Now let's think
about the TTP for a minute. So first of
all, you notice that the TTP is needed for
every single key exchange. So basically
Alice and Bob simply cannot do key change
unless the TTP is online and available to
help them do that. And the other property
of this protocol is in fact, the TTP knows
all the session keys. So if somehow the
TTP is corrupt, or maybe it's broken into,
then an attacker can very easily steal all
the secret keys that have been exchanged
between every user of this system. This is
why this TTP is called the Trusted Third
Party because, essentially, it knows all
the session keys that have been generated
in the system. Nevertheless the beauty of
this mechanism is that it only uses
symmetric key cryptography, nothing beyond
what we've already seen and as a result it is
very fast and efficient. The only issue is
that you have to use this online trusted
party and it's not immediately clear if for
example we wanted to use this in the
world wide web who would function as this
online trusted third party. However, in a
corporate setting this might actually make
sense if you have a single company with a
single point of trust it might make sense
to actually designate a machine as a
trusted third party. And in fact a
mechanism like this not quite as the way I
described it, but a mechanism like this is
the basis of the Kerberos system. So
this is our first example of a key
exchange protocol that allowed Alice and
Bob to set up shared keys, however I
really want to point out that this is just
a toy protocol. Very, very simple and is
only secure against eavesdropping
attack. It's actually completely insecure
against an active attacker. And here's a
very simple example of how an active
attacker might destroy this protocol, and
so let's just look at replay attacks. So
here imagine the attacker records the
conversation between Alice and some online
merchant. Let's call him Merchant Bob. So
for example, imagine Alice orders a book
from the merchant Bob and the transaction
completes and Bob accepts payment for this
book. And actually sends Alice a copy
of this book. What an attacker can do now
is, he can complete, completely record the
conversation and simply replay the
conversation to merchant Bob at a later
time. Bob will think that Alice just
reordered another, another copy of the
book and he'll charge her again for it,
and send her this, this copy again. So
essentially by replaying a conversation
you can cause quite a bit of harm to
Alice, and as a result this is a simple
example of why this protocol is completely
insecure against active attacks, and
should never be used in the real world. As
I said we're going to come back in a few weeks
and talk about secure versions of this
protocol, and you'll see how to make this
work, in the real world. Nevertheless, you
see that this, this very simple protocol
already raises a very interesting
question. And the question is, can we
basically design key exchange protocols
whether they're secure against
eavesdropping or secure against active
attackers. The question is, can we design
key exchange protocols that are secure,
but work without an online trusted third
party. So we don't wanna rely on any
online trusted party that's necessary to
complete the key exchange protocol. And so
the amazing answer is that in fact this is
possible. We can do key exchange without a
trusted third party. And this is, in fact,
the starting point of public cryptography.
So I'm gonna show you three ideas for
making this happen and we're gonna talk
about them in much more detail in the, in
the coming modules. So the first idea is
actually due to Ralph Merkle back in 1974.
This was, he was, when he was just an
undergraduate student. And already he came
up with this really nice idea for key
exchange without an online trusted third
party. So that's one example that
we're gonna look at. Another example is
due to Diffie and Hellman. Back in 1976
they both actually, working here at
Stanford University, came up with this idea
that launched the world of modern key
cryptography. And the third idea is due to
Rivest, Shamir and Adleman working at MIT and
we're going to look in detail exactly how
each of these ideas work. But I do want to
mention that the work on public key
management hasn't stopped in the late
seventies. In fact there have been many
ideas over the years and here I'll just
mention two from the last decade. One is
call identity based encryption, which is
another way for managing public keys. And
another is called functional encryption,
which is a way of giving secret keys that
only partially decrypt a given cipher text.
And so we're gonna talk about the core of
public key crypto in this and the next week
and we'll talk about these more advanced
ideas later on in the course.