In this module I wanna show you another
approach to key exchange based on the
concept of public key encryption. So again
just to remind you of the settings, we
have our friends Alice and Bob as usual,
and they're both to exchange a secret key
K. The eavesdropper gets to see the
messages they send to one another, but
even though he shouldn't learn anything
about the key K that, that they exchanged.
And as usual in this module we're only
going to be looking at eavesdropping
security. That is we don't allow the
attacker to tamper with data or to mount
any other form of active attack. So, just
to remind you, earlier in this module we
saw an inefficient mechanism based on
generic block ciphers. In the previous
segment we saw the Diffie-Hellman key
exchange mechanism which has an
exponential gap between the work that the
participants have to do versus the work
that the attacker has to do. And in fact
this Diffie-Hellman protocol is used all
over the web very frequently. In this
segment I want to show you, a different
approach based on public key encryption.
So, what is public encryption? So just as
in the case of symmetric encryption, there's an encryption algorithm and a
decryption algorithm. However, here the
encryption algorithm is given one key,
which we're going to call a public key.
Let's call this the public key that
belongs to Bob. And the decryption algorithm is given a different key, we'll
call it a secret key. That also belongs to
Bob. So these two keys are sometimes
called a key pair. One half of the pair is
the public key and the other half of the
pair is the secret key. Now the way you
encrypt this as usual, a message would
come in, the encryption algorithm would
generate a cipher text, that is the
encryption of this message using the given
public key. And then when the cipher text
is given to the decryption algorithm, the
decryption algorithm basically outputs the
corresponding, message. So, as I said, PK
is called the public key and SK is called
the secret key. So more precisely, what is
public encryption? Well, public encryption
is actually made up of three algorithms,
G, E, and D. Algorithm G is what's called
a key generation algorithm. When you run
algorithm G, it will output two keys, the
public key and the secret key. The
encryption algorithm basically, given the
public key in the message, will output the
corresponding cipher text. And the
decryption algorithm, given the secret key
in the cipher text, will output the
message or it will output bottom if an
error occurred. And as usual we have the
usual consistency properties that say that
for any public key and secret key that
could have been output by the key generation
algorithm if we encrypt the message using
the public key and then decrypt using the
secret key we should get the original
message back. Now, what does it mean for a
public key system to be secure? Well, we
use the same concept of semantic security
that we used before, except the game is now
a little bit different. So let me
explain, how we define semantic security
for a public key system. So here, the
challenger is gonna run the key generation
algorithm to generate a public key and a
secret key pair, and he's gonna give the
public key to the adversary. The
challenger keeps the secret key to
himself. What the adversary will do is he
will output two equal length messages M0 and
M1 as before and then the challenger will
give him the encryption of M0 or M1. As
usual we define two experiments: experiment
zero and experiment one. In experiment
zero the adversary is given the encryption
of M0. In experiment one the adversary is
given the encryption of M1 and then the
adversary's goal is to guess which
encryption he was given. Was he given the
encryption of M0 or was he given
encryption of M1. And we refer to his
guess as the output of experiment zero or
experiment one. One thing I want to
emphasize is that in the case of public
encryption there's no need to give the
attacker the ability to mount a chosen
plaintext attack. Why is that? Well in
the case of a symmetric key system, the
attacker had to request the encryption of
messages of his choice. In the case of a
public key system, the attacker has the
public key and therefore he can by
himself, encrypt for himself any message
that he wants. He doesn't need the
challenger's help to create encryptions of
messages of his choice. And as a result,
in a public key setting, a chosen
plaintext attack is inherent. There's no
reason to give the attacker extra power to
mount a chosen plaintexts attack. And
that's why we never discussed chosen
plaintext queries in the context of
defining semantic security for public key
systems. Now that we defined the game
we're going to say that a public key system
GED is semantically secure if
basically the attacker cannot distinguish
experiment zero from experiment one. In
other words, the adversary's probability
of outputting one in experiment zero is
about the same as his probability of
outputting one in experiment one. So again,
the attacker can't tell whether he was
given the encryption of M0 or the
encryption of M1. Now that we understand
what a public key encryption is let's see
how to use it to establish a shared
secret. See here are our friends Alice and
Bob. Alice will start off by generating a
random public key secret key pair for
herself using the key generation
algorithm. And then she's going to send to
bob the public key PK. And she also says,
hey this message is from Alice. What Bob
will do is he will generate a random 128
bit value X and he will send back to Alice
saying hey this message is from Bob and he
will send back the encryption of X under
Alice's public key. Alice will receive
this cipher text, she will decrypt it
using her secret key and that will give
her the value X and now this value X can
be used basically as a shared secret
between the two of them. I wanna emphasize
that this protocol is very different from
the Diffie-Hellman protocol that we saw in
the last segment in the sense that here
the parties have to take turns, In the
sense that Bob cannot send his message
until he receives the message from Alice.
In other words, Bob cannot encrypt X to
Alice's public key until he receives the
public key from Alice. In the
Diffie-Hellman protocol however the two
parties could send their messages at
arbitrary times and there was no ordering
enforced on those messages. As a result we
had this nice application of
Diffie-Hellman, where, everybody could
post their messages to Facebook, for
example. And then just by looking at
Facebook profiles, any pair would already
have a shared key, without any need for
additional communication. Here, this is
not quite true, even if everybody posts
their public key to Facebook, there would
still be a need to send this message
before a shared key can be established. So
now that we understand protocol the first
question we need to ask is why is this
protocol secure. And as usual we're only
gonna look at eavesdropping security. So
in this protocol the attacker gets to see
the public key and the encryption of X
under the public key and what he wants to
get is basically this value X. Now we know
that the system the public key system that
we used is semantically secure, what that
means is that the attacker cannot
distinguish the encryption of X, From the
encryption of something random. In other
words, just given encryption of X, the
attacker can't tell whether the plain text
is X or just some random junk that was
chosen from M, And because of that, that
basically says that just by looking at
messages in this protocol, the value of X
is indistinguishable in the attacker's
view from a random element in M and as a
result, X can be used as a session key
between the two parties. It's just a
random value which the attacker cannot
actually guess other than by trying all
possible values in M. Then I should say
that showing that these two distributions
are distinguishable follows directly from
semantic security and in fact it's a
simple exercise to show that if the
attacker could distinguish this
distribution from that distribution then
the attacker could also break semantic
security. And as usual even though this
protocol is secure against eavesdropping,
it's completely insecure against the
man-in-the-middle attack. So let's see a
simple man in the middle attack. Well so
here we have Alice generating her public
key secret key pair. At the same time the
man in the middle is also going to
generate his own public key secret key
pair. And now when Alice sends her public
key over to Bob, The man in the middle
will intercept that and instead he'll say
yeah this is a message from Alice, but
Alice's public key is p K prime. So now
Bob receives this message, he thinks he
got a message from Alice, what he'll send
back is, well he's going to choose his
random X, and he'll send back the
encryption of X under PK prime. The man in
the middle is going to intercept this
message, and he's going to replace it with
something else. So, his goal is to make
sure that the key exchange succeeds, in
other words Alice thinks that she got a
message from Bob, and yet the man in the
middle should know exactly what the
exchanged secret is. So what should the man in
the middle send to Alice in this case? So
yeah let's call the cipher text C. What
the man in the middle will do is he will
decrypt the cipher text C using his own
secret key that will reveal X to the man
in the middle. And then he's going to go
ahead and encrypt X under Alice's public
key, send the value back to Alice. Alice
will obtain this X and as far as she's
concerned, she just did a key exchange
with Bob, where both of them learned the
value X, but the problem of course is that
the man in the middle also knows the value
X. So this protocol becomes completely
insecure once the man in the middle can
tamper with messages from Alice to Bob and
from Bob to Alice. So again we have to do something to this protocol to make it secure and
we're gonna see how to do that, actually,
in two weeks after we introduce digital
signatures. So now that I've show you that
public encryption implies key exchange
security against eavesdropping. The next
question is how do we construct public key
encryption systems? And it turns out that
these constructions generally rely on
number theory and some algebra, and just
like the Diffie-Hellman protocol relied on
some algebra. And so before we go into
these protocols in more detail what I'd
like to do is kind of take a quick detour.
In the next module we're going to look at
the relevant number theory background.
We'll just do one module on this and then
come back and talk about these public key
constructions and more constructions for
key exchange. So this is the end of this
module. And as further reading, I just
wanted to point to this paper that shows
if in fact all we do is rely on symmetric
ciphers and hash functions then
Merkle puzzles are optimal for key
exchange and in fact we cannot achieve
more than a quadratic gap as long as we
treat the primitives we're given as a
black box. So basically this shows that a
quadratic gap is the best possible and
also I wanted to point to another paper
that kind of summarizes some of these key
exchange mechanisms that we talked about,
key exchange using public key cryptography
and key exchange using Diffie-Hellman. You
can take a look at this paper and it kind
of will give you a look ahead into what's
coming and how to make these key exchange
protocols secure against man in the middle
and not just secure against eavesdropping.
Okay so that's the end of this module and
in the next module we'll take a brief
detour and do a kind of a brief overview
of algebra and number theory.