In the last module we saw that number
theory can be useful for key exchange.
In this modlule we will review some basic facts
of number theory that will help us build
many public key systems next week. As we
go through the material in this module it
might help to pause the video from time to
time to make sure all the examples are clear
So as I said we're gonna use number
theory to build key exchange protocols.
We're gonna use number theory to build
digital signatures, public encryption and many, many other things.
But before we can
do all that, we have to review some basic
facts from number theory and in fact in
this module we're gonna do a quick course
on the relevant concept. If you'd like to
review some of the material discussed in
this module offline, I referenced at the
end of the module a free textbook by
Victor Shoup and I pointed to some
specific chapters in his book that will
explain the materials that we will cover
here. So from here on I'm going to use the
following notation. I'm going to use
capital N to always denote a positive
integer, and I'm going to use lower case p
to always denote a positive prime number.
Now I'd like to introduce the following
notation, there's this funny Z that's
written like two diagonal lines here with
a subscript N I'm gonna use that to denote
the sets as zero, one, two, up to N minus
one. This is actually a very common
notation that's used in Crypto, and so
I'll stick to that here. So again, Z sub N
denotes the set of integers 0,1 up to N-1. And in fact, this is not just a
set of integers. We can do addition and
multiplication in this set as long as we
always multiply module of the number N.
For those of you who know a little bit of
algebra, I'll just say that Z sub N
denotes a ring where addition and
multiplication are done modulo N. This is
very common notation in crypto, although
in modern mathematics Z sub N sometimes
denotes something else. But as I said I'm
gonna keep on using Z sub N to denote the
set of integers 0 to N-1 with
addition and multiplication modulo N. So
I want to make sure everybody's
comfortable with modular arithmetic. And
so let's just look at the number, say, N=12
And let's just see some basic facts about modular arithmetic. So
I'm gonna say that nine plus eight is
seventeen; seventeen is five modulo
twelve, so I'm gonna write that nine plus
eight is equal to five in Z 12. Now
can someone tell me how much is five times
seven in Z12? In other words, how much is modular 12?
Well, five times seven is 35. And if you recall, 36 is divisible by 12
So five times seven is really -1 module of 12. 35 is minus
one module of twelve. But minus one module
of 12 is basically the same as 11,
cuz I just add 12  to -1 and I
get 11. And the next question is, how
much is 5 - 7 seven in the Z12?
Well, 5-7 is -2.
-2 modulo 12, well, I just add 12
to -2 and I get 10. As a result,
we say that 5 - 7 is equal to
10. So again, this is just to make sure
everybody is comfortable with this notation of working
in Z12. In other words, working in modulo 12.
Now, I'd just like to make a
general statement that, in fact,
arithmetic in ZN, in other words,
arithmetic modulo N works just as you
would expect. So, for example, all the
laws that you know about addition and
multiplication work equally well in ZN.
For example, the distributive law, X times
Y plus Z, is still gonna be equal to X
times Y plus X times Z. So many of the
things that you know about arithmetic when
working over the integers or in the reals,
will translate to working in, ZN, namely
working modulo N.
So the next concept we need is what's called a greatest common
divisor, or a GCD. And so suppose they
give you two integers X and Y. We say that
the GCD of X and Y is basically the
greatest common divisor it's the largest
number, the largest integer that divides
both X and Y. So for example, what is the
GCD of 12 and 18?
Well the GCD is 6, because 6 divides both 12
and 18,
and it's the largest number that divides both 12 and 18.
Now
there is an important fact about GCD's in particular, if I give you two numbers, two
integers X and Y, there will always exist
two other integers, I will call them A and
B, such that if I look at a times X + B
times Y what I get is the GCD of X and Y.
In other words the GCD of X and Y is a
linear combination of X and Y using the
integers A and B. So far let us look at a
simple example, here, let's look at the
GCD from before, so the integers for the
GCD would be 2 times 12 Minus 1
times 18. That's 24 minus 18,
which is equal to 6. So the integers A
and B in this case would be 2 and -1
But this is just an example, and in
fact, these integers, A and B will exist
for any integers, X and Y. Now not only do
A and B exist, in fact there's a very
simple and efficient algorithm to find
these integers, to find A and B. The
algorithm is what's called the extended
Euclidean algorithm. This is actually one
of the prettiest algorithms from ancient
Greek times, due to Euclid of course. I'm
not gonna show you how this algorithm
works here, I. It's a fairly simple
algorithm. I'll just tell that in fact
given X and Y, this algorithm will find A
and B in time roughly quadratic in the
logarithms of X and Y. We'll come back to
that and discuss the, the performance of
Euclid's algorithm I have a bit more
detail in just a minute. But, for now all
we need to know is that A and B can
actually be found efficiently. Now, if the
GCD of X and Y happens to be 1. In other
words, 1 is the largest integer that
divides both X and Y, then we say that X
and Y are relatively prime. For example,
the GCD of three and five, it's not
difficult to see that it hap, that happens
to be 1, Because both 3 and 5 are
prime. The next topic we need to talk
about is modulated inversion. So other
than rationals we know what the inverse of
a number is. In other words if I give you
the number 2 the inverse of 2 is
simply the fraction one half.
the qestion is what about inverses when we, we
work module N. Well, so the inverse of
an element X in Z N is simply another
element Y in Z N such that X times Y is
equal to 1 in Z N. In other words X
times Y is equal to 1 modulo N. And this
number Y is denoted by X inverse. And it's
not difficult to see that if, if Y exists,
then in fact it's unique. And as I said,
we'll use X inverse to denote the inverse
of X. So let's look at a quick example.
Suppose N is some odd integer, and I ask
you what is the inverse of 2 in ZN?
So it's not too difficult to see that the
inverse of two in ZN in fact is N plus one
over 2 and you can see that this is an
integer because N is odd, therefore, N+1 is even and, therefore, (N+1)/2
is in fact an integer and the
range 1..N as required. Now why is (N+1)/2
the inverse of two?
Well, let's just multiply the 2 so we do
2 times (N+1) over 2 and what do
we get? Well, that's simply equal to N+1
and N+1 is simply equal to
1 in ZN. So since their product is equal
to 1. We know that (N+1)/2
is the inverse of 2 in ZN.
Now we understand what a modular inverse is, the
question is which elements actually have
an inverse in ZN? And so there's a very
simple lemma that says that if for an
element X in ZN, that element has
an inverse if and only if it is relatively
prime to the modulus N, to the number N.
So I'll say that again. X and ZN is
invertible if and only if X is relatively
prime to N. And let's quickly prove that.
It's actually fairly simple to see. So
suppose a GCD of X and N happens to be
equal to one. So X is relatively prime to
N. Well, by this property of GCD as we
know that there exists integers A and B.
Such that A times X plus B times N is
equal to the GCD of X and N, which happens
to be one. So A times X plus B times N is
equal to 1. Now we can actually take
this equation here and, and us it reduce
it's modulo N. So what this means is that
a times X is equal to one in Z, N. Once we
reduce this equation modulo N this term
simply falls off because B times N is
divisible by N and therefore is 0
modulo N. But what we just showed is that
in fact X inverse is simply A in ZN. So
because X is relatively prime to N, we
were able to show that X is invertible by
actually building the inverse of X modulo N
Now what about the other direction?
What happens if the GCD is greater than 1?
Then we want to show that there is no
inverse. But that's actually very easy to
see because in this case, if you claim
that A happens to be the inverse of X
modulo N, well, let's look at ax; aX we know should be equal to 1 modulo N
But if the GCD(X,N) is
bigger than 1, then the GCD(aX,N)
is bigger than one. But, if the GCD
of A times X and N is bigger than 1,
then it's not possible that AX is
equal to 1. So AX must also be
bigger than 1, and therefore, A cannot
be the inverse of X module N.
So this proves that, in fact, in, when the GCD is
greater than 1, X cannot have an
inverse, because there is no A, such that
A times X is equal to one modulo N
And this might be a bit confusing, so you
might be best just to, do an example. So
let's look at, let's suppose that the GCD
of X and N happens to be equal to 2.
I claim that X is therefore, is not
invertible modular N. Well, why is that
true? Well, for all A, we know that A
times X is gonna be even, is even. And the
reason we know that is because, well, 2
divides X and 2 divides N. Well, since
two divide X, 2 is also gonna divide A
times X. And therefore, A times X must be
even. But what that means is that there's
no way that A times X is equal to 1 modulo N
In particular, there's no way
that A times X is equal to B times N + 1
This simply can't happen, this
equality must not hold. Because this side
happens to be even, as we said. B times N
for exactly the same reason is also even:
N is divisible by two; therefore B times N
is also divisible by two. So therefore B
times N+1 is odd. And since even
can't equal to odd, it's not possible that
A times X is equal to some multiple of N+1. And in particular this means
that A cannot be the inverse of X because
A times X cannot be 1 mod N so X is not
invertible modular N. So now we have a
complete understanding of what are the
invertible elements. Basically, we know
that an element is invertible if and only
if it's relatively prime to N. And what I
like about this proof is I would say this
is what's called a computer-science proof
In the sense that not only does it prove
to you that the inverse exists; it also
shows you how to efficiently calculate the
inverse. And the way we calculate the
inverse, is basically by using this
extending decreasing algorithm. Define the
numbers A and B. And once we found the
numbers A and B, we done because A is the
inverse of X. And the numbers A and B can
be found very efficiently. So along the
way I've also shown you an algorithm for
inverting elements, modulo N.
Okay. So
bear with me, and let's introduce this little more notation. So we're gonna denote by ZN as the set of invertible elements in
Z N. In other words, ZN is the set
of all elements in ZN such that GCD(X,N)=1
Okay. But I want you, again, to think of ZN as
basically those elements in ZN that have
an inverse. So let's look at a few
examples. So let's start with a prime p.
We know that of the integers from zero to
p-1, all of them are gonna be
relatively primed to p except one
integer--namely, the integer 0. Zero is
not relatively primed to P, because the
GCD(p,0)=0, not 1. So
therefore, if p is a prime, the set ZP
is simply ZP minus 0, Which means
that everything in ZP is invertible
except for 0. So if you like the size
of ZP, it's simply P-1. Now
let's look at our favorite integer again.
So why don't you tell me what is Z12
what is the set of invertible elements modulo 12?
And the answer, of course, is all the numbers
that are relatively primed to 12--namely,
1, 5, 7, and 11. So, for
example, 3, 4, 6--all of those are
not invertible because they all have a, a
non-trivial GCD with twelve, And as we
said before, if I give you an element X
and ZN, you can find its inverse
using the extended Euclidean algorithm.
You can find its inverse very efficiently,
in fact, using this algorithm. So what we
just learned is basically how to solve
modular linear equations. In other words,
if I give you a linear equation and I ask
you to solve it mod N, it's actually very
easy to do. All you do is you move B to
the other side so you have a minus B, and
then you multiply by A inverse. So the
answer is minus B times A inverse. And you
can find A inverse using the Euclidean
algorithm. And once you have a inverse,
you'd simply multiply it by minus B,
modulo N, and that gives you the solution
to this linear equation. Now the
Euclidian algorithm actually takes time
that's quadratic in logarithm of N. So it
takes time proportional to log squared N.
And as a result we say that this is a
quadratic algorithm for solving linear
equations, modulo N, and if fact this is
the best know algorithm. And so if you
think back to your high-school algebra
days, after you learned how to solve
linear equations, the next question was,
well, what about quadratic equations. And
that problem is actually quite
interesting, and we're gonna see that in
the next few segments.