1
00:00:00,152 --> 00:00:01,703
接下来我们将讨论的问题是

2
00:00:00,152 --> 00:00:01,703
The next question, we're going to ask:

3
00:00:01,703 --> 00:00:03,638
RSA真的是一个单向函数吗

4
00:00:01,703 --> 00:00:03,638
is RSA really an one-way function?

5
00:00:03,638 --> 00:00:05,788
换句话说，在不知道天窗的情况下

6
00:00:03,638 --> 00:00:05,788
In other words, is it really hard to

7
00:00:05,788 --> 00:00:08,104
求RSA的逆真的很难吗？

8
00:00:05,788 --> 00:00:08,104
invert RSA without knowing the trapdoor?

9
00:00:09,012 --> 00:00:11,998
所以，如果一个攻击者想要求函数的RSA的逆

10
00:00:09,012 --> 00:00:11,998
So, if an attacker wanted to invert the RSA function,

11
00:00:11,998 --> 00:00:15,001
攻击者有的是公钥

12
00:00:11,998 --> 00:00:15,001
well, what the attacker has, is basically the public key,

13
00:00:15,001 --> 00:00:19,054
也就是（N，e）现在他有x^e

14
00:00:15,001 --> 00:00:19,054
namely he has N and e. And now, he is given x to the e

15
00:00:19,054 --> 00:00:23,293
他的目标是复原X。好了，问题是

16
00:00:19,054 --> 00:00:23,293
and his goal is to recover x. OK, so the question really is:

17
00:00:23,293 --> 00:00:26,131
有了想X^e（mod N）,还原x的难度有多大呢

18
00:00:23,293 --> 00:00:26,131
given x to the e modulo N, how hard is it to

19
00:00:26,131 --> 00:00:28,933
我们真正问的是

20
00:00:26,131 --> 00:00:28,933
recover x? So, what we're really asking is,

21
00:00:28,933 --> 00:00:33,113
计算合数模e的次方根有多难

22
00:00:28,933 --> 00:00:33,113
how hard is it to compute e'th roots modulo a composite?

23
00:00:34,178 --> 00:00:38,544
如果这个问题很难被解决，则RSA是单向函数

24
00:00:34,178 --> 00:00:38,544
If this problem turns out to be hard, then RSA is in fact an one-way function.

25
00:00:38,544 --> 00:00:39,968
如果这个问题很容易被解决

26
00:00:38,544 --> 00:00:39,968
If this problem turns out to be easy, which

27
00:00:39,968 --> 00:00:44,564
当然我们不相信它是容易的，那么RSA就会被破解了

28
00:00:39,968 --> 00:00:44,564
of course we don't believe it's easy, then RSA would actually be broken.

29
00:00:44,564 --> 00:00:46,832
所以，解决这个问你的最好算法是

30
00:00:44,564 --> 00:00:46,832
So, it turns out the best algorithm for this problem

31
00:00:46,832 --> 00:00:49,563
需要我们先分解模N

32
00:00:46,832 --> 00:00:49,563
requires us to first factor the modulus N.

33
00:00:50,050 --> 00:00:52,236
然后，一旦我们分解了模，上周我们就知道了

34
00:00:50,050 --> 00:00:52,236
And then, once we factored the modulus, we have already

35
00:00:52,236 --> 00:00:55,892
计算模p的e的次方根就很容易了

36
00:00:52,236 --> 00:00:55,892
seen last week, that it's easy to compute the e'th root modulo p,

37
00:00:55,892 --> 00:00:58,483
容易计算模p的e次方根

38
00:00:55,892 --> 00:00:58,483
it's easy to compute the e'th root modulo q.

39
00:00:58,483 --> 00:01:02,107
然后有了这些e的次方根，把他们组合在一起就很容易了

40
00:00:58,483 --> 00:01:02,107
And, then given both those e'th roots, it's actually easy to combine them together,

41
00:01:02,107 --> 00:01:04,699
使用中国剩余定理

42
00:01:02,107 --> 00:01:04,699
using what's called the Chinese remainder theorem

43
00:01:04,699 --> 00:01:07,667
就可以还原模N的e的次方根

44
00:01:04,699 --> 00:01:07,667
and actually recover the e'th root modulo N.

45
00:01:07,667 --> 00:01:09,946
所以，一旦我们能分解模

46
00:01:07,667 --> 00:01:09,946
So, once we are able to factor the modulus,

47
00:01:09,946 --> 00:01:12,848
计算模p的e的次方根就变得很容易

48
00:01:09,946 --> 00:01:12,848
computing e'th roots modulo N becomes easy.

49
00:01:12,848 --> 00:01:14,636
但是，分解模

50
00:01:12,848 --> 00:01:14,636
But,  factoring  the modulus, as far as

51
00:01:14,636 --> 00:01:16,761
正如我们所知，是一个非常非常困难的问题

52
00:01:14,636 --> 00:01:16,761
we know, is a very, very difficult problem.

53
00:01:16,761 --> 00:01:19,865
但是一个自然的问题是，为了计算模N的e次方根

54
00:01:16,761 --> 00:01:19,865
But a natural question is, is it true that in

55
00:01:19,865 --> 00:01:22,568
我们去分解模N是正确的吗？

56
00:01:19,865 --> 00:01:22,568
order to compute e'th roots modulo N, we have to

57
00:01:22,568 --> 00:01:25,707
正如我们所知

58
00:01:22,568 --> 00:01:25,707
factor the modulus N? As far as we know, the

59
00:01:25,707 --> 00:01:27,369
计算模N 的e次方的最佳算法

60
00:01:25,707 --> 00:01:27,369
best algorithm for computing e'th roots

61
00:01:27,369 --> 00:01:30,002
是需要将N进行分解

62
00:01:27,369 --> 00:01:30,002
modulo N requires factorization of N.

63
00:01:30,002 --> 00:01:31,626
但是，谁知道呢，也许有一条捷径

64
00:01:30,002 --> 00:01:31,626
But, who knows, maybe there is a short cut

65
00:01:31,626 --> 00:01:33,771
能让我们计算模N的e次方根

66
00:01:31,626 --> 00:01:33,771
that allows us to compute e'th roots modulo N,

67
00:01:33,771 --> 00:01:36,704
而不需要分解模

68
00:01:33,771 --> 00:01:36,704
without factoring the modulus. To show that

69
00:01:36,704 --> 00:01:38,808
为了证明这是不可能，我们必须证明一个简约

70
00:01:36,704 --> 00:01:38,808
that's not possible, we have to show a reduction.

71
00:01:38,808 --> 00:01:40,314
也就是说，我们需要证明

72
00:01:38,808 --> 00:01:40,314
That is, we have to show that,

73
00:01:40,314 --> 00:01:42,001
如果我给大家一个有效的算法

74
00:01:40,314 --> 00:01:42,001
if I give you an efficient algorithm for

75
00:01:42,001 --> 00:01:43,872
可以计算模N的e次方根

76
00:01:42,001 --> 00:01:43,872
computing e'th roots modulo N, that

77
00:01:43,872 --> 00:01:48,132
那么这个有效的算法就被可以改造成一个计算分解因子的算法

78
00:01:43,872 --> 00:01:48,132
efficient algorithm can be turned into a factoring algorithm.

79
00:01:48,132 --> 00:01:51,015
这叫做一个简约，给定一个计算模N的e次方根的算法

80
00:01:48,132 --> 00:01:51,015
So, this is called a reduction. Namely, given an algorithm for

81
00:01:51,015 --> 00:01:53,137
我们可以得到一个计算分解因子的算法

82
00:01:51,015 --> 00:01:53,137
e'th roots modulo N, we obtain a factoring algorithm.

83
00:01:53,137 --> 00:01:57,314
这就说明任何人都不能计算模N的e次方根

84
00:01:53,137 --> 00:01:57,314
That would show that one cannot compute e'th roots modulo N

85
00:01:57,314 --> 00:02:00,101
比分解模的速度更快

86
00:01:57,314 --> 00:02:00,101
faster than factoring the modulus.

87
00:02:00,101 --> 00:02:02,285
如果我们有这样一个结论，这说明

88
00:02:00,101 --> 00:02:02,285
If we had such a result, it would show that

89
00:02:02,285 --> 00:02:05,716
破解RSA和分解大合数一样难

90
00:02:02,285 --> 00:02:05,716
actually breaking RSA, in fact is as hard as factoring.

91
00:02:05,716 --> 00:02:08,110
但很不幸，目前这个证明我们还不知道

92
00:02:05,716 --> 00:02:08,110
But, unfortunately, this is not really known at the moment.

93
00:02:08,110 --> 00:02:11,969
事实上，这是公钥密码学里最古老的问题之一

94
00:02:08,110 --> 00:02:11,969
In fact, this is one of the oldest problems in public key crypto.

95
00:02:11,969 --> 00:02:14,415
让我举个具体的例子

96
00:02:11,969 --> 00:02:14,415
So, just let me give you a concrete example.

97
00:02:14,415 --> 00:02:18,523
假设我给你们一个可以计算出模N的立方根的算法

98
00:02:14,415 --> 00:02:18,523
Suppose, I give you an algorithm that will compute cube roots modulo N.

99
00:02:19,037 --> 00:02:23,693
所以，对于任意的Z_N中的x，这个算法可以算出x的模N的立方根

100
00:02:19,037 --> 00:02:23,693
So, for any x in ZN, the algorithm will compute the cube root of x modulo N.

101
00:02:23,693 --> 00:02:25,971
我的问题是，你能证明

102
00:02:23,693 --> 00:02:25,971
My question is, can you show that using

103
00:02:25,971 --> 00:02:29,066
用这样的算法可以分解模N吗？

104
00:02:25,971 --> 00:02:29,066
such an algorithm you can factor the modulus N?

105
00:02:29,066 --> 00:02:31,239
即使这个证明你不知道。我们都知道的

106
00:02:29,066 --> 00:02:31,239
And, even that is not known. What is known,

107
00:02:31,239 --> 00:02:33,920
我要告诉你的是，例如e=2

108
00:02:31,239 --> 00:02:33,920
I'll tell you, is for example that for e equals 2,

109
00:02:34,375 --> 00:02:37,711
如果给你一个计算模N的平方根的算法

110
00:02:34,375 --> 00:02:37,711
that is if I give you an algorithm for computing square roots modulo N,

111
00:02:37,711 --> 00:02:40,696
事实上，这就暗示着分解模的算法

112
00:02:37,711 --> 00:02:40,696
then in fact, that does imply factoring the modulus.

113
00:02:40,696 --> 00:02:44,699
所以，计算模N的平方根和分解模式一样困难的

114
00:02:40,696 --> 00:02:44,699
So, computing square roots is in fact as hard as factoring the modulus.

115
00:02:44,712 --> 00:02:47,779
不幸的是，如果你回想起来RSA的定义

116
00:02:44,712 --> 00:02:47,779
Unfortunately, if you think back to the definition of RSA,

117
00:02:47,779 --> 00:02:52,913
它要求ed=1mod φ（N）

118
00:02:47,779 --> 00:02:52,913
that required that e times d be 1 modulo phi(N).

119
00:02:52,913 --> 00:02:58,612
意思是，e和模φ（N）必须是互质的

120
00:02:52,913 --> 00:02:58,612
What that means is, that e necessarily needs to be relatively prime to phi(N).

121
00:02:58,612 --> 00:03:03,128
这里第一个方程就是说，e是模φ（N）可逆的

122
00:02:58,612 --> 00:03:03,128
Right, this, what the first equation says is that e is invertible modulo phi(N).

123
00:03:03,128 --> 00:03:06,125
但是，如果e模φ（N）式可逆的，这意味着

124
00:03:03,128 --> 00:03:06,125
But, if e is invertible modulo phi(N), necessarily that means that

125
00:03:06,125 --> 00:03:09,107
e必须和φ（N）是互质的

126
00:03:06,125 --> 00:03:09,107
e must be relatively prime to phi(N).

127
00:03:09,107 --> 00:03:13,927
但是，φ（N），如果你们记得，φ（N）=（p-1）*（q-1）

128
00:03:09,107 --> 00:03:13,927
But, phi(N), if you remember, that is equal to p minus 1 times q minus 1.

129
00:03:13,927 --> 00:03:19,377
如果p和q都是大质数，（p-1）和（q-1）一定是偶数

130
00:03:13,927 --> 00:03:19,377
And, since p and q are both large primes,  p - 1 times q - 1 is always even.

131
00:03:19,377 --> 00:03:25,503
事实上，GCD（2，φ（N））=2

132
00:03:19,377 --> 00:03:25,503
And, as a result,  the GCD of 2 and phi(N) is equal to 2,

133
00:03:25,503 --> 00:03:28,221
因为φ（N）是偶数，因此

134
00:03:25,503 --> 00:03:28,221
because phi(N) is even. And therefore, the public

135
00:03:28,221 --> 00:03:30,863
公钥指数2和φ（N）不是互质的

136
00:03:28,221 --> 00:03:30,863
exponent 2 is not relatively prime to phi(N).

137
00:03:30,863 --> 00:03:33,174
意思是说，即使我们有了一个简约

138
00:03:30,863 --> 00:03:33,174
Which means that, even though we have a reduction

139
00:03:33,174 --> 00:03:35,263
从计算平方根来求因子分解

140
00:03:33,174 --> 00:03:35,263
from taking square roots to factoring,

141
00:03:35,263 --> 00:03:38,758
e=2也不能被拿来当做RSA指数

142
00:03:35,263 --> 00:03:38,758
e equals 2 cannot be used as an RSA exponent.

143
00:03:38,758 --> 00:03:43,643
那么真正合法的最小的RSA指数等于3

144
00:03:38,758 --> 00:03:43,643
So, really the smallest RSA exponent that is legal is in fact e equals 3.

145
00:03:43,643 --> 00:03:46,911
但是等于3，问题就是计算立方根

146
00:03:43,643 --> 00:03:46,911
But, for e equal 3, the question of whether computing cube roots

147
00:03:46,911 --> 00:03:48,976
与因子分解一样难，这是个开放的问题

148
00:03:46,911 --> 00:03:48,976
is as hard as factoring, is an open problem.

149
00:03:48,976 --> 00:03:50,978
这个问题很有趣，值得想想

150
00:03:48,976 --> 00:03:50,978
It's actually a lot of fun to think about this question.

151
00:03:50,978 --> 00:03:53,444
那么我鼓励大家简单想想这个问题

152
00:03:50,978 --> 00:03:53,444
So, I would encourage you to think about it just a little bit.

153
00:03:53,444 --> 00:03:58,352
就是说，如果我给你一个有效算法，来计算模N的立方根

154
00:03:53,444 --> 00:03:58,352
That is, if I give you an efficient algorithm for computing cube roots modulo N,

155
00:03:58,352 --> 00:04:02,111
你能使用这个算法来分解模N吗？

156
00:03:58,352 --> 00:04:02,111
can you use that algorithm to actually factor the modulus N?

157
00:04:02,111 --> 00:04:05,301
我会告诉大家，有一些证据说明

158
00:04:02,111 --> 00:04:05,301
I will tell you that there is a little bit of evidence to say

159
00:04:05,301 --> 00:04:09,402
这样的规约可能并不存在，但这只是一个很弱的证据

160
00:04:05,301 --> 00:04:09,402
that a reduction like that,  actually doesn't exist, but it is very, very weak evidence.

161
00:04:09,402 --> 00:04:11,366
这个证据是说

162
00:04:09,402 --> 00:04:11,366
What this evidence says is  basically, if you

163
00:04:11,366 --> 00:04:13,500
如果你给我一个非常特别的形式的规约

164
00:04:11,366 --> 00:04:13,500
give me a reduction of a very particular form.

165
00:04:13,500 --> 00:04:16,070
换句话说，如果你的规约是代数的

166
00:04:13,500 --> 00:04:16,070
In other words, if your reduction is what's called algebraic,

167
00:04:16,070 --> 00:04:18,509
我在这里先不解释它的意义

168
00:04:16,070 --> 00:04:18,509
(I am not going to explain what that means here.)

169
00:04:18,509 --> 00:04:23,087
如果有一个立方根神谕，你可以给我一个算法

170
00:04:18,509 --> 00:04:23,087
That is, if given a cube root oracle, you could actually show me an algorithm

171
00:04:23,087 --> 00:04:26,055
可以计算因子分解。这个规约本身

172
00:04:23,087 --> 00:04:26,055
that would then factor. That reduction, by itself,

173
00:04:26,055 --> 00:04:28,554
就会蕴含着因子分解的算法

174
00:04:26,055 --> 00:04:28,554
would actually imply a factoring algorithm.

175
00:04:28,554 --> 00:04:31,084
这就是说，如果因子分解是困难的

176
00:04:28,554 --> 00:04:31,084
Okay  so, that would say that if factoring is hard,

177
00:04:31,084 --> 00:04:33,637
那么规约根本就不存在

178
00:04:31,084 --> 00:04:33,637
a reduction actually doesn't  exist.

179
00:04:33,637 --> 00:04:35,537
但是，如我所说，这是非常弱的证据

180
00:04:33,637 --> 00:04:35,537
But, as I say this is very weak evidence.

181
00:04:35,537 --> 00:04:37,617
因为，需要规约是代数的

182
00:04:35,537 --> 00:04:37,617
Because, who is to say that the reduction needs to be algebraic.

183
00:04:37,617 --> 00:04:39,725
也许会有其他类型的规约

184
00:04:37,617 --> 00:04:39,725
Maybe, there are some other types of reductions that

185
00:04:39,725 --> 00:04:42,857
比如我们没有考虑过的类型

186
00:04:39,725 --> 00:04:42,857
we haven't really considered. So, I would

187
00:04:42,857 --> 00:04:44,339
那么我会鼓励大家去略微考虑一下这个问题

188
00:04:42,857 --> 00:04:44,339
encourage you to think a little bit about this

189
00:04:44,339 --> 00:04:46,235
这是很有趣的

190
00:04:44,339 --> 00:04:46,235
question. It's actually quite interesting.

191
00:04:46,235 --> 00:04:50,087
如何使用一个立方根算法来分解模？

192
00:04:46,235 --> 00:04:50,087
How would you use a cube root algorithm to factor the modulus?

193
00:04:51,308 --> 00:04:54,143
但是如我所说，我们目前只知道RSA是一个单向函数

194
00:04:51,308 --> 00:04:54,143
But as I said, as far as we know, RSA is a one way function.

195
00:04:54,143 --> 00:05:00,274
事实上破解RSA，计算e次方根，都要求因子分解模

196
00:04:54,143 --> 00:05:00,274
In fact, breaking RSA, computing e'th roots that is, actually requires factoring the modulus.

197
00:05:00,274 --> 00:05:02,918
我们都相信那是正确的，这就是目前的研究现状

198
00:05:00,274 --> 00:05:02,918
We all believe that's true, and that's the state of the art.

199
00:05:02,918 --> 00:05:07,637
但是，现在有很多研究工作，试图提高RSA的性能

200
00:05:02,918 --> 00:05:07,637
But, now there has been a lot of work on trying to improve the performance of RSA.

201
00:05:07,637 --> 00:05:12,041
提高RSA加密的性能，或是RSA解密的性能

202
00:05:07,637 --> 00:05:12,041
Either, RSA encryption or improve the performance of RSA decryption.

203
00:05:12,041 --> 00:05:14,901
实际上，这个研究方向开始时人们走了很多弯路

204
00:05:12,041 --> 00:05:14,901
And it turns out, there has been a number of false starts in this direction.

205
00:05:14,901 --> 00:05:18,796
我想展示给大家这个非常好的例子，作为警示

206
00:05:14,901 --> 00:05:18,796
So I want to show you, this wonderful example as a warning.

207
00:05:18,796 --> 00:05:23,232
这是一个试图提高RSA性能的错误例子

208
00:05:18,796 --> 00:05:23,232
So basically, this is an example of how not to improve the perfomance of RSA.

209
00:05:23,232 --> 00:05:26,772
设想如果我想加速RSA解密

210
00:05:23,232 --> 00:05:26,772
So, you might think that if I wanted to speed up RSA decryption,

211
00:05:26,772 --> 00:05:28,578
记得解密是通过计算

212
00:05:26,772 --> 00:05:28,578
remember decryption is done by raising the

213
00:05:28,578 --> 00:05:30,895
密文的d次方。大家记得

214
00:05:28,578 --> 00:05:30,895
ciphertext to the power of d. And, you remember

215
00:05:30,895 --> 00:05:34,265
指数算法的运行时间

216
00:05:30,895 --> 00:05:34,265
that the exponentiation algorithm ran in linear

217
00:05:34,265 --> 00:05:37,767
与d的长度大小成线性关系，与log(d)成线性

218
00:05:34,265 --> 00:05:37,767
time in the size of d. Linear time in log of d.

219
00:05:37,767 --> 00:05:39,762
那么大家可以回想一下，如果我想

220
00:05:37,767 --> 00:05:39,762
So, you might think to yourself, well if I wanted

221
00:05:39,762 --> 00:05:43,522
加速RSA解密，我为什么不使用一个小d呢？

222
00:05:39,762 --> 00:05:43,522
to speed up RSA decryption, why don't I just use a small d.

223
00:05:43,522 --> 00:05:48,265
比如说，使用一个解密指数，大约是2的128次方

224
00:05:43,522 --> 00:05:48,265
I'll say, I'll say a decryption exponent that's on the order of 2 to the 128.

225
00:05:48,419 --> 00:05:52,350
那么这已经够大了，穷举d实际上是不可能的

226
00:05:48,419 --> 00:05:52,350
So it's clearly big enough so that exhaustive search against d is not possible.

227
00:05:52,350 --> 00:05:57,418
但正常情况下，解密指数d约与模一般大，比如说2000位

228
00:05:52,350 --> 00:05:57,418
But normally, the decryption exponent d would be as big as the modulus, say 2000 bits.

229
00:05:57,418 --> 00:06:04,669
通过使用仅为128位的d，我可以提高RSA解密速度20倍

230
00:05:57,418 --> 00:06:04,669
By using d that's only 128 bits, I basically speed up RSA decryption by a factor of 20.

231
00:06:04,669 --> 00:06:07,533
我从2000位降到100位

232
00:06:04,669 --> 00:06:07,533
Right, I went down from 2000 bits to 100 bits.

233
00:06:07,533 --> 00:06:10,915
那么计算指数的速度会快20倍

234
00:06:07,533 --> 00:06:10,915
So, exponentiation would run 20 times as fast.

235
00:06:10,915 --> 00:06:15,440
实际上这是一个糟糕的点子。非常糟糕的点子，根据接下来的思路来看

236
00:06:10,915 --> 00:06:15,440
It turns out this is a terrible idea. Terrible, terrible idea, in the following sense.

237
00:06:15,440 --> 00:06:18,638
Michael Wiener有一个攻击，证明了事实上

238
00:06:15,440 --> 00:06:18,638
There is an attack by Michael Wiener that shows that, in fact,

239
00:06:18,638 --> 00:06:23,425
一旦私钥指数d小于模的4次方

240
00:06:18,638 --> 00:06:23,425
as soon as the private exponent d is less than the fourth root of the modulus.

241
00:06:23,425 --> 00:06:27,526
我们看，如果模大约是2048位

242
00:06:23,425 --> 00:06:27,526
Let's see, if the modulus is around 2048 bits

243
00:06:27,526 --> 00:06:34,581
这意味着如果d小于2的512次方，那么RSA是完全不安全的

244
00:06:27,526 --> 00:06:34,581
that means that if d is less that 2 to the 512, then RSA is completely, completely insecure.

245
00:06:34,581 --> 00:06:37,509
而且这是最坏的一种不安全

246
00:06:34,581 --> 00:06:37,509
And, this is, it's insecure in the worst possible way.

247
00:06:37,509 --> 00:06:43,129
即给定一个公钥。你可以很快还原出私钥d

248
00:06:37,509 --> 00:06:43,129
Namely, just given a public key and an e, you can very quickly recover the private key d.

249
00:06:44,227 --> 00:06:48,493
所以有传言说：这个攻击可以针对最多512位

250
00:06:44,227 --> 00:06:48,493
Well, so some folks said: well this attack works up to 512 bits.

251
00:06:48,493 --> 00:06:52,378
那么我们为什么不让这个模，比如说530位

252
00:06:48,493 --> 00:06:52,378
So, why donÂ´t we make the modulus, say, you know 530 bits.

253
00:06:52,378 --> 00:06:54,234
那么这个攻击就不能用了

254
00:06:52,378 --> 00:06:54,234
Then, this attack actually wouldn't apply.

255
00:06:54,234 --> 00:06:57,545
但是我们依然可以让RSA解密加速4倍

256
00:06:54,234 --> 00:06:57,545
But still, we get to speed up RSA decryption by a factor of 4,

257
00:06:57,545 --> 00:07:01,997
因为我们能把指数从2000位降到比如说530位

258
00:06:57,545 --> 00:07:01,997
because we shrunk the exponent from 2000 bits to, say, 530 bits.

259
00:07:01,997 --> 00:07:03,978
实际上，即使这是不安全的。事实上

260
00:07:01,997 --> 00:07:03,978
Well it turns out, even that is not secure. In fact,

261
00:07:03,978 --> 00:07:06,243
Wiener的攻击有一个扩展

262
00:07:03,978 --> 00:07:06,243
there is an extension to Wiener's attack, that's actually much

263
00:07:06,243 --> 00:07:08,176
复杂的多的扩展，证实了

264
00:07:06,243 --> 00:07:08,176
more complicated, that shows that if d

265
00:07:08,176 --> 00:07:13,233
如果d小于N^0.292，那么RSA也是不安全的

266
00:07:08,176 --> 00:07:13,233
is less than N to the 0.292, then also RSA is insecure.

267
00:07:13,233 --> 00:07:16,674
事实上这个猜想是说，这对最多N^0.5来说是正确的

268
00:07:13,233 --> 00:07:16,674
And in fact, the conjecture that this is true up to N to the 0.5.

269
00:07:16,674 --> 00:07:21,975
即使d大约为N^0.4999，RSA依然是不安全的

270
00:07:16,674 --> 00:07:21,975
So even if d is like N to the 0.4999, RSA should still be insecure,

271
00:07:21,975 --> 00:07:25,780
尽管这是个开放问题，也是一个极好的开放问题

272
00:07:21,975 --> 00:07:25,780
although this is an open problem. It's again, a wonderful open problem,

273
00:07:25,780 --> 00:07:28,394
这个问题存在到现在已经14年了

274
00:07:25,780 --> 00:07:28,394
It's been open for like, what is it, 14 years now.

275
00:07:28,394 --> 00:07:31,556
没人可以超过这个0.292

276
00:07:28,394 --> 00:07:31,556
And, nobody can progress beyond this 0.292.

277
00:07:31,556 --> 00:07:34,327
这有点奇怪 为什么0.292是正确的答案

278
00:07:31,556 --> 00:07:34,327
Somehow, it seems kind of strange, why would 0.292

279
00:07:34,327 --> 00:07:38,217
没人能超过0.292呢

280
00:07:34,327 --> 00:07:38,217
be the right answer and yet no one can go beyond 0.292.

281
00:07:38,802 --> 00:07:41,671
所以 为了准确 当我说RSA是不安全的

282
00:07:38,802 --> 00:07:41,671
So, just to be precise, when I say that RSA is insecure,

283
00:07:41,671 --> 00:07:45,218
我的意思是 当给了公钥（N,e）时

284
00:07:41,671 --> 00:07:45,218
what I mean is just given the public key N and e,

285
00:07:45,218 --> 00:07:48,077
你的目标是还原私钥d

286
00:07:45,218 --> 00:07:48,077
your goal is to recover the secret key d.

287
00:07:49,102 --> 00:07:52,257
如果你对0.292是怎么来的感到好奇

288
00:07:49,102 --> 00:07:52,257
If you are curious where 0.292 comes from,

289
00:07:52,257 --> 00:07:56,312
我会告诉你 它实际上是等于1减去1除以根号2

290
00:07:52,257 --> 00:07:56,312
I'll tell you that what it is, it's basically 1 minus 1 over square root of 2.

291
00:07:56,312 --> 00:07:58,503
为什么这会是问题的正确答案呢

292
00:07:56,312 --> 00:07:58,503
Now how could this possibly be the right answer to this problem?

293
00:07:58,503 --> 00:08:01,296
答案是N^0.5看起来会更加合理

294
00:07:58,503 --> 00:08:01,296
It's much more natural that the answer is N to the 0.5.

295
00:08:01,296 --> 00:08:04,340
但这仍然是一个开放问题 如果你仍然想思考这个问题

296
00:08:01,296 --> 00:08:04,340
But this is still an open problem. Again if you want to think about that,

297
00:08:04,340 --> 00:08:06,163
这是一个很有趣的值得研究的问题

298
00:08:04,340 --> 00:08:06,163
it's kind of a fun problem to work on.

299
00:08:06,163 --> 00:08:10,101
这里得到的经验是不应该在d上强制添加任何结构

300
00:08:06,163 --> 00:08:10,101
So the lesson in this is that one should not enforce any structure on d

301
00:08:10,101 --> 00:08:12,475
来提高RSA的性能 实际上

302
00:08:10,101 --> 00:08:12,475
for improving the performance of RSA, and in fact

303
00:08:12,475 --> 00:08:15,276
现在有很多这样的结果

304
00:08:12,475 --> 00:08:15,276
now there's a slew of results like this that show

305
00:08:15,276 --> 00:08:19,714
证明了任何像这样的试图提高RSA性能的技巧

306
00:08:15,276 --> 00:08:19,714
that basically, any kind of tricks like this to try and improve RSA's performance

307
00:08:19,714 --> 00:08:24,285
最后都会以灾难结束 所以这不是正确的改善RSA性能的方法

308
00:08:19,714 --> 00:08:24,285
is going to end up in disaster. So this is not the right way to improve RSA's performance.

309
00:08:24,285 --> 00:08:27,987
原本我不想讲解Wiener攻击的细节

310
00:08:24,285 --> 00:08:27,987
Initially I wasn't going to cover the details of Wiener's attack.

311
00:08:27,987 --> 00:08:31,582
但是根据课堂上的讨论 我觉得你们当中有些人会想看这些细节

312
00:08:27,987 --> 00:08:31,582
But given the discussions in the class, I think some of you would enjoy seeing the details.

313
00:08:31,582 --> 00:08:35,229
它所有涉及到的只是对不等式的一些运算

314
00:08:31,582 --> 00:08:35,229
All it involves is just manipulating some inequalities.

315
00:08:35,229 --> 00:08:37,743
如果你对这些不太感兴趣 放轻松 跳过这几张幻灯片就好

316
00:08:35,229 --> 00:08:37,743
If you're not comfortable with that, feel free to skip over this slide,

317
00:08:37,743 --> 00:08:40,979
尽管我觉得你们当中很多人会对这些细节很感兴趣

318
00:08:37,743 --> 00:08:40,979
although I think many of you would actually enjoy seeing the details.

319
00:08:40,979 --> 00:08:43,365
那么我提醒大家 在Wiener的攻击里

320
00:08:40,979 --> 00:08:43,365
So let me remind you in Wiener's attack basically

321
00:08:43,365 --> 00:08:46,893
我们给定了模和RSA指数（N,e）

322
00:08:43,365 --> 00:08:46,893
we're given the modulus and the RSA exponent N and e,

323
00:08:46,893 --> 00:08:50,513
我们的目标是得到私钥指数d

324
00:08:46,893 --> 00:08:50,513
and our goal is to recover d, the private exponent d,

325
00:08:50,513 --> 00:08:54,171
我们知道的信息只有d是小于N的四次方根的

326
00:08:50,513 --> 00:08:54,171
and all we know is that d is basically less than the fourth root of N.

327
00:08:54,171 --> 00:08:57,711
实际上 我将假设d是小于N的四次方根除以3的

328
00:08:54,171 --> 00:08:57,711
In fact, I'm going to assume that d is less than the fourth root of N divided by 3.

329
00:08:57,711 --> 00:09:02,373
这个3不重要 但是这里主要起作用的项是d小于N的四次方根

330
00:08:57,711 --> 00:09:02,373
This 3 doesn't really matter, but the dominating term here is that d is less than the 4th root of N.

331
00:09:02,373 --> 00:09:05,944
那么我们来看看是怎么做的 首先记住

332
00:09:02,373 --> 00:09:05,944
So let's see how to do it. So first of all, recall that

333
00:09:05,944 --> 00:09:09,144
因为e和d分别是RSA的公钥和私钥指数

334
00:09:05,944 --> 00:09:09,144
because e and d are RSA public and private exponents,

335
00:09:09,144 --> 00:09:14,145
我们知道e*d=1modφ（N） 这是什么意思

336
00:09:09,144 --> 00:09:14,145
we know that e times d is 1 modulo phi(N). Well what does that mean?

337
00:09:14,145 --> 00:09:22,248
这意味着这里存在某个整数k 满足e*d=kφ（N）+1

338
00:09:14,145 --> 00:09:22,248
That means that there exists some integer k such that e times d is equal to k times phi(N) plus 1.

339
00:09:22,248 --> 00:09:26,280
这就是e^d=1modφ（N）的含义

340
00:09:22,248 --> 00:09:26,280
Basically that's what it means for e times d to be 1 modulo phi(N).

341
00:09:26,280 --> 00:09:29,832
即某个整数乘以φ（N）+1

342
00:09:26,280 --> 00:09:29,832
Basically some integer multiple of phi(N) plus 1.

343
00:09:29,832 --> 00:09:32,592
那么现在让我们盯着这个等式看一会儿

344
00:09:29,832 --> 00:09:32,592
So now let's stare at this equation a little bit.

345
00:09:32,592 --> 00:09:35,826
实际上这个等式就是攻击的关键

346
00:09:32,592 --> 00:09:35,826
And in fact this equation is the key equation in the attack.

347
00:09:35,826 --> 00:09:40,352
那么我们首先将要做的是两边同时除以φ（N）

348
00:09:35,826 --> 00:09:40,352
And what we're going to do is first of all divide both sides by d times phi(N).

349
00:09:40,352 --> 00:09:43,703
实际上我把这一项移到左边

350
00:09:40,352 --> 00:09:43,703
And in fact I'm going to move this term here to the left.

351
00:09:43,703 --> 00:09:47,453
在我对两边同时除以d*φ（N）我得到了

352
00:09:43,703 --> 00:09:47,453
So after I divide by d times phi(N), what I get is that

353
00:09:47,453 --> 00:09:58,500
e/φ（N）-k/d=1/(d*φ（N）)

354
00:09:47,453 --> 00:09:58,500
e divided by phi(N) minus k divided by d is equal to 1 over d times phi(N).

355
00:09:59,469 --> 00:10:02,902
我只做了除以d*φ（N）

356
00:09:59,469 --> 00:10:02,902
Okay, so all I did is I just divided by d times phi(N)

357
00:10:02,902 --> 00:10:05,850
然后我把k*φ（N）这一项移到等式左边

358
00:10:02,902 --> 00:10:05,850
and I moved the k times phi(N) term to the left-hand side.

359
00:10:05,850 --> 00:10:09,119
为了更清楚的表达 我将会加上绝对值

360
00:10:05,850 --> 00:10:09,119
Now, just for the heck of it I'm going to add absolute values here.

361
00:10:09,119 --> 00:10:13,484
这个马上会用到 当然，这不会改变它们的相等性

362
00:10:09,119 --> 00:10:13,484
These will become useful in just a minute, but of course they don't change this equality at all.

363
00:10:13,484 --> 00:10:20,184
现在 φ（N）约等于N 即与N非常接近 正如我们之前所说

364
00:10:13,484 --> 00:10:20,184
Now, phi(N) of course is almost N; phi(N) is very, very close to N, as we said earlier.

365
00:10:20,184 --> 00:10:23,371
现在我需要它们 我们认为这个分式

366
00:10:20,184 --> 00:10:23,371
And all I'm going to need then for this fraction is just to say that

367
00:10:23,371 --> 00:10:26,639
小于1除以根号N 它远小于1除以根号N

368
00:10:23,371 --> 00:10:26,639
it's less than 1 over square root of N. It's actually much, much smaller

369
00:10:26,639 --> 00:10:30,571
因为1/φ（N）的数量级是1/N

370
00:10:26,639 --> 00:10:30,571
than 1 over square root of N, it's actually on the order of 1 over N or even more than that,

371
00:10:30,571 --> 00:10:35,638
但是对于我们的目标 我们所需要的只是这个分式小于1除以根号N

372
00:10:30,571 --> 00:10:35,638
but for our purposes all we need is that this fraction is less than 1 over square root of N.

373
00:10:35,638 --> 00:10:37,939
现在我们仔细看一下这个分式

374
00:10:35,638 --> 00:10:37,939
Now let's stare at this fraction for just a minute.

375
00:10:37,939 --> 00:10:44,506
大家会发现我们并不知道分式的左边

376
00:10:37,939 --> 00:10:44,506
You realize that this fraction on the left here is a fraction that we don't actually know.

377
00:10:44,506 --> 00:10:49,039
我们知道e 但是我们不知道φ（N） 所以我们不知道e/φ（N）

378
00:10:44,506 --> 00:10:49,039
We know e, but we don't know phi(N), and as a result we don't know e over phi(N).

379
00:10:49,039 --> 00:10:53,631
但是对于e/φ（N）我们有一个不错的估算方法 我们知道

380
00:10:49,039 --> 00:10:53,631
But we have a good approximation to e over phi(N). Namely we know that phi(N)

381
00:10:53,631 --> 00:10:59,238
φ（N）与N非常接近 因此e/φ（N）就约等于e/φ（N）

382
00:10:53,631 --> 00:10:59,238
is very close to N. Therefore e over phi(N) is very close to e over N.

383
00:10:59,238 --> 00:11:03,436
那么我们对等式左边的e/N有了很好的估算

384
00:10:59,238 --> 00:11:03,436
So we have a good approximation to this left-hand side fraction, namely e over N.

385
00:11:03,436 --> 00:11:06,028
现在我们最想得到的是等式右边的部分

386
00:11:03,436 --> 00:11:06,028
What we really want is the right-hand side fraction,

387
00:11:06,028 --> 00:11:07,649
因为一旦我们得到了右边的分式

388
00:11:06,028 --> 00:11:07,649
because once we get the right-hand side fraction,

389
00:11:07,649 --> 00:11:12,960
它包含了d 那么我们就可以得到d了

390
00:11:07,649 --> 00:11:12,960
basically that's going to involve d, and then we'll be able to recover d. Okay, so let's see

391
00:11:12,960 --> 00:11:19,041
如果我们用e/N代替e/φ（N） 看看会得到哪种错误

392
00:11:12,960 --> 00:11:19,041
if we replace e over phi(N) by e over N, let's see what kind of error we're going to get.

393
00:11:19,041 --> 00:11:22,514
分析一下 我们首先要提醒自己

394
00:11:19,041 --> 00:11:22,514
So to analyze that, what we'll do is first of all remind ourselves

395
00:11:22,514 --> 00:11:26,204
φ（N）= N - p - q + 1

396
00:11:22,514 --> 00:11:26,204
that phi(N) is basically N - p - q + 1,

397
00:11:26,204 --> 00:11:30,804
这意味着N-φ（N）要小于p+q

398
00:11:26,204 --> 00:11:30,804
which means that N minus phi(N) is going to be less than p + q.

399
00:11:30,804 --> 00:11:34,752
实际上我应该写p+q+1 但是大家知道

400
00:11:30,804 --> 00:11:34,752
Actually I should, to be precise I should really write p + q + 1, but you know,

401
00:11:34,752 --> 00:11:37,838
并不用在意这个1 它不会对结果产生任何影响

402
00:11:34,752 --> 00:11:37,838
who cares about this 1, it's not, it doesn't really affect anything.

403
00:11:37,838 --> 00:11:40,238
所以我将会忽略它来使问题变得更简单

404
00:11:37,838 --> 00:11:40,238
So I'm just going to ignore it for simplicity.

405
00:11:40,238 --> 00:11:45,508
好的 N-φ（N）小于p+q p和q都大约为N的长度的一半

406
00:11:40,238 --> 00:11:45,508
Okay, so N - phi(N) is less than p + q. Both p and q are roughly half the length of N,

407
00:11:45,508 --> 00:11:48,918
大家知道 它们的数量级是N^2

408
00:11:45,508 --> 00:11:48,918
so you know, they're both kind of on the order of square root of N,

409
00:11:48,918 --> 00:11:53,876
那么 p+q 比N的3次放根要小

410
00:11:48,918 --> 00:11:53,876
so basically p + q we'll say is less than 3 times square root of N.

411
00:11:53,876 --> 00:11:56,844
我们很快会用到这个不等式

412
00:11:53,876 --> 00:11:56,844
Okay, so we're going to use this inequality in just a minute.

413
00:11:56,844 --> 00:12:00,243
但我们现在要用的是我们知道的一些关于d的事实

414
00:11:56,844 --> 00:12:00,243
But now we're going to start using the fact that we know something about d,

415
00:12:00,243 --> 00:12:02,958
也就是d是一个比较小的数 所以如果我们观察这个不等式

416
00:12:00,243 --> 00:12:02,958
namely that d is small. So if we look at this inequality here,

417
00:12:02,958 --> 00:12:05,543
d比N的四次方根除3要小

418
00:12:02,958 --> 00:12:05,543
d is less than the fourth root of N divided by 3.

419
00:12:05,543 --> 00:12:08,596
这很容易就能看出 我们将两边平方

420
00:12:05,543 --> 00:12:08,596
It's actually fairly easy to see that if I square both sides

421
00:12:08,596 --> 00:12:12,118
我稍微配平一下 就不难看出

422
00:12:08,596 --> 00:12:12,118
and I just manipulate things a little bit, it's [not] difficult to see that

423
00:12:12,118 --> 00:12:15,510
这直接推出了下面的联系

424
00:12:12,118 --> 00:12:15,510
this directly implies the following relation,

425
00:12:15,510 --> 00:12:24,263
N平方根的2d-1次分之一比N平方根的份子三要大

426
00:12:15,510 --> 00:12:24,263
basically 1 over 2 d squared minus 1 over square root of N is greater than 3 over square root of N.

427
00:12:24,263 --> 00:12:28,542
正如我所说 下一步是两边平方

428
00:12:24,263 --> 00:12:28,542
As I said, this basically follows by squaring both sides, then taking the

429
00:12:28,542 --> 00:12:33,334
两边取反 然后将一边乘以另一半

430
00:12:28,542 --> 00:12:33,334
inverse of both sides, and then I guess multiplying one side by a half.

431
00:12:33,334 --> 00:12:37,906
现在你可以很容易的得到结论了 我们马上用到这个关系

432
00:12:33,334 --> 00:12:37,906
Okay, so you can easily derive this relation, and we'll need this relation in just a minute.

433
00:12:37,906 --> 00:12:40,166
现在我们看看 我们要做的是比较

434
00:12:37,906 --> 00:12:40,166
So now let's see, what we'd like to do is bound

435
00:12:40,166 --> 00:12:45,059
e除N和k除d 好的 我们知道的有什么

436
00:12:40,166 --> 00:12:45,059
the difference of e over N and k over d. Well what do we know?

437
00:12:45,059 --> 00:12:47,872
根据三角不等式 我们知道它等于

438
00:12:45,059 --> 00:12:47,872
By the triangular inequality, we know that this is equal to

439
00:12:47,872 --> 00:12:52,122
e除N次到phi（N)分之e的距离

440
00:12:47,872 --> 00:12:52,122
the distance between e over N and e over phi(N) plus

441
00:12:52,122 --> 00:12:56,566
加phi（N)分之e到k分之d的距离

442
00:12:52,122 --> 00:12:56,566
the distance from e over phi(N) to k over d.

443
00:12:56,566 --> 00:13:01,813
这就是所谓的三角不等式 这只适用于绝对值

444
00:12:56,566 --> 00:13:01,813
This is just what's called a triangular inequality; this is just a property of absolute values.

445
00:13:01,813 --> 00:13:04,705
这里的绝对值 我们已经知道如何定界了

446
00:13:01,813 --> 00:13:04,705
Now this absolute value here, we already know how to bound.

447
00:13:04,705 --> 00:13:07,116
如果你考虑的话 这就是我们已经导出的界

448
00:13:04,705 --> 00:13:07,116
If you think about it it's basically the bound that we've already derived.

449
00:13:07,116 --> 00:13:11,977
所以我们知道这里的绝对值比N的平方根小

450
00:13:07,116 --> 00:13:11,977
So we know that this absolute value here is basically less than 1 over square root of N.

451
00:13:11,977 --> 00:13:17,737
现在我们知道什么关于这个绝对值的了呢 e的N次减e的phi（N）次是什么？

452
00:13:11,977 --> 00:13:17,737
Now what do we know about this absolute value here? What is e over N minus e over phi(N)?

453
00:13:17,737 --> 00:13:20,486
我们同分母化 看我们得到什么

454
00:13:17,737 --> 00:13:20,486
Well let's do common denominators and see what we get.

455
00:13:20,486 --> 00:13:25,236
共同的分母会是N*phi（N)

456
00:13:20,486 --> 00:13:25,236
So the common denominator is going to be N times phi(N),

457
00:13:25,236 --> 00:13:31,253
这里的分子是e*phi（N)-N

458
00:13:25,236 --> 00:13:31,253
and the numerator in this case is going to be e times phi(N) minus N.

459
00:13:31,253 --> 00:13:35,760
我们这里知道 这个表达式比N平方根的3倍小

460
00:13:31,253 --> 00:13:35,760
Which we know from this expression here is less than 3 times square root of N.

461
00:13:35,760 --> 00:13:40,842
所以分子应该取3e倍N平方根

462
00:13:35,760 --> 00:13:40,842
So really what this numerator is going to be is e times 3 square root of N.

463
00:13:40,842 --> 00:13:44,327
分子要比3e倍N平方根

464
00:13:40,842 --> 00:13:44,327
The numerator is going to be less than e times 3 square root of N.

465
00:13:44,327 --> 00:13:51,246
现在我们知道e比phi（N）小 所以我知到e除以phi（N)小于1

466
00:13:44,327 --> 00:13:51,246
So now I know that e is less than phi(N), so I know that e over phi(N) is less than 1.

467
00:13:51,246 --> 00:13:57,313
换句话说 如果我们消掉e和phi（N) 我们只会让分数更大

468
00:13:51,246 --> 00:13:57,313
In other words, if I erase e and I erase phi(N) I've only made the fraction larger.

469
00:13:57,313 --> 00:14:00,016
那么最初的绝对值将

470
00:13:57,313 --> 00:14:00,016
Okay, so this initial absolute value is now going to be

471
00:14:00,016 --> 00:14:03,655
小于N平方根*3除N 这很简单

472
00:14:00,016 --> 00:14:03,655
smaller than 3 square root of N over N, which is simply,

473
00:14:03,655 --> 00:14:09,237
N平方根*3除N就是3除N平方根

474
00:14:03,655 --> 00:14:09,237
3 square root of N over N is simply 3 over square root of N.

475
00:14:09,237 --> 00:14:11,270
那么对3除N平方根我们又知道什么

476
00:14:09,237 --> 00:14:11,270
Okay, but what do we know about 3 over square root of N?

477
00:14:11,270 --> 00:14:17,706
我们知道它比1除N平方根分之负一的2d次

478
00:14:11,270 --> 00:14:17,706
We know that it's less than 1 over 2 d squared minus 1 over square root of N.

479
00:14:17,706 --> 00:14:20,473
这就是我们的推导过程

480
00:14:17,706 --> 00:14:20,473
Okay, so that's the end of our derivation.

481
00:14:20,473 --> 00:14:26,439
所以现在我们知道第一个绝对值小于1除N平方根分之负一的2d次

482
00:14:20,473 --> 00:14:26,439
So now we know that the first absolute value is less than 1 over 2 d squared minus square root of N.

483
00:14:26,439 --> 00:14:29,509
第二个绝对值比N平方根分之一小

484
00:14:26,439 --> 00:14:29,509
The second absolute value is less than 1 over square root of N.

485
00:14:29,509 --> 00:14:34,369
因此他们的和小于2d方分之一

486
00:14:29,509 --> 00:14:34,369
And therefore their sum is less than 1 over 2 d squared.

487
00:14:34,369 --> 00:14:36,576
我希望你们好好看看这个公式

488
00:14:34,369 --> 00:14:36,576
And this is the expression that I want you to stare at.

489
00:14:36,576 --> 00:14:42,951
那么让我稍稍化简 约掉这部分和这部分

490
00:14:36,576 --> 00:14:42,951
So here, let me circle it a little bit. So let me circle this part and this part.

491
00:14:43,582 --> 00:14:46,445
我们注意下这个分式

492
00:14:43,582 --> 00:14:46,445
Now, so let's stare a little bit at this fraction here.

493
00:14:46,445 --> 00:14:51,444
我们首先注意到的 和之前一样 现在我们知道N分之e的值

494
00:14:46,445 --> 00:14:51,444
And what we see is first of all, as before, now we know the value of e over N,

495
00:14:51,444 --> 00:14:54,825
我们想要知道的是d分之k的值

496
00:14:51,444 --> 00:14:54,825
and what we'd like to find out is the value k over d.

497
00:14:54,825 --> 00:14:56,862
但我们对k分之d知道什么呢？

498
00:14:54,825 --> 00:14:56,862
But what do we know about this fraction k over d?

499
00:14:56,862 --> 00:15:00,715
我们知道这两个分式之间的差别很小

500
00:14:56,862 --> 00:15:00,715
We know somehow that the difference of these two fractions is really small;

501
00:15:00,715 --> 00:15:05,385
小于2d平方分之一 这出现很不频繁

502
00:15:00,715 --> 00:15:05,385
it's less than 1 over 2 d squared. Now this turns out to happen very infrequently,

503
00:15:05,385 --> 00:15:10,588
k分之d接近N分之e 那么

504
00:15:05,385 --> 00:15:10,588
that k over d approximates e over N so well that

505
00:15:10,588 --> 00:15:15,307
这两者之间的差距小于k分之d的分母的平方

506
00:15:10,588 --> 00:15:15,307
the difference between the two is less than the square of the denominator of k over d.

507
00:15:15,307 --> 00:15:17,324
这就说明这不可能频繁发生

508
00:15:15,307 --> 00:15:17,324
It turns out that that can't happen very often.

509
00:15:17,324 --> 00:15:22,338
也说明很少有k分之d的分母接近于另一个分母

510
00:15:17,324 --> 00:15:22,338
It turns out that there are very few fractions of the form k over d that approximate another fraction

511
00:15:22,338 --> 00:15:26,422
那么他们之间的差距小于2d方分之一

512
00:15:22,338 --> 00:15:26,422
so well that their difference is less than 1 over 2 d squared.

513
00:15:26,422 --> 00:15:30,308
事实上这样分母的数值最多为N的对数

514
00:15:26,422 --> 00:15:30,308
And in fact the number of such fractions is going to be at most logarithmic in N.

515
00:15:30,308 --> 00:15:33,953
现在还有一个分母算法 这是一个很著名的算法

516
00:15:30,308 --> 00:15:33,953
So now there's a continued fraction algorithm. It's a very famous fraction

517
00:15:33,953 --> 00:15:38,877
简单来说 他做的是 从N分之e的分母

518
00:15:33,953 --> 00:15:38,877
that basically what it will do is, from the fraction e over N,

519
00:15:38,877 --> 00:15:42,977
这会恢复log（N)的k分之d的可能值

520
00:15:38,877 --> 00:15:42,977
it will recover log(N) possible candidates for k over d.

521
00:15:42,977 --> 00:15:47,148
我们一个个尝试 直到我们找到正确的k分之的

522
00:15:42,977 --> 00:15:47,148
So we just try them all one by one until we find the correct k over d.

523
00:15:47,148 --> 00:15:51,645
我们就做完了 因为我们知道

524
00:15:47,148 --> 00:15:51,645
And then we're done. We're done, because we know that,

525
00:15:51,645 --> 00:15:55,376
e乘d模k为1 因此d对k是互素的

526
00:15:51,645 --> 00:15:55,376
well e times d is 1 mod k, therefore d is relatively prime to k,

527
00:15:55,376 --> 00:16:00,852
那么如果我们用k分之d代表合理的分母 你知道 分子除分母

528
00:15:55,376 --> 00:16:00,852
so if we just represent k over d as a rational fraction, you know, numerator by denominator,

529
00:16:00,852 --> 00:16:05,271
分母一定是d 我们就恢复了 你知道

530
00:16:00,852 --> 00:16:05,271
the denominator must be d. And so we've just recovered, you know,

531
00:16:05,271 --> 00:16:10,355
我们会尝试所有可能的log（N)分数接近N分之e

532
00:16:05,271 --> 00:16:10,355
we've tried all possible log(N) fractions that approximate e over N so well

533
00:16:10,355 --> 00:16:13,688
使差距小于2d方分之一

534
00:16:10,355 --> 00:16:13,688
that the difference is less than 1 over 2 d squared.

535
00:16:13,688 --> 00:16:19,338
然后我们看所有这些分式的分母 其中的一个一定是d

536
00:16:13,688 --> 00:16:19,338
And then we just look at the denominator of all those fractions, and one of those denominators must be d.

537
00:16:19,338 --> 00:16:22,841
那么我们就做完了 我们已经恢复了私钥

538
00:16:19,338 --> 00:16:22,841
And then we're done; we've just recovered the private key.

539
00:16:22,841 --> 00:16:26,341
这就是一个漂亮的攻击 这展示了如何

540
00:16:22,841 --> 00:16:26,341
So this is a pretty cute attack. And it shows basically how,

541
00:16:26,341 --> 00:16:31,267
如果私有指数是小的 小于N的四次方根

542
00:16:26,341 --> 00:16:31,267
if the private exponent is small, smaller than the fourth root of N,

543
00:16:31,267 --> 00:16:35,354
那么我们就可以完全恢复d 很简单 好的 就说到这

544
00:16:31,267 --> 00:16:35,354
then we can recover d completely, quite easily. Okay, so I'll stop here.

