1
00:00:00,000 --> 00:00:02,432
In this module, we're gonna stop talking
about encryption,

2
00:00:00,000 --> 00:00:02,432
这一部分我们将不再讨论加密

3
00:00:02,432 --> 00:00:04,415
and instead discuss message integrity.

4
00:00:02,432 --> 00:00:04,415
而讨论消息完整性

5
00:00:04,415 --> 00:00:08,987
然后 我们会再回到加密 展示一下怎么同时提供保密性和完整性

6
00:00:04,415 --> 00:00:08,987
Next, we will come back to encryption, and show
how to provide both encryption and integrity.

7
00:00:08,987 --> 00:00:13,222
如我所言 这里我们的目标是提供不带保密性的完整性

8
00:00:08,987 --> 00:00:13,222
So as I said, our goal here is to provide
integrity without any confidentiality.

9
00:00:13,222 --> 00:00:16,561
实际中 有很多场景是需要这样的体制

10
00:00:13,222 --> 00:00:16,561
There are actually in fact many cases in
the real world where this comes up.

11
00:00:16,561 --> 00:00:19,583
例如 你可能想对你硬盘上的系统文件进行操作

12
00:00:16,561 --> 00:00:19,583
For example, you can think of
operating system files on your disk.

13
00:00:19,583 --> 00:00:24,608
如果你用的是Windows 所有Windows操作系统文件在硬盘上都是没有加密的

14
00:00:19,583 --> 00:00:24,608
Say if you're using Windows, all the Windows
operating system files on disk are not confidential,

15
00:00:24,608 --> 00:00:26,116
它们对整个世界可知

16
00:00:24,608 --> 00:00:26,116
they're public and known to the world,

17
00:00:26,116 --> 00:00:30,883
但是 很重要的一点是要确保它们没有被病毒或者什么恶意软件修改

18
00:00:26,116 --> 00:00:30,883
but it is quite important to make sure that
they're not modified by a virus or some malware.

19
00:00:30,883 --> 00:00:33,760
那就是一个你需要提供完整性但不

20
00:00:30,883 --> 00:00:33,760
That's an example where you want
to provide integrity but you don't

21
00:00:33,760 --> 00:00:38,127
care about confidentiality. Another
example is banner ads on web pages.

22
00:00:33,760 --> 00:00:38,127
关心保密性的例子 另一个例子是网页上的标题广告

23
00:00:38,127 --> 00:00:41,467
The provider of the ads doesn't care
at all if someone copies them

24
00:00:38,127 --> 00:00:41,467
广告供应商不用在意谁拷贝

25
00:00:41,467 --> 00:00:45,128
and shows them to other people.
So there's no confidentiality issue at all.

26
00:00:41,467 --> 00:00:45,128
并给其它人看 所以完全不存在保密的问题

27
00:00:45,128 --> 00:00:47,458
But they do care about modifying those ads.

28
00:00:45,128 --> 00:00:47,458
但是他们确实在意对这些广告的修改

29
00:00:47,458 --> 00:00:52,046
So, for example, they do wanna prevent people from
changing the ads into different types of ads.

30
00:00:47,458 --> 00:00:52,046
比如 他们不希望人们把这些广告改成其它的广告

31
00:00:52,046 --> 00:00:57,814
So that's another example where integrity matters
but confidentiality is not important at all.

32
00:00:52,046 --> 00:00:57,814
所以这是另一个例子 完整性重要但是保密性压根不重要

33
00:00:57,814 --> 00:00:59,940
So how do we provide message integrity?

34
00:00:57,814 --> 00:00:59,940
那么我们怎么提供完整性呢？

35
00:00:59,940 --> 00:01:04,980
The basic mechanism is what's called a MAC,
a message authentication code, MAC.

36
00:00:59,940 --> 00:01:04,980
基本体制是是所谓MAC 消息认证码 MAC

37
00:01:04,980 --> 00:01:08,842
And the way we do it is as follows.
So here we have our friends, Alice and Bob.

38
00:01:04,980 --> 00:01:08,842
我们操作方法如下 我们的两个朋友 Alice和Bob来了

39
00:01:08,842 --> 00:01:13,783
They have a shared key, K, which is not known
to the attacker, but known to both of them.

40
00:01:08,842 --> 00:01:13,783
他们有一个共享密钥k 攻击者不知道 但他两知道

41
00:01:13,783 --> 00:01:16,868
And there's a public message M that Alice
wants to send to Bob,

42
00:01:13,783 --> 00:01:16,868
有个公开的消息M Alice想把M发给Bob

43
00:01:16,868 --> 00:01:21,743
such that an attacker along the way cannot
modify this message on its way to Bob.

44
00:01:16,868 --> 00:01:21,743
但是信道上的攻击者不能修改这个消息

45
00:01:21,743 --> 00:01:27,935
Alice采取的方法是 使用所谓MAC签字算法 我们用S来表示

46
00:01:21,743 --> 00:01:27,935
The way Alice does it, is by using what's called
a MAC signing algorithm, we'll denote it by S,

47
00:01:27,935 --> 00:01:32,558
MAC签字算法以密钥和这个消息作为输入

48
00:01:27,935 --> 00:01:32,558
where the MAC signing algorithm takes
as input the key and the message,

49
00:01:32,558 --> 00:01:37,243
生成一个很短的标签 标签可能是90比特或100比特 或者其它

50
00:01:32,558 --> 00:01:37,243
and produces a very short tag. The tag could
be like 90 bits or 100 bits, or so on.

51
00:01:37,243 --> 00:01:41,905
尽管消息可能是Gb量级的 标签实际上非常非常短

52
00:01:37,243 --> 00:01:41,905
Even though the message is gigabytes long,
the tag is actually very, very short.

53
00:01:41,905 --> 00:01:46,640
那么 她给这个消息价格标签 把这两个合起来发送给Bob

54
00:01:41,905 --> 00:01:46,640
Then, she appends the tag to the message
and sends the combination of the two to Bob.

55
00:01:46,640 --> 00:01:48,790
Bob接受到消息和标签

56
00:01:46,640 --> 00:01:48,790
Bob receives the message and the tag,

57
00:01:48,790 --> 00:01:53,311
他接着对这个标签运行所谓MAC验证算法

58
00:01:48,790 --> 00:01:53,311
and then he runs what's called a MAC
verification algorithm on this tag.

59
00:01:53,311 --> 00:01:56,564
MAC验证算法把这个标签、消息和密钥作为输入

60
00:01:53,311 --> 00:01:56,564
So the MAC verification algorithm takes
as input to the key, the message,

61
00:01:56,564 --> 00:02:01,359
给出是或否 取决于消息是否有效

62
00:01:56,564 --> 00:02:01,359
and the tag and it says basically yes or no,
depending on whether the message is valid

63
00:02:01,359 --> 00:02:05,585
或者是否被篡改过 好 更准确的 什么是MAC？

64
00:02:01,359 --> 00:02:05,585
or whether it's been tampered with.
Okay, so more precisely, what is a MAC?

65
00:02:05,585 --> 00:02:08,401
我们说MAC基本上由两个算法构成

66
00:02:05,585 --> 00:02:08,401
Well, we said the MAC basically consists of
two algorithms,

67
00:02:08,401 --> 00:02:10,766
一个签字算法 一个验证算法

68
00:02:08,401 --> 00:02:10,766
a signing algorithm and a verification algorithm.

69
00:02:10,766 --> 00:02:16,214
和往常一样 他们是定义在一个密钥空间 一个消息空间和一个标签空间上

70
00:02:10,766 --> 00:02:16,214
As usual, they're defined over a key space,
a message space, and a tag space.

71
00:02:16,214 --> 00:02:18,641
就像我们前面说的 这是一对算法

72
00:02:16,214 --> 00:02:18,641
And as we said, it's a pair of algorithms.

73
00:02:18,641 --> 00:02:22,637
签字算法会在标签空间输出一个标签 验证算法

74
00:02:18,641 --> 00:02:22,637
So the signing algorithm will output a
tag in the tag space, and the verification

75
00:02:22,637 --> 00:02:27,536
在已知密钥、消息和标签的情况下 输出是或否

76
00:02:22,637 --> 00:02:27,536
algorithm, basically given the key, the
messages and the tag, will output yes or no.

77
00:02:27,536 --> 00:02:31,770
像往常一样 我要求大家注意一致性要求 就是

78
00:02:27,536 --> 00:02:31,770
And I want to remind you as usual there are
these consistency requirements, such that

79
00:02:31,770 --> 00:02:36,755
对密钥空间的所有k 和消息空间的所有消息

80
00:02:31,770 --> 00:02:36,755
for every K in the key space and for every
message in the message space,

81
00:02:36,755 --> 00:02:41,067
如果我对消息用一个特定的密钥签字

82
00:02:36,755 --> 00:02:41,067
it so happens that if I sign a message
using a particular key,

83
00:02:41,067 --> 00:02:47,364
那么我用同样的密钥对标签进行验证 我应该得到“是”这个结果

84
00:02:41,067 --> 00:02:47,364
and then I verify the tag using the same
key, I shall get yes in response.

85
00:02:47,364 --> 00:02:50,915
这是标准的一致性要求

86
00:02:47,364 --> 00:02:50,915
So this is the standard consistency
requirement which is the analog of

87
00:02:50,915 --> 00:02:54,736
和我们在加密中看到的一样 现在 我想指出的一点是

88
00:02:50,915 --> 00:02:54,736
the one that we saw for encryption.
Now, one thing I'd like to point out is that

89
00:02:54,736 --> 00:02:58,477
完整性必须要求Alice和Bob共享密钥

90
00:02:54,736 --> 00:02:58,477
integrity really does require a shared
key between Alice and Bob.

91
00:02:58,477 --> 00:03:02,121
实际上 人们经常犯同一个错误 他们试图

92
00:02:58,477 --> 00:03:02,121
And, in fact, there's a common mistake
that people make, where they try to

93
00:03:02,121 --> 00:03:05,795
在没有共享密钥的情况下保证完整性 给个例子

94
00:03:02,121 --> 00:03:05,795
provide integrity without actually a
shared key. So here's an example.

95
00:03:05,795 --> 00:03:10,554
考虑一下CRC CRC代表循环冗余校验

96
00:03:05,795 --> 00:03:10,554
So consider CRC. CRC stands for cyclic
redundancy check. This is a classic

97
00:03:10,554 --> 00:03:14,544
这已是个典型的校验和算法 用来检测消息中的随机错误

98
00:03:10,554 --> 00:03:14,544
checksum algorithm that's designed to
detect random errors in messages.

99
00:03:14,544 --> 00:03:19,636
想象一下 不用密钥来生成标签 Alice用无密钥

100
00:03:14,544 --> 00:03:19,636
So imagine, instead of using a key to
generate the tag, Alice basically uses a

101
00:03:19,636 --> 00:03:24,162
的CRC算法来 不用任何密钥 生成标签

102
00:03:19,636 --> 00:03:24,162
CRC algorithm which is keyless. Doesn't
take any key, to generate a tag.

103
00:03:24,162 --> 00:03:27,594
然后她把标签贴在消息上 发给Bob

104
00:03:24,162 --> 00:03:27,594
And then she appends this tag to the
message, she sends it over to Bob,

105
00:03:27,594 --> 00:03:31,984
Bob还用CRC来验证它是不是正确 换句话说

106
00:03:27,594 --> 00:03:31,984
Bob will basically verify that the CRC is
still correct. In other words, Bob will still

107
00:03:31,984 --> 00:03:37,108
Bob仍然验证这个标签等于CRC(m) 就是说

108
00:03:31,984 --> 00:03:37,108
verify the tag is equal to CRC(m).
And if so the verification algorithm

109
00:03:37,108 --> 00:03:40,454
如果相等 验证算法就给出是 不等就给出否

110
00:03:37,108 --> 00:03:40,454
will say yes, and otherwise the
verification algorithm will say no.

111
00:03:40,454 --> 00:03:44,027
这个的问题是 对于攻击者而言非常容易击破

112
00:03:40,454 --> 00:03:44,027
So the problem with this is this is
very easy for an attacker to defeat.

113
00:03:44,027 --> 00:03:48,173
换句话说 攻击者可以非常容易地更改消息 并路由篡改过的消息

114
00:03:44,027 --> 00:03:48,173
In other words, an attacker can very easily
modify the message and route,

115
00:03:48,173 --> 00:03:51,645
并让Bob以为这个新消息是有效的

116
00:03:48,173 --> 00:03:51,645
and fool Bob into thinking that the
new message is a valid one.

117
00:03:51,645 --> 00:03:55,205
攻击者这样做 他把消息中的标签先删掉

118
00:03:51,645 --> 00:03:55,205
The way the attacker will do it
is he'll cancel the message in the tag.

119
00:03:55,205 --> 00:03:58,352
就是屏蔽掉 然后自己生成一个消息 m一撇

120
00:03:55,205 --> 00:03:58,352
He'll simply block them. And then he'll
produce his own message,

121
00:03:58,352 --> 00:04:03,042
计算这个消息m一撇的CRC值

122
00:03:58,352 --> 00:04:03,042
M prime, and compute his own CRC
on this message M prime,

123
00:04:03,042 --> 00:04:06,622
然后串接这两个发给Bob

124
00:04:03,042 --> 00:04:06,622
and then send the concatenation
of the two over to Bob.

125
00:04:06,622 --> 00:04:10,948
Bob就会返回一个验证算法 验证正确

126
00:04:06,622 --> 00:04:10,948
Bob will run the verification algorithm,
verification will work properly because

127
00:04:10,948 --> 00:04:15,856
因为实际上右边的是左边的一个有效的CRC

128
00:04:10,948 --> 00:04:15,856
in fact the right-hand side is in fact
a valid CRC for the left-hand side.

129
00:04:15,856 --> 00:04:19,898
结果是 Bob会认为这个消息来自Alice但是实际上

130
00:04:15,856 --> 00:04:19,898
And as a result, Bob would think that this
message came from Alice but in fact its been

131
00:04:19,898 --> 00:04:24,980
消息已经完全被攻击者篡改了 和Alice发的原始消息没有一点关系

132
00:04:19,898 --> 00:04:24,980
completely modified by the attacker and had
nothing to do with the original message that Alice sent.

133
00:04:24,980 --> 00:04:29,440
好 那么问题是 因为CRC没有密钥 Alice

134
00:04:24,980 --> 00:04:29,440
Okay, so the problem is, because CRC
doesn't have a key, there's no difference

135
00:04:29,440 --> 00:04:34,609
和攻击者没有区别 结果是 Bob不知道消息是从谁发来的

136
00:04:29,440 --> 00:04:34,609
between Alice and the attacker. And as a result,
Bob doesn't know where the message came from.

137
00:04:34,609 --> 00:04:39,579
一旦我们引入密钥 Alice就能做一些攻击者不能做的事

138
00:04:34,609 --> 00:04:39,579
Once we introduce a key, now Alice can do
something that the attacker can't do.

139
00:04:39,579 --> 00:04:44,194
结果是 她能计算出一些攻击者不能篡改的标签

140
00:04:39,579 --> 00:04:44,194
And as a result, she might be able to compute a
tag that the attacker can't modify.

141
00:04:44,194 --> 00:04:50,166
所以 要牢记的是 CRC是设计来检测随机错误的 而不是恶意的错误

142
00:04:44,194 --> 00:04:50,166
So the point to remember is that CRC is designed
to detect random errors, not malicious errors.

143
00:04:50,166 --> 00:04:55,490
现在我们的目标是确保恶意的攻击者不能再信道中篡改消息

144
00:04:50,166 --> 00:04:55,490
And here our goal is to make sure that even a
malicious attacker cannot modify messages in route.

145
00:04:55,490 --> 00:04:59,390
下面我们想对MAC系统的安全性给出定义

146
00:04:55,490 --> 00:04:59,390
So next we want to define what it means
for a MAC system to be secure.

147
00:04:59,390 --> 00:05:04,635
和平时一样 我们从攻击者能力的角度来定义安全性 攻击者能干什么？

148
00:04:59,390 --> 00:05:04,635
So as usual, we define security in terms of the
attacker's power. What can the attacker do?

149
00:05:04,635 --> 00:05:08,842
攻击者的目标 他想干什么 在MAC的情况中

150
00:05:04,635 --> 00:05:08,842
And the attackers goal. What is he trying
to do? So in the case of MACs, the

151
00:05:08,842 --> 00:05:13,699
攻击者的能力被称为选择消息攻击 换句话说

152
00:05:08,842 --> 00:05:13,699
attacker's power is what's called a chosen
message attack. In other words, the

153
00:05:13,699 --> 00:05:19,039
攻击者可一个给Alice任何消息 根据他的选择 m1 mq等等

154
00:05:13,699 --> 00:05:19,039
attacker can give Alice arbitrary
messages of his choice, m<u>1 to m<u>q,</u></u>

155
00:05:19,039 --> 00:05:24,921
Alice会给他计算这些消息的标签 给他这些标签

156
00:05:19,039 --> 00:05:24,921
and Alice will compute the tag for him on
those messages, and give him those tags.

157
00:05:24,921 --> 00:05:28,070
再一次 你可能会问 为什么Alice会这么做？

158
00:05:24,921 --> 00:05:28,070
So again, you might wonder, why
would Alice ever do that?

159
00:05:28,070 --> 00:05:31,796
为什么Alice要计算攻击者给她的消息的标签？

160
00:05:28,070 --> 00:05:31,796
Why would Alice ever compute the tag on a
message that the attacker gave her?

161
00:05:31,796 --> 00:05:35,935
看一下选择消息攻击的场景 其实在现实中很常见

162
00:05:31,796 --> 00:05:35,935
So just like in the case of chosen plaintext
attack, it's very common in the real world,

163
00:05:35,935 --> 00:05:40,276
攻击者可以给Alice一个消息 Alice会计算这个消息的标签

164
00:05:35,935 --> 00:05:40,276
that the attacker can give Alice a message.
Alice will compute the tag on that message,

165
00:05:40,276 --> 00:05:45,803
接着攻击者获得标签 例如 攻击者给Alice发个Email

166
00:05:40,276 --> 00:05:45,803
and then the attacker will obtain the resulting tag.
For example, the attacker might send Alice an email.

167
00:05:45,803 --> 00:05:50,262
Alice可能想把这个email存在硬盘上 为了防止其他人

168
00:05:45,803 --> 00:05:50,262
Alice might want to save the email to
disk in a way that will prevent someone

169
00:05:50,262 --> 00:05:53,441
篡改这个硬盘 她会计算这个消息的标签

170
00:05:50,262 --> 00:05:53,441
from tampering with the disk. So she'll
compute a tag on the message,

171
00:05:53,441 --> 00:05:58,798
并把这个消息和标签都存在这个硬盘上 后来 攻击者偷了Alice的硬盘

172
00:05:53,441 --> 00:05:58,798
and save the message and the tag to disk.
Later on, the attacker might steal Alice's disk.

173
00:05:58,798 --> 00:06:03,385
那么他现在就有了他发给Alice消息的标签

174
00:05:58,798 --> 00:06:03,385
And now he's recovered Alice's tag on the
message that he sends to Alice.

175
00:06:03,385 --> 00:06:07,670
这是真实世界选择消息攻击的例子 这里攻击者

176
00:06:03,385 --> 00:06:07,670
So this is an example of a chosen message
attack in the real world, where the attacker

177
00:06:07,670 --> 00:06:11,497
确实拥有一个他发给Alice的消息的标签

178
00:06:07,670 --> 00:06:11,497
actually obtained a tag on a
message that he gave Alice.

179
00:06:11,497 --> 00:06:15,796
好 攻击者能干什么 基本上 这种选择消息攻击

180
00:06:11,497 --> 00:06:15,796
Okay, so that's what the attacker can do,
basically, this chosen message attack.

181
00:06:15,796 --> 00:06:20,441
那么他的目标是什么？他的目标是是做一种所谓的“存在伪造”

182
00:06:15,796 --> 00:06:20,441
And what is his goal? Well, his goal is to do
something called an existential forgery.

183
00:06:20,441 --> 00:06:26,312
他想做的是生成一些 一些新的有效的消息标签

184
00:06:20,441 --> 00:06:26,312
What he's trying to do is to produce some,
some new valid message tag there.

185
00:06:26,312 --> 00:06:30,984
好 一些消息标签对 和之前

186
00:06:26,312 --> 00:06:30,984
Okay, so some message tag pair
that's different from one of the

187
00:06:30,984 --> 00:06:34,327
他有的那些消息标签对不同

188
00:06:30,984 --> 00:06:34,327
pairs that were given to him during
the chosen message attack.

189
00:06:34,327 --> 00:06:38,788
如果他能这么做 那么我们就说这个系统是不安全的 如果他不能

190
00:06:34,327 --> 00:06:38,788
And if he can do that, then we say that
the system is insecure, and if he can't,

191
00:06:38,788 --> 00:06:42,704
我们就说这个系统是安全的 所以 这里我想强调存在

192
00:06:38,788 --> 00:06:42,704
then we'll say the system is secure.
So I wanna emphasize this existential

193
00:06:42,704 --> 00:06:47,591
伪造意味着攻击者不能生成一对新的消息标签对

194
00:06:42,704 --> 00:06:47,591
forgery means that the attacker cannot
produce a new message/tag pair,

195
00:06:47,591 --> 00:06:52,575
即便这个消息是完全无意义的 你可能又要问了 好

196
00:06:47,591 --> 00:06:52,575
even for a message that's completely gibberish.
And again, you might wonder, well,

197
00:06:52,575 --> 00:06:55,737
为什么我们会关心攻击者会不会对无意义的消息做标签

198
00:06:52,575 --> 00:06:55,737
why do we care if the attacker computes
a tag on a message that's gibberish?

199
00:06:55,737 --> 00:06:57,697
这对攻击者来说没有任何价值

200
00:06:55,737 --> 00:06:57,697
That's not of any value to the attacker.

201
00:06:57,697 --> 00:07:02,220
But we want to build MACs that are
secure under any usage settings.

202
00:06:57,697 --> 00:07:02,220
但是我们想在任何应用场景下构建安全的MAC

203
00:07:02,220 --> 00:07:06,741
And there are, in fact cases where, for example,
you might want to compute an integrity tag on

204
00:07:02,220 --> 00:07:06,741
然后有 实际状况下 比如你可能想计算一个随机秘钥

205
00:07:06,741 --> 00:07:12,517
a random secret key. In which case, even if the
attacker is able to compute a tag on a completely

206
00:07:06,741 --> 00:07:12,517
下的完整标签 在这种情况下 甚至攻击者也能够计算这个完全随机的消息

207
00:07:12,517 --> 00:07:18,365
random message, he might be able to fool
a user into using the wrong secret key.

208
00:07:12,517 --> 00:07:18,365
的标签 他可能能够诱使用户使用错误的秘钥

209
00:07:18,365 --> 00:07:22,422
And as a result we want to make sure that
if the MAC is secure, the attacker can't

210
00:07:18,365 --> 00:07:22,422
因此我们想要确认MAC是否是安全的 攻击者不能

211
00:07:22,422 --> 00:07:26,848
produce a valid tag for any message
whether it's gibberish or sensical.

212
00:07:22,422 --> 00:07:26,848
对任何消息创建合法的标签 不论消息是无用的还是无意义的

213
00:07:26,848 --> 00:07:31,725
Another property that's implied by the security
definition is if the attacker is given some

214
00:07:26,848 --> 00:07:31,725
另一个隐含的安全定义的性质是如果攻击者获得了一些

215
00:07:31,725 --> 00:07:37,691
message tag pair he shouldn't be able to
produce a new tag for the same message.

216
00:07:31,725 --> 00:07:37,691
消息标签对 他不能为同一消息写出新的标签

217
00:07:37,691 --> 00:07:42,456
In other words even though there might be
another tag t´ for the same message m,

218
00:07:37,691 --> 00:07:42,456
换句话说即使消息m可能有另一个标签t´

219
00:07:42,456 --> 00:07:48,099
the attacker given m and t shouldn't be able
to find this new tÂ´ and again you

220
00:07:42,456 --> 00:07:48,099
攻击者得到m和t后不应该有能力找到这个新的t´

221
00:07:48,099 --> 00:07:52,177
might wonder well why do we care the
attacker already has a tag on message M.

222
00:07:48,099 --> 00:07:52,177
这时你可能奇怪为何我们要在乎攻击者已经拥有了消息m的一个标签

223
00:07:52,177 --> 00:07:55,774
Why does it matter if he can produce
another tag for the message M,he already

224
00:07:52,177 --> 00:07:55,774
为什么他能写出另一个消息m的标签这件事很重要 他已经

225
00:07:55,774 --> 00:08:00,672
has one tag. But as we'll see, there are
actually applications where it's really important

226
00:07:55,774 --> 00:08:00,672
有一个标签了 但是正如我们所看到的 很重要的一点是

227
00:08:00,672 --> 00:08:05,689
that the attacker not to be able to produce
a new tag for a previously signed message.

228
00:08:00,672 --> 00:08:05,689
攻击者不能对已经签名的信息产生新的标签

229
00:08:05,689 --> 00:08:09,360
In particular, this will come up when we
combine encryption and integrity.

230
00:08:05,689 --> 00:08:09,360
特别是 它将在我们融合了加密与完整性之后发生

231
00:08:09,360 --> 00:08:13,145
So that we are gonna demand that given
one tag in the message it's impossible

232
00:08:09,360 --> 00:08:13,145
所以我们会要求给出消息的一个标签不可能

233
00:08:13,145 --> 00:08:17,226
to find another tag for the same message.
Okay, so now that we understand the

234
00:08:13,145 --> 00:08:17,226
找到这个消息的另一个标签 好的 所以现在我们清楚了

235
00:08:17,226 --> 00:08:21,703
intuition of what we are trying to achieve, let's
define it as usual using a more precise game.

236
00:08:17,226 --> 00:08:21,703
我们正在努力获得的客观事实 让我们照旧用一个更严谨的游戏来定义它

237
00:08:21,703 --> 00:08:26,180
So here we have two algorithms S and V,
and we have an adversary A,

238
00:08:21,703 --> 00:08:26,180
这里我们有两个算法S和V 而且我们有个对手A

239
00:08:26,180 --> 00:08:29,589
and the game proceess as follows.
The challenger as usual just chooses

240
00:08:26,180 --> 00:08:29,589
然后游戏进行如下 挑战者照例只为MAC

241
00:08:29,589 --> 00:08:34,833
a random key for the MAC and the adversary
basically does his chosen message attack.

242
00:08:29,589 --> 00:08:34,833
选择一个随机秘钥 然后对手基本上根据他选择的消息攻击

243
00:08:34,833 --> 00:08:39,697
So he submits an m1 to the challenger
and receives the tag on that message m1.

244
00:08:34,833 --> 00:08:39,697
所以他提交了一个m1给挑战者随后收到一个m1的标签

245
00:08:39,697 --> 00:08:43,897
Then he submits an m2 to the challenger
and receives a tag on that m2.

246
00:08:39,697 --> 00:08:43,897
然后他提交了一个m2给挑战者随后收到一个m2的标签

247
00:08:43,897 --> 00:08:48,816
And so on and so forth, until, you know,
he submits Q messages to the adversary and

248
00:08:43,897 --> 00:08:48,816
然后如此进行下去 直到 他给对手提交了q条消息然后

249
00:08:48,816 --> 00:08:53,628
receives Q tags on all those messages. So
that's the chosen message attack part.

250
00:08:48,816 --> 00:08:53,628
收到了所有消息的q个标签 所以这就是选定消息攻击的部分

251
00:08:53,628 --> 00:08:57,216
And then the adversary goes ahead and
tries to do an existential forgery.

252
00:08:53,628 --> 00:08:57,216
然后对手继续试着去做一个存在伪造

253
00:08:57,216 --> 00:09:02,321
Namely, he outputs a message tag pair,
a new message tag pair.

254
00:08:57,216 --> 00:09:02,321
也就是说 他输出一个消息标签对 一个新的消息标签对

255
00:09:02,321 --> 00:09:07,704
We say that he wins the game, in other words
b is equal to 1 means that he wins the game if,

256
00:09:02,321 --> 00:09:07,704
我们说这样的话他赢得了这场游戏 换句话说b等于1的意思就是他赢了这个游戏

257
00:09:07,704 --> 00:09:12,196
first of all, the message tag pair that he
outputs is a valid message tag pair,

258
00:09:07,704 --> 00:09:12,196
如果 首先 他输出的这个消息秘钥对是有效的

259
00:09:12,196 --> 00:09:17,593
so the verification algorithm says yes.
And second of all, it's a fresh message tag pair.

260
00:09:12,196 --> 00:09:17,593
所以验证算法通过了 其次 它是一个新的消息标签对

261
00:09:17,593 --> 00:09:21,168
In other words, it's not one of the message
tag pairs that we gave him before.

262
00:09:17,593 --> 00:09:21,168
换句话说 它不是我们之前给过他的消息标签对

263
00:09:21,168 --> 00:09:25,339
In other words we say that the attacker lost
the game. Namely b is equal to zero.

264
00:09:21,168 --> 00:09:25,339
换个角度 我们说攻击者输掉了这场游戏 也就是b等于0

265
00:09:25,339 --> 00:09:30,855
And as usual we say, we define the advantage
of an adversary as the probability that

266
00:09:25,339 --> 00:09:30,855
然后照例我们说 我们定义了一个对手的优势是

267
00:09:30,855 --> 00:09:35,267
the challenger outputs one in this game.
We say that the MAC system is secure

268
00:09:30,855 --> 00:09:35,267
在这场游戏中挑战者输出1的可能性 我们说MAC系统是安全的

269
00:09:35,267 --> 00:09:39,564
if for all efficient adversaries the advantage
is negligible. Okay, in other words,

270
00:09:35,267 --> 00:09:39,564
如果对于所有有能力的对手这个优势都是微不足道的 好的 换句话说

271
00:09:39,564 --> 00:09:43,853
no efficient adversary can win this
game with non negligible probability.

272
00:09:39,564 --> 00:09:43,853
在没有有能力的对手能够以不可忽视的概率赢得这场游戏

273
00:09:43,853 --> 00:09:48,799
Alright, that's our definition of secure MACs,
and our goal is to build secure MACs like this.

274
00:09:43,853 --> 00:09:48,799
好的 这就是我们对于MAC安全性的定义 然后我们的目标是建立像这样的安全的MAC

275
00:09:48,799 --> 00:09:53,529
Before we do that, I wanna ask you two questions.
So the first question is, suppose we have a MAC.

276
00:09:48,799 --> 00:09:53,529
在我们做这件事之前 我要问你两个问题 第一个问题是 假设我们有一个MAC

277
00:09:53,529 --> 00:09:59,154
And it so happens that the attacker can
find two message, m0 and m1,

278
00:09:53,529 --> 00:09:59,154
而且碰巧攻击者能够找到两条消息 m0和m1

279
00:09:59,154 --> 00:10:02,904
that happen to have the same tag
for about half of the keys.

280
00:09:59,154 --> 00:10:02,904
它们碰巧对于一半的秘钥有相同的标签

281
00:10:02,904 --> 00:10:07,505
In other words, if you choose a key at
random with probability one half, the tag

282
00:10:02,904 --> 00:10:07,505
换句话说 如果你按照各半的概率随机选择一个秘钥 m0的

283
00:10:07,505 --> 00:10:12,339
of the message m0 will be the same as the
tag of the message m1. And my question to

284
00:10:07,505 --> 00:10:12,339
标签将会和m1的标签一样 然后我给你的问题是

285
00:10:12,339 --> 00:10:16,072
you is can this be a secure MAC. So I want
to emphasize the attacker doesn't know

286
00:10:12,339 --> 00:10:16,072
这是一个安全的MAC吗？所以我想强调的是攻击者并不知道

287
00:10:16,072 --> 00:10:21,832
what the tag on m0 and m1 is. All he knows
is that the two messages happen to have

288
00:10:16,072 --> 00:10:21,832
m0和m1的标签是什么 他只知道两条消息碰巧有

289
00:10:21,832 --> 00:10:27,559
the same tag with probability one half. So
the question is whether this is a secure MAC.

290
00:10:21,832 --> 00:10:27,559
相同的标签的几率是二分之一 于是问题来了 这是不是一个安全的MAC

291
00:10:27,559 --> 00:10:31,162
So the answer is no, this is not a secure
MAC and the reason is because of

292
00:10:27,559 --> 00:10:31,162
答案是否定的 这不是一个安全的MAC 原因是

293
00:10:31,162 --> 00:10:36,192
the chosen message attack. Essentially the
attacker can ask for the tag on the message

294
00:10:31,162 --> 00:10:36,192
选定消息攻击 本质上攻击者可以请求一个m0的

295
00:10:36,192 --> 00:10:42,665
m0, then he will receive m0, T from the
challenger and in fact T would be a valid

296
00:10:36,192 --> 00:10:42,665
标签 然后他会从挑战者那里收到m0,T 事实上T是一个

297
00:10:42,665 --> 00:10:49,590
tag for message m0 and then what he would
output as his existential forgery is m1, T

298
00:10:42,665 --> 00:10:49,590
m0的有效的标签 然后他要作为存在伪造输出的是m1,T

299
00:10:49,590 --> 00:10:55,330
and you notice that m1, T is different from
m0, T, so this is a valid existential forgery.

300
00:10:49,590 --> 00:10:55,330
然后你发现这个m1,T和m0 T是不同的 所以这是一个有效的存在伪造

301
00:10:55,330 --> 00:10:59,748
And as a result, the attacker wins
the game with advantage one-half.

302
00:10:55,330 --> 00:10:59,748
而作为结果 攻击者在只有一半优势的情况下赢得了这场游戏

303
00:10:59,748 --> 00:11:03,968
So we conclude that this MAC is not secure.
The second question I'd like to ask you, is,

304
00:10:59,748 --> 00:11:03,968
所以我们断定这个MAC是不安全的 我想问的第二个问题是

305
00:11:03,968 --> 00:11:07,378
suppose we have a MAC that happens
to always output a five bit tag.

306
00:11:03,968 --> 00:11:07,378
假设我们有一个MAC碰巧总是输出5比特的标签

307
00:11:07,378 --> 00:11:11,823
In other words, the tag space for this Mac
happens to be {0,1} to the five.

308
00:11:07,378 --> 00:11:11,823
换句话说 这个MAC的标签空间碰巧是{0,1}^5

309
00:11:11,823 --> 00:11:17,680
So for every key and for every message, the
signing algorithm will just output a five bit tag.

310
00:11:11,823 --> 00:11:17,680
所以对于每条消息的每个秘钥来说 签名算法只输出5比特的标签

311
00:11:17,680 --> 00:11:21,949
And the question is, can this MAC be secure?

312
00:11:17,680 --> 00:11:21,949
然后问题是 这个MAC安全吗？

313
00:11:21,949 --> 00:11:26,204
Of course the answer is no, because the
attacker can simply guess the tag.

314
00:11:21,949 --> 00:11:26,204
很显然答案是否定的 因为攻击者可以简单的猜测这个标签

315
00:11:26,204 --> 00:11:28,810
So what he would do is he wouldn't
ask any chosen message attacks.

316
00:11:26,204 --> 00:11:28,810
所以他需要做的就是 并不需要选定消息攻击

317
00:11:28,810 --> 00:11:32,324
All he would do, is he would output
an existential forgery as follows.

318
00:11:28,810 --> 00:11:32,324
他只需要做的 只是输出一个如下的存在伪造

319
00:11:32,324 --> 00:11:39,661
He would just choose a random tag. So
choose a random tag t at random in {0,1}^5,

320
00:11:32,324 --> 00:11:39,661
他只需要选择一个随机的标签 在{0,1}^5的空间中选择一个随机标签

321
00:11:39,661 --> 00:11:45,492
and then he would just output his existential
forgery as say, the message zero and the tag t.

322
00:11:39,661 --> 00:11:45,492
然后他只需要按刚才提到的那样输出他的存在伪造 消息0和标签t

323
00:11:45,492 --> 00:11:52,720
And now with probability of 1/2^5, this
tag will be a valid tag for the message zero.

324
00:11:45,492 --> 00:11:52,720
然后现在有1/2^5的概率 这个标签是对消息0有效的

325
00:11:52,720 --> 00:11:56,974
And so the adversary's advantage is
1/32, which is non-negligible.

326
00:11:52,720 --> 00:11:56,974
所以对手的优势是1/32 这是不可忽略的

327
00:11:56,974 --> 00:12:00,573
So this basically says that tags
can't be too short.

328
00:11:56,974 --> 00:12:00,573
所以它基本上告诉我们 标签不能过短

329
00:12:00,573 --> 00:12:05,759
They have to have some length to them.
And in fact, the typical tag length would be,

330
00:12:00,573 --> 00:12:05,759
他们需要有一定的长度 而且事实上 典型标签的长度会有

331
00:12:05,759 --> 00:12:14,704
say 64 bits. or 96 bits, or 128 bits. Here let's
for example use the tags that are 96 bits long.

332
00:12:05,759 --> 00:12:14,704
例如64比特 或者96比特 或128比特 这里我们以使用96比特的标签为例

333
00:12:14,704 --> 00:12:19,338
If you try to guess the tag for a message
when the tag is 96 bits the probability of

334
00:12:14,704 --> 00:12:19,338
如果你试图去猜测一个96比特的标签的消息 你猜对

335
00:12:19,338 --> 00:12:23,726
guessing it correctly is 1/2^96.
So the adversary's advantage would

336
00:12:19,338 --> 00:12:23,726
的概率是1/2^96 所以对手的优势

337
00:12:23,726 --> 00:12:28,114
just be 1/2^96 which is negligible.
So now that we understand what MACs are,

338
00:12:23,726 --> 00:12:28,114
仅仅是1/2^96 这是微不足道的 所以既然我们已经理解了什么是MAC

339
00:12:28,114 --> 00:12:29,935
I wanna show you a simple application.

340
00:12:28,114 --> 00:12:29,935
我将给你展示一个简单的应用

341
00:12:29,935 --> 00:12:34,193
In particular, let's see how MACs can be
used to protect system files on disk.

342
00:12:29,935 --> 00:12:34,193
特别地说 我们来看一下MAC是如何被用来保护硬盘上的文件的

343
00:12:34,193 --> 00:12:37,831
So imagine that when you install an operating
system, say, when you install Windows on

344
00:12:34,193 --> 00:12:37,831
想象一下你安装了一个操作系统 假如 当你在你的机器上

345
00:12:37,831 --> 00:12:42,179
your machine. One of the things that,
Windows does, is it asks the user for a

346
00:12:37,831 --> 00:12:42,179
安装了Windows 其中一件事 Windows也这么做 是它要求用户提供

347
00:12:42,179 --> 00:12:47,444
password, and then derives a key K from
this password. And then for every file

348
00:12:42,179 --> 00:12:47,444
一个密码 然后从这个密码导出一个秘钥K 然后对于它写到硬盘

349
00:12:47,444 --> 00:12:52,790
that it writes to disk, in this case, the
files would be F1, F2, up to Fn, what the

350
00:12:47,444 --> 00:12:52,790
上的每个文件 在这种情况下 文件可以是F1、F2直到Fn

351
00:12:52,790 --> 00:12:56,123
operating system would do is it
would compute a tag for that file,

352
00:12:52,790 --> 00:12:56,123
操作系统做的就是它会为那个文件计算一个标签

353
00:12:56,123 --> 00:13:01,908
and then store the tag along with the file. So here
it concatenates the tag, to each one of the files.

354
00:12:56,123 --> 00:13:01,908
然后把标签和文件一起保存 所以这里它连接了每个标签和它对应的文件

355
00:13:01,908 --> 00:13:06,326
And then it erases the key K.
So it no longer stores the key K on disc,

356
00:13:01,908 --> 00:13:06,326
然后它删除了秘钥K 所以秘钥K不再被储存在硬盘里

357
00:13:06,326 --> 00:13:10,884
or on memory, or anywhere. Okay, so now
later imagine that the machine gets

358
00:13:06,326 --> 00:13:10,884
或者内存里 或者其他地方 好的 所以想象一下今后机器

359
00:13:10,884 --> 00:13:15,532
infected with a virus and the virus tries
to modify some of the system files.

360
00:13:10,884 --> 00:13:15,532
感染上一个病毒 这个病毒试图修改一些系统文件

361
00:13:15,532 --> 00:13:19,154
The question is whether the user can
detect which files were modified.

362
00:13:15,532 --> 00:13:19,154
问题就是用户是否能够察觉哪些文件被修改了

363
00:13:19,154 --> 00:13:24,270
So here's one way to do it. Basically, the user
would reboot the machine into some clean OS.

364
00:13:19,154 --> 00:13:24,270
所以这里有一个方法 使用一些未被感染的操作系统重新启动机器

365
00:13:24,270 --> 00:13:28,868
Say you reboot from a USB disk or something.
And then, once the machine boots from this

366
00:13:24,270 --> 00:13:28,868
比如你从U盘或者哪里启动 然后 一旦机器从这个未被感染的操作系统

367
00:13:28,868 --> 00:13:34,052
clean OS, the user would supply his password
to this clean running operating system.

368
00:13:28,868 --> 00:13:34,052
启动 用户可以提供他的密码给这个正在运行的未被感染的操作系统

369
00:13:34,052 --> 00:13:37,974
And then this new clean running operating
system would go ahead and check the MAC for

370
00:13:34,052 --> 00:13:37,974
然后这个正在运行的未被感染的操作系统将继续执行并检查每个

371
00:13:37,974 --> 00:13:43,279
each one of the system files. Now, the
fact that the MAC is secure, means that

372
00:13:37,974 --> 00:13:43,279
系统文件的MAC 现在 事实是MAC是安全的 这就意味着

373
00:13:43,279 --> 00:13:49,819
the poor virus couldn't actually create a
new file, let's call it F prime, with a valid tag.

374
00:13:43,279 --> 00:13:49,819
这个可怜的病毒并不能确实地创建一个拥有有效的标签的新文件 我们叫它F'

375
00:13:49,819 --> 00:13:53,928
So it couldn't actually create an
fÂ´, tÂ´. Because, if it could,

376
00:13:49,819 --> 00:13:53,928
所以它实际上不能创建一个fÂ´, tÂ´ 因为 如果它可以

377
00:13:53,928 --> 00:13:58,757
then that would be an existential forgery
on this MAC. And because, well,

378
00:13:53,928 --> 00:13:58,757
它就是在这个MAC中的一个存在伪造 然后因为

379
00:13:58,757 --> 00:14:02,973
the MAC is existentially unforgeable. The
virus couldn't create any F Prime, no

380
00:13:58,757 --> 00:14:02,973
这个MAC是存在不可伪造的 这个病毒不能创建任何F' 不论

381
00:14:02,973 --> 00:14:07,092
matter what the F Prime is. And
consequently, because of the security of

382
00:14:02,973 --> 00:14:07,092
F'是什么 因此 由于MAC的安全性

383
00:14:07,092 --> 00:14:10,829
the MAC, the user will detect all the
files that were modified by the virus.

384
00:14:07,092 --> 00:14:10,829
用户将会发现所有被病毒修改的文件

385
00:14:10,829 --> 00:14:16,104
Now, there's one caveat to that. One thing
that the virus can do. Is actually swap

386
00:14:10,829 --> 00:14:16,104
现在 这里有一个警告 有一件病毒可以做的事 那就是交换

387
00:14:16,104 --> 00:14:22,190
two files. So, for example, he can swap
this file, file F1, with the file F2 here,

388
00:14:16,104 --> 00:14:22,190
两个文件 所以 例如 他可以交换这个文件 文件F1 和这里的文件F2

389
00:14:22,190 --> 00:14:26,364
just literally swap them. So when the
system, or when the user, tries to run

390
00:14:22,190 --> 00:14:26,364
仅仅是照字面意思交换它们 所以当系统 或者用户 尝试打开

391
00:14:26,364 --> 00:14:31,126
file F1, instead they'll be running file
F2. And of course that could cause all

392
00:14:26,364 --> 00:14:31,126
文件F1 作为替代它们会打开文件F2 所以自然这会造成

393
00:14:31,126 --> 00:14:35,475
sorts of damage. And so the way to defend
against that is essentially by placing the

394
00:14:31,126 --> 00:14:35,475
各种各样的损害 所以防范它的方法本质上就是把

395
00:14:35,475 --> 00:14:40,345
file name inside of the MACed area, so in
fact we're computing an integrity check on

396
00:14:35,475 --> 00:14:40,345
文件名放到MAC空间里 所以事实上我们在做一个完整性检查

397
00:14:40,345 --> 00:14:44,658
the file name as well as on the contents
of the file. And as a result, if the virus

398
00:14:40,345 --> 00:14:44,658
就像我们对文件内容所做的一样 结果是 如果病毒

399
00:14:44,658 --> 00:14:48,602
tries to swap two files, the system will
say hey, the file that's located in

400
00:14:44,658 --> 00:14:48,602
试图替换两个文件 系统将会说 嗨 这个位于

401
00:14:48,602 --> 00:14:52,757
position F1 doesn't have the right name
and therefore it will detect that the virus

402
00:14:48,602 --> 00:14:52,757
F1位置的文件没有正确的文件名 然后因此它会发现这个病毒

403
00:14:52,757 --> 00:14:56,859
that did the swap even though the MAC
actually verifies. So it is important to

404
00:14:52,757 --> 00:14:56,859
做了文件替换 虽然MAC确实验证通过了 所以重要的是

405
00:14:56,859 --> 00:15:01,094
remember that MACs can help you defend
against file tampering. Or data tampering

406
00:14:56,859 --> 00:15:01,094
记住MAC可以帮你防范文件被篡改 或者数据被篡改

407
00:15:01,094 --> 00:15:06,403
in general. But they won't help you defend
against swapping of authenticated data,

408
00:15:01,094 --> 00:15:06,403
但是它们并不能帮助你防范已验证数据的替换

409
00:15:06,403 --> 00:15:09,725
and that has to be done by some other
means. Okay, so that concludes our

410
00:15:06,403 --> 00:15:09,725
所以这需要通过其他手段实现 好的 这就是我们

411
00:15:09,725 --> 00:15:13,037
introduction to MACs, and in the next
segment, we'll go ahead and construct our

412
00:15:09,725 --> 00:15:13,037
对MAC入门的总结 在下个部分 我们将继续介绍并构造

413
00:15:13,037 --> 00:15:15,173
first examples of secure MACs.

414
00:15:13,037 --> 00:15:15,173
我们第一个安全MAC的例子

