Over the years many natural cryptographic
constructions were found to be insecure.
In response, modern cryptography was
developed as a rigorous science where
constructions are always accompanied by a
proof of security. The language used to
describe security relies on discreet
probability. In this segment and the next,
I'll give a brief overview of discreet
probability, and I point to this Wiki
books article over here for a longer
introduction. Discrete probability is
always defined over a universe which I'll
denote by u and this universe in our case
is always going to be a finite set. In
fact very commonly our universe is going
to be simply the set of all n bit strings
which here is denoted by zero one to the
n. So for example the set zero one squared
is the set of all two bit strings which
happens to be the string zero, zero, zero
one, One, zero, and one, one. So there are
four elements in this set, and more
generally in the set zero one to the N,
there are two to the N elements. Now a
probability distribution over this
universe U is simply a function which I'll
denote by P, and this function, what it
does, is it assigns to every element in
the universe a number between zero and
one. And this number is what I'll call the
weight or the probability of that
particular element in the universe. Now
there's only one requirement on this
function P, and that is that the sum of
all the weights, sum up to one. That is,
if I sum the probability of all elements X
in the universe, what I end up with is the
number one. So let's look at a very simple
example looking back to our 2-bit
universe. So 0001, ten and eleven And you
can consider the following probability
distribution Which, for example, assigns
to the element 00, the probability one
half. The elements 01, we assign the
probability 1/8th, to ten we assign the
probability one quarter and to eleven we
assign the probability 1/8th. Okay we can
see that if we sum up these numbers in
fact we get one which means that this
probability P is in fact the probability
distributio N. Now what these number mean
is that if I sample from this probability
distribution I'll get the string 00 with
probability one half I'll get the string
01 with probability 1/8th and so on and so
forth. So now that we understand what a
probability distribution is, let's look at
two classic examples of probability
distributions. The first one is what's
called the uniform distribution. The
uniform distribution assigns to every
element in the universe, exactly the same
weight. I'm gonna use U between two bars
to denote the size of the universe U. That
is the number of elements in the universe,
and since we want the sum of all the
weights to sum out to one, and we want all
these weights to be equal, what this means
is that for every element X in the
universe, we assign a probability of one
over U. So in particular if we look at our
example, the uniform distribution and the
set of two [inaudible] strings, would
simply assign one-quarter the weight,
one-quarter to each one of these strings
And clearly that, the sum of all the
weights sums up to one. Well again, what
this means is that if I sample at random
from this distribution, I'll get a uniform
sample across all our 2-bit strings So all
of these 4-bit strings are equally likely
to be sampled by this distribution.
Another distribution that's very common is
what's called a point distribution at the
point X0 And what this point distribution
does is basically it puts all the weight
on a single point, namely X0. So here we
assign to the point X0 all the weight, one
And then to all other points in the
universe, we assign the weight zero And by
the way, I want to point out that this,
inverted, A here should be read as, for
all. So all this says is, that for all X
that are not equal to X zero, the
probability of that X is zero. So again
going back to our example a point
distribution for example, that would put
all its mass on the string 1-0, would
assign probability one to the string 1-0
and zero to all other strings. So now if I
sample from this distribution pretty much
I'm always guaranteed to always sample the
string 1-0 and never sample any of the
other strings. So now we know what a
distribution is, and I just want to make
one last point, and that is that because
this universe U is always gonna be a
finite set up for us, we can actually
write down the weights that the
distribution assigns to every element in
U, and represent the entire distribution
as a vector. So, here for example, if you
look at the universe of an all 3-bit
strings, we can literally write down the
ways that the distribution assigns to the
string 000, then the way that distribution
assigns to the string 001 And so on, and
so forth. We you can see that we can write
this as a vector, in this case it will be
a vector of dimension eight, there will
be, there are eight strings of 3-bits as a
result basically the entire distribution
is captured by this vector of eight real
numbers, in the range of all zero to one.
The next thing I wanna do is define the
concept of an event. So consider a subset
A of our universe And I, I'll define the
probability of the subsets to be simply
the sum of the weights of all the elements
in the set A. In other words, I'm summing
over all X and A, the weights of these
elements X in the set A, Now because the
sum over the entire universe of all
weights needs to be one. This means that
if we sum, well if you look at the
probability of the entire universe,
basically we get one. And if we look at
the probability of a subset of the
universe, we're gonna get some number in
the interval zero to one And we say that
the probability of this set A, is the sum
which is a number between zero and one.
And I'll tell you that a subset A of the
universe is called an event. And the
probability of the set A is called the
probability of that event. So let's look
at a simple example. So suppose we look at
the universe u, which consists of all
8-bit strings, right? So the size of this
universe u is 256 because there are 256
8-bit strings. Essentially we're looking
at all byte values, all 256 possible byte
values. Now let's define the following
event. Basically the event is gonna
contain all bytes so all [inaudible]
extremes in the universe such that the two
least significant bits of the byte happens
to be eleven So for example, if we look at
01011010 that's an element in the universe
that's not in the set A, but if we choose
a zero to a one. Then that's an element of
the universe which gives in our set A. And
now let's look at the uniform distribution
over the universe U and let me ask you
what is the probability of the, of the
event A? So what is the probability that
when we choose a random byte, the two
least significant bits of that byte
happens to be one, one? Well the answer is
one-fourth, and the reason that's true is
because it's not too difficult to convince
yourself that of the 256 eight bit
strings, exactly 64 of them, one quarter
of them, end in one, one. And the
probability of each string is, we're
looking at the uniform distribution or
probability of each string is exactly one
over the size of the universe, mainly one
over 256. And the product of these, you
know, 64 elements, each one has weight one
over 256 is exactly one-fourth, which is
the probability of the event A that we're
looking at. So a very simple bound on the
probability of events is called the union
bound. So imagine we have two events a1
and a2. So these are both subsets of some
universe U Snd we wanna know what is the
probability that either A1 occurs, or A2
occurs In other words, what is the
probability of the union of these two
events? This little U here denotes the
union of the two sets. So the union bound
tells us that the probability that either
A1 occurs or A2 occurs is basically less
than the sum of the two probabilities. And
that's actually quite easy to see. So
simply look at this picture here, you can
see that when we look at, at the sum of
the two probabilities, we're basically
summing the probability of all the
elements in A1, all the elements in A2 And
you realized, we kind of double-summed
these elements in the intersec tion. They
get summed twice here on the right hand
side And as a result, the sum of the two
probabilities is going to be larger or
larger than or equal to, the actual
probability of the union of A1 and A2. So
that's the classic union bound And in fact
I'll tell you that if the two events are
disjoint, in other words they're
intersection is empty, in that case if we
look at the sum, at the probability that
either A-1 or A02 happens, that's exactly
equal to the sum of the two probabilities.
Okay? So we'll use these facts here and
there throughout the course. So just to be
clear, the inequality holds always But
when the two events are disjoint, then in
fact we get an equality over here. So
let's look at a simple example. Suppose
our, event A1 is the set of all n-bit
stings that happen to end in 1-1 And
suppose A2 is the set of all n-bit strings
that happen to begin with 1-1. Okay, so N
thinks of it as H or some large number and
I'm asking that what is the probability
that either a one happens or a two
happens, In other words if I sample
uniformly from the universe U, what is the
probability that either the least
significant bits are one, one or the most
significant digits are one, one. Well as
we said that's basically the probability
of the union of A1 and A2. We know that
the probability of each one of these
events is one-quarter by what we just did
previous slide And therefore by the union
[inaudible] the probability of the
[inaudible]. Is, you know, a quarter of
the probability of A1, plus the
probability of A2, which is a quarter plus
a quarter. And we just proved that the
probability of seeing 1-1 in the most
significant bit, or 1-1 least significant
bit, is less than one-half. So that's a
simple example of how we might go about
using the Union Bound to bound the
probability that one of two events might
happen. The next concept we need to
define, is what's called a random
variable. Now, random variables are fairly
intuitive objects. But unfortunately the
formal definition of a random variable can
be a little c onfusing. So what I'll do
is, I'll give an example, and hopefully
that will be clear enough. So formally, a
random variable denoted say, by X. Is a
function, from the universe into some set
V And we say that this set V is where the
random variable takes its values. So let's
look at a particular example. So suppose
we have a random variable x And this
random variable maps into the set 01. So
the values of this random variable are
going to be either zero or one. So, one
bit, basically. Now, this random variable
maps our universe, which is the center of
all end bit binary strings, 01 to the end
And how does it do it? Well, given a
particular sample in the universe, a
particular end-bit string y. What the
random variable will do is simply output
the least significant bit of y And that's
it. That's the whole random variable. So,
now let me ask you. Suppose we look at a
uniform distribution on the set zero one
to the end. Let me ask you what is the
probability that this random variable
output zero and what is the probability
that a random variable outputs one? Well
you can see that the answers are half and
half. Well let's just lead them through
why that's the case. So here we have a
picture showing the universe and the
possible alpha space. And so in this case
the variable can output a zero or a one.
When there is a variable output zero,
there is a variable output zero when the
sample in the universe happens to be, to
have its least inefficient [inaudible] bid
be set to zero. In variable one, output
one When the sample in the universe
happens to have its least significant bit
set to one. Well, if choose strings
uniformly at random, the probability that
we choose a string that has its least
significant bits set to zero is exactly
one half Which the random variable output
zero with a probability of exactly
one-half. Similarly, if we choose a random
end-bit string, the probability that the
least significant bit is equal to one is
also one-half. And so we say that the
random variable output's one, also with
exactly proba bility of one-half. Now,
more generally, if we have a random
variable taking values in a certain set v,
then this random variable actually induces
a distribution on this set v. And here, I
just wrote a, kind of a, in symbols, what
this distribution means But it's actually
very easy to explain. Essentially, what it
says is that the variable outputs v
Basically, with the same probability that
if we sample a random element in the
universe, and, and then we apply the
function x. We ask, how likely is it that
the output is actually=to v? So formally
we say that the probability that X outputs
V, is the same as the probability of the
event That when we sample a random element
in the universe, we fall into the pre
image of V under the function X And again,
if this wasn't clear, it's not that
important. All you need to know is that a
random variable takes values in a
particular set V, and in, induces a
distribution on that set V. Now there's a
particularly important random variable
called a uniform random variable. And it's
basically defined as you would expect. So
let's say that U is some fine [inaudible]
set For example the set of all N bit
binary strings, and we're gonna denote a
random variable R that's basically
sample's uniformly from the set U by this
little funny arrow with a little R on top
of it. In this, again the notes that the
random variable R is literally a uniform
random variable sampled over the set U. So
in symbols what's this means is that for
all elements A in the universe, the
probability that R is equal to A is simply
R one over U. And if you want to stick to
the formal definition of a, of a uniform
variable, it's not actually that important
But I would just say that formally the
uniform random variable is an identity
function namely R [inaudible] is equal to
X for all X in the universe So just to see
that this is clear, let me ask you a
simple puzzle. Suppose we have a uniform
random variable over 2-bit strings, so
over the set, 01, ten, one and now, let's
define a new random variable X to basicall
y sum the first and second bits of R. That
is, X simply is the sum of R1 and R2, the
first and second bits of R, treating those
bits as integers. So, for example, if, r
happens to be 00, then x will be zero+0,
which is zero. So let me ask you, what is
the probability that x is = to two? So
it's not difficult to see that the answer
is exactly, one-fourth because, basically
the only way that x is equal to two is if
r happens to be 1,1 but the probability
that r is equal to 1,1 is basically
one-fourth because r is uniform over the
set of all two bit stings. The last
concept I want to define in this segment
is what's called a randomized algorithm.
So I'm sure you're all familiar with
deterministic algorithms. These are
algorithms that basically take a
particular, input data, as input, and they
always produce the same output, say Y. So
if we run the algorithm a hundred times on
the same input, we'll always get the same
output. So you can think of a
deterministic algorithm as a function that
given a particular input data, M, will
always produce exactly the same output, A
of M. A randomized algorithm is a little
different, in that, as before, it takes
the [inaudible] and as input, but it also
has an implicit argument called R, where
this R is sampled anew every time the
algorithm is run. And in particular this R
is sampled uniformly at random from the
set of all N-bit strings, for some
arbitrary end. Now what happens is every
time we run the algorithm on a particular
input M we're gonna get a different output
because a different R is generated every
time. So the first time we run the
algorithm we get one output. The second
time we run the algorithm a new R is
generated and we get a different output.
The third time we run the algorithm a new
R is generated and we get a third output
and so on. So really the way to think
about a randomized algorithm is it's
actually defining a random variable.
Right? So given a particular input
message, M, it's defining a random
variable which is, defining a distribution
over the set of a [laugh] possible outputs
of this algorithm, given the input, M. So
the thing to remember is that the output
of a randomized algorithm changes every
time you run it And in fact, the algorithm
defines a distribution and the set of all
possible outputs. So let's look at a
particular example. So suppose we have a
randomized algorithm that takes as input a
message M And of course it also takes an
implicate input which is this random
string that is used to randomize its
operation. So now what the algorithm will
do is simply will encrypt the message M
using the random string as input. So this
basically defines a random variable. This
random variable takes values that are
encryptions of the message M And really
what this random, random variable is it's
a distribution over the set of all
possible encryptions of the message M
under a uniform key. So the main point to
remember is that even though the inputs to
a randomized algorithm might always be the
same every time you run the randomized
algorithm you're gonna get a different
output. Okay So, that concludes this
segment, and we'll see a bit more discrete
probability in the next segment.