Now that we understand chosen plaintext
security, let's build encryption schemes
that are chosen plaintext secure. And the
first such encryption scheme is going to
be called cipher bock chaining. So here
is how cipher block chaining works.
Cipher block chaining is a way of using a
block cipher to get chosen plaintext
security. In particular, we are going to
look at a mode called cipher block chaining
with a random IV. CBC stands for cipher
block chaning. So suppose we have a block
cipher, so EB is a block cipher. So now
let's define CBC to be the following
encryption scheme. So the encryption
algorithm when it's asked to encrypt a
message m, the first thing it's going to do
is it's going to choose a random IV that's
exactly one block of the block
cipher. So IV is one cypher block.
So in the case of AES the IV
would be 16 bytes. And then we're
gonna run through the algorithm here, the
IV basically that we chose is gonna be XORed
to the first plain text
block. And then the result is gonna be
encrypted using the block cipher and
output of the first block of the ciphertext.
And now comes the chaining part
where we actually use the first block of
the ciphertext to kind of mask the second
block of the plaintext. So we XOR
the two together and the encryption of
that becomes the second ciphertext block.
And so on, and so on, and so forth. So
this is cIpher block chaining, you can
see that each cIpher block is chained and
XORed into the next plaintext
block, and the final ciphertext is going to
be essentially the IV, the initial IV
that we chose along with all the ciphertext blocks. I should say that IV stands
for Initialization Vector. And we're going to
be seeing that term used quite a bit,
every time we need to pick something at
random at the beginning of the encryption
scheme typically we'll call that an IV
for initialization vector. So you notice
that the cIphertext is a little bit
longer than the plain text because we had
to include this IV in the cIphertexts
which basically captures the randomness
that was used during encryption. So the
first question is how do we decrypt the
results of CBC encryption, and so
let me remind you again that if when we
encrypt the first message block we
XOR it with the IV, encrypt the
result and that becomes the first ciphertext
block. So let me ask you how would
you decrypt that? So given the first
ciphertext block, how would you recover
the original first plaintext block? So
decryption is actually very similar to
encryption, here I wrote down the
decryption circuit, you can see basically
it's almost the same thing except the XOR
is on the bottom, instead of on the top, and
again you realize that essentially we
chopped off the IV as part of the
decryption process and we only output the
original message back, the IV is dropped
by the decryption algorithm. Okay, so the
following theorem is going to show that in
fact CBC mode encryption with a random IV
is in fact semantically secure under a
chosen plaintext attack, and so let's
take that more precisely, basically if we
start with a PRP, in other words, our
block cipher E, that is defined over a
space X, then we are gonna to end up with
a encryption algorithm Ecbc that takes
messages of length L and outputs
ciphertexts of length L+1. And then
suppose we have an adversary that makes q
chosen plaintext queries. Then we can
state the following security fact, that
for every such adversary that's attacking
Ecbc, to exist an adversary that's
attacking the PRP, the block cipher, with
the following relation between the two
algorithms, in other words, the advantage
of algorithm A against the encryption scheme
is less than the advantage of algorithm B
against the original PRP plus some noise
term. So let me interpret this theorem for
you as usual, so what this means is that
essentially since E is a secure PRP this
quantity here is negligible, and our goal
is to say that adversary A's advantage is
also negligible. However, here we are
prevented from saying that because we got
this extra error term. This is often
called an error term and to argue that CBC
is secure we have to make sure that the
error term is also negligible. Because if
both of these terms on the right are
negligible, there sum is negligible and
therefore the advantage of A against Ecbc
would also be negligible. So this says
that in fact for Ecbc to be secure it has better
be the case that q squared L squared Is
much, much, much smaller than the value X,
so let me remind you what q and L are, so
L is simply the length of the messages
that we're encrypting. Okay, so L could be
like say a 1000, which means that we are
encrypting messages that are at most 1000
AES blocks. q is the number of ciphertexts
that the adversary gets to see under the
CPA attack, but in real life what q is, is
basically the number of times that we have
used the key K to encrypt messages, in other
words if we use a particular AES key to
encrypt 100 messages, Q would be 100.
It is because the adversary would then see
at most 100 messages encrypted under this key K. Okay
so lets see what this means in the real
world. So here I've rewrote the error
balance from the theorem. And just to remind
you to use the messages encrypted with K
and L with the lengths of the messages and so
suppose we want the adversary's advantage
to be less than one over two to the thirty
two. This means that the error term had
better be less than one over two to the
thirty two. Okay, so let's look at AES and see
what this mean. For AES, AES of course uses
128 bit blocks, so X is going to be two
to the 128, the
size of X is going to be 2 to the
128, and if you
plug this into the expression you see that
basically the product q times L had
better be less than two to the forty eight.
This means that after we use a particular
key to encrypt 2 to the 48 AES
blocks we have to change the key. Okay, so
essentially CBC stops being secure after
the key is used to encrypt 2 to the 48  different AES blocks.
So its
kinda nice that the security theorem tells
you exactly how long the key can be used
and then how frequently, essentially, you have to
replace the key. Now interestingly if you
apply the same analogy to the 3DES it
actually has a much shorter block, maybe
only 64 bits, you see the key has to be
changed much more frequently, maybe after every
65 thousand DES blocks, essentially you need to generate a new key. So
this is one of the reasons why AES has a
larger block size so that in fact modes
like CBC would be more secure and one can
use the keys for a longer period of time, before having
to replace it. What this means is having
to replace two to the sixteen blocks,
each block of course is 8 bytes, so
after you encrypt about half a megabyte of
data you would have to change the DES key
which is actually quite low. And you
notice with AES you can encrypt quite a
bit more data before you have to change the
key. So I want to warn you about a very
common mistake that people have made when
using CBC with a random IV. That is that
the minute that the attacker can predict
the IV that you're going to be using for
encrypting a particular message decipher
this Ecbc is no longer CPA secure. So when
using CBC with a random IV like we've
just shown It's crucial that the IV is not
predictable. But lets see an attack. So
suppose it so happens that given a
particular encryption in a message that
attacker can actually predict that IV that
will be used for the next message. Well
let's show that in fact the resulting
system is not CPA secure. So the first thing the
adversary is going to do is, he is going
to ask for the encryption of a one block
message. In particular that one block is
going to be zero. So what the adversary
gets back is the encryption of one
block, which namely is the encryption of
the message namely zero, XOR the IV. Okay
and of course the adversary also gets the
IV. Okay so now the adversary by
assumption can predict the IV that's gonna
be used for the next encryption. Okay so
let's say that IV is called, well IV. So
next the adversary is going to issue his
semantic security challenge and the
message m0 is going to be the predicted IV
XOR IV1 which was used in the encryption
of c1. And the, the message of m1 is just
going to be some other message, it doesn't
really matter what it is. So now let's see
what happens when the adversary receives
the result of the semantic security
challenge. Well, he is going to get the
encryption of m0 or m1. So when the
adversary receives the encryption of m0,
tell me what is the actual plain text
that is encrypted in the ciphertext c?
Well so the answer is that what is
actually encrypted is the message which is
IV XOR IV1 XOR the IV that's used to
encrypt that message which happens to be
IV and this of course is IV1. So when the
adversary receives the encryption of m0,
he is actually receiving the block cipher
encryption of IV1. And lo and behold,
you'll notice that he already has that
value from his chosen plaintext query.
And then, when he is receiving the
encryption of message m1, he just received
a normal CBC encryption of the message m1.
So you realize that now he has a simple
way of breaking the scheme, namely what
he'll do is he'll say, he's gonna ask, "Is the second
block of the ciphertext c equal to the
value that I received in my CPA query?" If
so I'll say that I received the encryption
of m0, otherwise I'll say that I received
the encryption of m1. So really his test
is c1 he refers to the second block
of c and c11 refers to the second block of
c1, if the two are equal he says zero,
otherwise he says one. So the advantage of
this adversary is going to be 1 and as a
result, he completely breaks CPA security
of this CBC encryption. So the lesson here
is, if the IV is predictable then, in
fact, there is no CPA security and
unfortunately, this is actually a very
common mistake in practice. In particular
even in SSL protocol and in TLS 1.1, it turns
out that IV for record number I is in fact
the last ciphertext block of record I-1. That means that exactly given
the encryption of record I-1, the
adversary knows exactly what IV is going
to be used as record number I. Very
recently, just last summer, this was
actually converted into a pretty
devastating attack on SSL. We'll describe
that attack once we talk about SSL in more
detail, but for now I wanted to make sure
you understand than when you use CBC encryption,
its absolutely crucial that the IV be random.
Okay, so now I going to show you the nonce based version of CBC encryption
So in this mode the IV is replaced by non random but unique nonce
for example the numbers 1,2,3,4,5, could all be used as a nonce, and now, the appeal of this mode
is that if the recipient actually knows
what the nonce is supposed to be
then there's no reason to include the nonce
in the ciphertext, in which case, the ciphertext
is exactly the same length as the plaintext,
unlike CBC with the random IV,
where we had to expand the ciphertext to include the IV, here, if the nonce is already known to the recipient,
there's no reason to include it in the ciphertext, and
the ciphertext is exactly the same length as the plaintext.
So it's perfectly fine to use a non-random but unique nonce. However, it's absolutely crucial to know that,
if you do this, there's one more step that you have
to do before you use the nonce in the CBC chain.
In particular, in this mode now we're going to
be using two independent keys, k and k1.
The key k is, as before, going to be used to
encrypt the individual message blocks,
However, this key k1 is going to be used to
encrypt the non-random but unique nonce,
so that the output is going to be a random IV,
which is then used in the CBC chain.
So this extra step here, encrypting the nonce
with the key k1, is absolutely crucial.
Without it, CBC mode encryption would not be secure.
However it if is going to be a counter you
need to do one more step. Before actually
encryption CBC and in particular you have
to actually encrypt the notes to obtain
the IV that will actually be used for
encryption. The notes on CBC is similar to
a random IV, the difference is that the
notes is first encrypted and the results
is that the IV is used in the CBC
encryption Now the beauty of this mode is
that the Nance doesn't necessarily have to
be included in the cipher text. It only
needs to be in there if its unknowns are
the decrypter but it if the decrypter
happens to already know the value of the
counter by some other means then in fact
the cipher text is only as big as the
plain text. There's no extra value
transmitted in the cipher text. And again,
I warn that when you're using non spaced
encryption, it's absolutely crucial that
the key common Nance spare is only used
for one message so for every message,
either the Nance has changed or the key
has changed. Okay, so here emphasize the
fact that you need to do this extra
encryption step before actual using the
Nance. This is very common mistake that
actually forgotten in practice and for
example in TLS, this was not done and as a
result there was a significant attack
against CBC encryption in TLS. Remember
the reason that this is so important to
know is that in fact many crypto APIs are
set up to almost deliberately mislead the
user to using CBC incorrectly. So let's
look to see how CBC implemented inside of
open SSL. So here are the arguments of the
function. Basically this is the plain
text, this is the place where the cipher
text will get written to. This is the
length of the plain text. This is a, a Yes
key Finally there is an argument here that
says whether you are crypting or
decrypting. And the most important
parameter that I wanted to point out here
is the actual IV and unfortunately, the
user is asked to supply this IV and the
function uses the IV directly in the CBC
encryption mechanism. It doesn't encrypt
the IV before using it and as a result, if
you ever call this function using a non
random IV, the resulting encryption system
won't be CPA secure. Okay, so it's very
important to know that when calling
functions like this. Cbc encryption or
open SSL either supply a truly random IV
or if you want the IV to be a counter than
you have to encrypt a counter using AAS
before you actually call a CBC encrypt and
you have to that yourself. So again, it's
very important that the programmer knows
that it needs to be done otherwise the CBC
encryption is insecure. One last
technicality about CBC is what to do when
the message is not a multiple of the block
cipher block length? That is what do we do
if the last message block is shorter than
the block length of AES, for example? So
the last message block is less than
sixteen bytes. And the answer is if we add
a pad to the last block so it becomes as
long as sixteen bytes, as long as the AES
block size. And this pad, of course, if
going to be removed during encryption. So
here is a typical path, this is the path
that is used in TLS. Basically a pad with
N bytes then essentially what you do is
you write the number N, N times. So for
example if you pad with five bytes, you
pad with the string 555555. So five bytes
where each byte is the value five. And the
key thing about this pad is basically when
the decrypter receives the message, what
he does is he looks at the last byte of
the last block. So suppose that value is
five, then he simply removes the last five
bytes of the message. Now the question is
what do we do if in fact the message is a
multiple of sixteen bytes so in fact no
pad is needed? If we don't pad at all,
well that's a problem because the
decrypter is going to look at the very
last byte of the last block which is not
part of the actual message and he's going
to remove that many bytes from the plain
text. So that actually would be a problem.
So the solution is, if in fact there is no
pad that's needed, nevertheless we still
have to add a dummy block. And since we
add the dummy block this would be a block
that's basically contains sixteen bytes
each one containing the number sixteen.
Okay, so we add essentially sixteen dummy
blocks. The decrypter, that when he's
decrypting, he looks at the last byte of
the last block, he sees that the value is
sixteen, therefore he removes the entire
block. And whatever's left is the actual
plain text. So it's a bit unfortunate that
in fact if you're encrypting short
messages with CBC and the messages happen
to be, say, 32 bytes, so they are a
multiple of sixteen bytes, then you have
to add one more block and make all these
ciphertexts be 48 bytes just to
accommodate the CBC padding. I should
mention there's a variant of CBC called
CBC with ciphertext stealing that actually
avoids this problem, but I'm not gonna
describe that here. If you're interested
you can look that up online. Okay, so
that's the end of our discussion of CBC
and in the next segment we'll see how to
use counter modes to encrypt multiple
messages using a single key.