So as our first example lets look at a
very simple way of using a block cipher
for encryption. In particular we'll see
how to use a block cipher with a one time
key. So in this segment we're just gonna
use the block cipher to encrypt using keys
that are used one time. In other words,
all the adversary gets to see is one ciphertext,
and its goal is to break semantic
security of that ciphertext. Now, in the
next segment, we're going to turn into
more, interesting applications of block
ciphers and we're going to see how to
encrypt using keys that are used many,
many times to encrypt many messages. So
before we start, I want to mention that
there's like a classic mistake in using a
block cipher. Unfortunately, there are some
products that actually work this way, and
they are badly broken, so I want to make
sure that none of you guys actually make
this mistake. So this mode of operation is
called an electronic code book. And it
works as follows: it's the first thing
that comes to mind when you want to use a
block cipher for encryption. What we do is
we take our message, we break it into
blocks, each block as big as the block's
cipher block. So in the case of AES, we
would be breaking our message into sixteen
byte blocks. And then we encrypt each
block separately. So this mode is often
called electronic codebook. And,
unfortunately, it's terribly insecure
because you realize if two blocks are
equal, for example here, these two blocks
happen to be equal, then necessarily the
resulting ciphertext is also going to be equal.
So an attacker who looks at the
ciphertext, even though he might not know
what's actually written in these blocks,
we'll know that these two blocks are
equal. And as a result, he learned
something about the plaintext that he
shouldn't have learned. And if this isn't
clear enough for you abstractly, the best
to explain this is using a picture. And so
here's this guy here that, you know, has
this really dark black hair. And when we
encrypt. This image, this bitmap image
using the electronic code book mode. You
see that his hair, that contains lots of
ones. Basically always gets encrypted the
same way, so that his silhouette,
actually, is completely visible, even in
the encrypted data. Okay, so this is a
nice example of how the electronic code
book mode can actually leak information
about the plaintext that could tell
something to the attacker. So the question
is, how to correctly use block ciphers to
encrypt long messages. And so, I just
want to briefly remind you of the notion
we're trying to achieve, which is
basically semantic security using a one
time key. So the adversary outputs two
messages, m0 and m1, and then he gets
either the encryption of m0 or the
encryption of m1, these are two different
experiments. And then our goal is to say
that the adversary can't distinguish
between these two experiments. So you
can't distinguish the encryption of m0
from the encryption of m1. And the reason
we call this security for a one time key
is that the key is only used to encrypt a
single message. And as a result, the
adversary will ever only see one ciphertext
encrypted using this key. Okay, so
the first thing we want to show is that in
fact the mode we just looked at,
electronic code book, in fact, is not
semantically secure. And this is true as
long as you're encrypting more than one
block. So here's an example. Suppose we
encrypt two blocks using a block cipher.
Let me show you that in fact electronic
code book will not be secure. So here's
what we would do. So we're the adversary.
So we would output two messages, m0 and
m1, where, in one message, the blocks are
distinct, and in the other message, the
blocks are the same. The two blocks are
equal to one another. Well, so what is the
challenger gonna do? The challenger's
going to encrypt either m0 or m1.
Either way we are gonna get two blocks
back. So the ciphertext actually contains two
blocks. The first block is going to be an
encryption of the word "Hello" and the
second block is gonna be either an
encryption of the word "Hello" or the word
"World". And if the two ciphertext blocks
are the same then the adversary knows that
he received an encryption of the message
"Hello Hello" and as a difference he knows
that he received encryption of the
message "Hello World". Okay? So, he just
follows a simple strategy here. And if you
think about it for a second, you'll see
what his advantage is. So, what is the
advantage? Well, this adversary when he
received an encryption of the message
m1 he will always output 0.
and when he receives an encryption of
the message m0 it will always output 1.
And because of that the advantage,
basically, is 1, which means that the
scheme is not secure, which again shows you
the electronic code book is not
semantically secure and should never ever
be used to encrypt messages that are more
than one block long. So, what should we
do? Well, so here's a simple example. What
we could do is we could use what's called
a deterministic counter mode. So in a
deterministic counter mode, basically we
build a stream cipher out of the block
cipher. So suppose we have a PRF, F. So
again you should think of AES when I say
that. So AES is also a secure PRF. And
what we'll do is, basically, we'll evaluate
AES at the point zero, at the point one,
at the point two, up to the point L. This
will generate a pseudo random pad. And I
will XOR that with all the message
blocks and recover the ciphertext as a
result. Okay, so really this is just a
stream cipher that's built out of a PRF,
like AES and triple DES, and it's a simple
way to do encryption. I wanted to just
very quickly show you the security
theorem. In fact, we've already seen the
security theorem when it applied to stream
ciphers using pseudo-random generators, so
I'm not going to repeat this again. I'll
just remind you that essentially for every
adversary A that's trying to attack
deterministic counter mode, we prove that
there's an adversary B that's trying to
attack the PRF. And since this quantity is
negligible, because the PRF is secure, we
obtain that this quantity is negligible.
And therefore, the adversary has
negligible advantage in defeating
deterministic counter mode. And the
proof in pictures is a really simple
proof. So I'll just show it to you one
more time for completeness. So basically,
what we want to show is, when the
adversary's given the encryption of the
message m0, here, this is the encryption
of the message, m0. m0 XOR counter
applied to the PRF, versus in giving the
encryption of the message, m1. We wanna
argue these two distributions are
computationally indistinguishable. So the
way we do that is basically we say, well
the top distribution, if instead of a PRF,
we use a truly random function, namely
here f is a truly random function, then
the adversary, because of the property of
the PRF, the adversary cannot distinguish
these two experiments, right. A PRF is
indistinguishable from a truly random
function, therefore when we replace the PRF
on the left with a truly random function
on the right, the adversary is going to
behave the same. Basically you can't
distinguish these two distributions. But
now because F is a truly random function,
the pad here is a truly one time pad, and
therefore no adversary can distinguish an
encryption of m0 from an encryption of m1
under the one time pad. So, again, these
two distributions are the same. In fact,
here there's an actual equality. These two
distributions literally are the same
distribution. And similarly again when we
go back from a truly random function here
to a PRF, because the PRF is secure, the
adversary can't distinguish these two
bottom distributions, the left from the
right. And so by following these three
equalities, basically we have proven that
the things we wanted to prove equal are
actually computationally
indistinguishable. Okay, so that's a very
simply proof to show that deterministic
counter mode is in fact secure and it's
basically the same proof as we had when we
proved that a stream cipher gives us
semantic security. Okay. So that completes
this segment and in the next segment we'll
talk about modes that enable us to use a
key to encrypt multiple messages.