Now that we know that block cyphers are we
know how to construct them, let's see how
to use them for secure encryption? But
before that, I wanna briefly remind you of
an important abstraction called a
pseudo-random function, and a
pseudo-random permutation. So as we said
in the last module, a block cipher's map,
N bits of inputs to N bits of outputs. And
we saw two examples of block ciphers,
triple DES and AES. Now, an important
abstraction of the concept of a block
cipher, is captured by this idea of a PRP
and a PRF. And remember that a
pseudo-random function, a PRF, basically
is a function that takes two inputs. It
takes a key and an element in some set X.
And in outputs an element in some set Y
and for now the only requirement is that
there's an efficient algorithm to evaluate
this function. We're going to talk about
security for PRFs in just a minute. And
then similarly, there's a related concept
called a pseudo-random permutation, which
is similar to a PRF. In fact, there's also
an efficient algorithm to evaluate, the
pseudo-random permutation. However,
there's an additional requirement, that
there's also an algorithm D that will
invert this function E. So a PRP, is
basically a PRF, but where the function is
required to be one to one for all keys.
And there is an efficient inversion
algorithm. So now lets talk about how to
define secure PRF's. So we already said
that essentially the goal of a PRF is to
look like a random function from the set X
to Y. So to capture that more precisely we
define this notation, funs XY to be the
set of all functions from the set X, to
the set Y. Similarly, we defined the set S
sub F to be the set of all functions from
the set X to Y that are defined by the
PRF. In other words. Once you fix the key
K, you obtain a function from the set X to
the set Y. And the set of all such
functions, given a particular PRF, would
be the set S sub F. So as we said last
time, funs XY is generally a gigantic set
of all functions from S to Y. I think I
mentioned that, in fact, for AES, where X
and Y are two to the 128, the size of the
set is two to the 128 times two to the
128. It's a double exponential, which is
an absolutely enormous number. On the
other hand, the number of functions
defined by the AES block cipher is just
two to the hundred and twenty-eight.
Namely, one function from each key. And
what we would like to say is that a random
choice from this huge set is
indistinguishable from a random choice
from the small set. And what do we mean by
indistinguishable, we mean that an
adversary who can interact with a random
function in here, can't distinguish that
interaction from an interaction with a
random function in here. Now let's find
out more precisely. So we're gonna, as
usual, define two experiments. Experiment
zero and experiment one. And our goal is
to say that the adversary can't
distinguish these two experiments. So in
experiment zero, the challenger,
basically, is gonna choose a random,
pseudo-random function. Okay? So he's
gonna fix the key K at random, and that's
gonna define this function, little f over
here, to be one of the functions
implemented by the PRF. And experiment
one, on the other hand, the challenger is
gonna choose a truly random function from
the set X to the set Y. And again, we're
gonna call this truly random function
little f, either way, either experiment
zero or experiment one, the challenger
ends up with this little function f that's
either chosen from the PRF, or chosen as a
truly random function from X to Y. Now the
adversary basically gets to query this
function, little f. So he gets to submit a
query X1 and he obtains the value of f at
the point X1, then he gets to submit at
X2, and he obtains the value of f at the
point X2. So on and so fourth, he makes Q
queries. And so he learns the value of the
function little f at those Q points. Now
his goal is to say whether the function
little f is chosen truly at random from
funs XY, or chosen just from the set of
functions implemented by the PRF. So he
outputs a certain bit b prime and we'll
refer to that output as the output of
experiments, either as experiment zero or
experiment one. As usual we say that the
PRF is secure. If, in fact, the adversary
can't distinguish these two experiments.
In other words, the probability that he
outputs one, experiments zero is the same,
pretty much the same as the probability
that he outputs one in experiment one. In
other words, the difference of these two
probabilities is negligible. So this
captures nicely, the fact that the
adversary couldn't distinguish a
pseudo-random function from a truly random
function from the set X to Y. Now, the
definition for a secure pseudo-random
permutation, a secure PRP, which is
basically a secure block cipher, is pretty
much the same. In experiment zero, the
adversary's gonna change a random instance
of the PRP. So he's gonna choose a random
K, and define little f to be the function
that corresponds to little k within the
pseudo-random permutation. In experiment
one: the adversary is gonna choose not a
truly random function from X to Y, but a
truly random one to one function from X to
X. Okay? So the goal of our PRP is to look
like a random permutation from X to X.
Namely, a random one to one function from
the set X to itself. So the little
functional little f here is again gonna be
a random function. From the set X to
itself. And again, the challenger ends up
with this function, little f. As before,
the adversary gets to submit queries and
it gets to see the results of those
queries. And then he shouldn't be able to
distinguish, again, experiment zero from
experiment one. So again, given the value
of the function f at cue points chosen by
the adversary, he can't tell whether the
function f came from a PRP, or
whether it's a truly random permutation
from X to X. So let's look at a simple
example. Suppose the set X contains only
two points, zero and one. In this case,
Perms[X] is really easy to define.
Essentially, there are two points, and
we're looking at, you know, 01. And we're
asking, what is the set of all invertible
functions on the set 01. Well, there are
only two such functions. One function is
the identity function. And the other
function is basically the function that
does crossovers, namely this function
here. These are the only two invertible
functions in the set 01. So really, Perms[X]
only contains two functions, in this
case. Now, let's look at the following
PRP. The key space is gonna be 01, and of
course, X is gonna be 01. And let's define
the PRP as basically X XOR K. Okay so
that's our PRP and my question to you is,
is this a secure PRP. In other words, is
this PRP indistinguishable from a random
function on Perms[X]? I hope everybody
said, yes, because essentially, the sets
of functions implemented in this PRP, is
identical to the set of functions in Perms[X].
So a random choice of key here is
identical to a random choice of function
over here. And as a result, the two
distributions, either pseudo-random or
random, are identical. So clearly, an
adversary can't distinguish the two
distributions. Now, we already said that
we have a couple of examples of secure
PRPs triple DES and AES. And I just wanted
to mention that, if you want to make
things very concrete, here's a concrete
security assumptions about AES. Just to
give an example, say that all algorithms
had run in time 2^80 have advantage
against AES of utmost 2^-40. This
is, a reasonable assumption about AES, and
I just wanted to state it for
concreteness. So let's look at another
example. Consider again the PRP from the
previous question. Namely XX or K.
Remember the set X was just one bit,
namely the value zero and one. And this
time, we're asking, is this PRP a secure
PRF? In other words, is this PRP
indistinguishable from a random function
from X to X? Now, the set of random
functions from X to X, Funs[XX] in
this case, contains only four elements.
There are the two invertible functions,
which we already saw in... I believe the
identity function, and the negation
function, the function that
sends zero to one, and one to zero. But
there are two other functions. Namely, the
function that sends everything to zero.
And the function that sends everything to
one. Okay, these are four functions inside
Funs[XX], and the question is: Is this
PRP that we just looked at, is it also
indistinguishable from a random choice
from Funs[XX]? So I hope everybody said no
and the reason it's not a secure prf is
because there's a simple attack, namely
the attacker supposed to distinguish
whether he's interacting with this PRP or
is he interacting with a random function
from Funs[XX]. And the distinguisher
is very simple. Basically we're gonna
query the function at both x equals zero
and x equals one, and then if we get a
collision, in other words, if f of zero is
equal to f of one, then for sure we're not
interacting with a PRP. In which case we
can just output one. In other words we're
interacting with a random function. In
other words we say zero. So let's look at
the advantage of this distinguisher. Well
when it's interacting with a PRP, it'll
never output a one, because f of zero can
never be equal to f of one. In other
words, the probability of outputting one
is zero. However, when we interact with a
truly random function in Funs[XX],
the probability that f of zero is equal to
f of one is exactly one-half.  Cause half the
functions satisfy F of zero's equal to F
of one, and half the functions don't. So
then, we'll output one with probability
one-half. So the advantage of this
distinguisher is one-half, which is non-negligible.
And as a result, this PRP here
is not a secure PRF. Now it turns out this
only true because if set X is very small.
And in fact there is an important lemma,
called the PRF Switching Lemma, that
says that a secure PRP, is in fact a
secure PRF, whenever the set X is
sufficiently large. And by sufficiently
large, I mean say the output space of AES
which is two to the 128th. So by this
lemma which will state more precisely in a
second, AES if it's a secure PRP, it is
also a secure PRF. So this lemma basically
says the following, if you give me a PRP
over the set X Then for any adversary that
queries the PRP, at at most Q points, so it
makes at most Q queries into the
challenge function. Then, the difference
between its advantage in attacking the PRP
when compared to a random function, is
very close to its advantage in
distinguishing the PRP from a random
permutation. In fact the difference, is
bounded by this quantity here, and since
we said that X is very large, this
quantity Q squared over 2X is negligible.
Okay. That's gonna be our goal. So
essentially, again, when X is large, say
two to the 128, Q say is going to be two
to the 32. That's a billion queries that
the adversary makes. Then, still the ratio
is going to be negligible. In which case,
we say that the adversary's advantage is
distinguishing the PRP from a random
function. It's pretty much the same as its
advantage of distinguishing a PRP from a
random permutation. So, again, it's
basically, if E is already a secure PRP,
then it's already a secure PRF. So for
AES, AES, we believe, is a secure PRP.
And therefore, AES, we can also use it as a
secure PRF. And so, as a final note, I
just want to mention that, really, from
now on, you can kinda forget about the
inner workings of AES and triple DES.
We're simply gonna assume that both are
secure PRPs, and then we're gonna see how
to use them. But whenever I say PRP, or
PRF, you should be thinking in your mind,
basically, AES or triple DES.